<TEI.2><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Math methods final reflection</title><author>anonymized</author></titleStmt><wordcount>669</wordcount><editionStmt><edition>Version 1.0</edition></editionStmt><extent>insert_extent</extent><publicationStmt><idno>EDU.G0.14.1</idno><publisher>The University of Michigan</publisher><pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan, USA</pubPlace><date>2007</date><availability><p>The MICUSP project is owned by the Regents of the University of Michigan, who hold the copyright. The database has been developed by the English Language Institute. The original text submissions are stored electronically in the English Language Institute and may be consulted by bona fide researchers under special arrangements. The database is available by password on the World Wide Web for study, teaching and research purposes. Copies of the text files may be distributed, as long as either this statement of availability or the citation given below appears in the text. However, if any portion of this material is to be used for commercial purposes, such as for textbooks or tests, permission must be obtained in advance and a license fee may be required. For further information about copyright permissions, please inquire at micusp@umich.edu.</p><p>The recommended citation for MICASE is: Ädel, A., J. M. Swales, and J. Sielaff. (2007) The Michigan Corpus of Upper-level Student Papers. Ann Arbor, MI: The Regents of the University of Michigan.</p></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>The Michigan Corpus of Upper-level Student Papers (MICUSP)</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><p>This document derives from an unpublished, student-authored paper contributed in electronic format.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>For information on corpus compilation and encoding practices, see the MICUSP Handbook.</p></projectDesc><classDecl><taxonomy><category><catDesc>departments</catDesc><category id="BIO"><catDesc>Biology</catDesc></category><category id="CEE"><catDesc>Civil and Environmental Engineering</catDesc></category><category id="CLS"><catDesc>Classical Studies</catDesc></category><category id="ECO"><catDesc>Economics</catDesc></category><category id="EDU"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category id="ENG"><catDesc>English</catDesc></category><category id="IOE"><catDesc>Industrial and Operational Engineering</catDesc></category><category id="LIN"><catDesc>Linguistics</catDesc></category><category id="MEC"><catDesc>Mechanical Engineering</catDesc></category><category id="NRE"><catDesc>Natural Resources</catDesc></category><category id="NUR"><catDesc>Nursing</catDesc></category><category id="PHI"><catDesc>Philosophy</catDesc></category><category id="PHY"><catDesc>Physics</catDesc></category><category id="POL"><catDesc>Political Science</catDesc></category><category id="PSY"><catDesc>Psychology</catDesc></category><category id="SOC"><catDesc>Sociology</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>student levels</catDesc><category id="G0"><catDesc>senior undergraduate</catDesc></category><category id="G1"><catDesc>first-year graduate</catDesc></category><category id="G2"><catDesc>second-year graduate</catDesc></category><category id="G3"><catDesc>third-year graduate and up</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>student-reported text types</catDesc><category id="CaseStudy"><catDesc>case study</catDesc></category><category id="Critique"><catDesc>critique</catDesc></category><category id="LiteratureReview"><catDesc>literature review</catDesc></category><category id="ResearchProposal"><catDesc>research proposal</catDesc></category><category id="ResponsePaper"><catDesc>response paper</catDesc></category><category id="TechnicalOrLabReport"><catDesc>technical report or lab report</catDesc></category><category id="TermPaper"><catDesc>term paper</catDesc></category><category id="OtherTextType"><catDesc>other</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>approximate preparation times</catDesc><category id="OneToThreeDays"><catDesc>1-3 days</catDesc></category><category id="FourToTenDays"><catDesc>4-10 days</catDesc></category><category id="TwoToThreeWeeks"><catDesc>2-3 weeks</catDesc></category><category id="ThreeToSixWeeks"><catDesc>3-6 weeks</catDesc></category><category id="OneFullSemester"><catDesc>one full semester</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>sources of feedback</catDesc><category id="NoFeedback"><catDesc>no feedback from others</catDesc></category><category id="PrimaryInstructor"><catDesc>primary course instructor</catDesc></category><category id="GSI"><catDesc>Graduate Student Instructor (teaching assistant)</catDesc></category><category id="WritingTutor"><catDesc>writing tutor</catDesc></category><category id="FriendOrClassmate"><catDesc>friend or classmate</catDesc></category><category id="OtherFeedback"><catDesc>other</catDesc></category></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><creation>Paper submitted to instructor in Dec 2007</creation><particDesc><person id="P363" sex="f" age="TwentyToTwentyThree"><affiliation>Education</affiliation><firstLang>English</firstLang><dominantLang>English</dominantLang><englishInPrimarySchool value="YES"/><englishInSecondarySchool value="YES"/><englishInUndergraduate value="YES"/></person></particDesc><textClass><catRef target="EDU G0 ResponsePaper ResponsePaper OneToThreeDays PrimaryInstructor"><classification><primary>Response Paper</primary><secondary/></classification><classification><primary>Response Paper</primary><secondary/></classification><features> </features></catRef></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change><date>2008-10-22</date><respStmt><name>Emily Lin</name><resp>coder</resp></respStmt><item>manual adjustment of tags</item></change><change><date>2007-05-22</date><respStmt><name>Gregory Garretson</name><resp>programmer</resp></respStmt><item>initial (automated) encoding in XML</item></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="opener"><head>Learning and professional growth: Committing to the learning and achievement of all students</head><p/></div><div type="main"><p>In the beginning of this course, I was equipped with minimal strategies for ensuring that each and every student in my classroom will succeed in mathematics.  I knew that it was important to provide students with equal opportunities; I understood that managing and maintaining a classroom of individuals was a necessary consideration in planning and enacting lessons.  Through the work in this course, I was able to acquire specific strategies and approaches that will help me to develop equitable opportunity for all of my students.</p><p>	In September, one assignment was to read Chapter 5 in our Classroom Discussions text, which outlined <q type="quote">solution methods and problem-solving strategies.</q>  I took note of these specific strategies and gave summaries of each, but I was unable to put the strategies into practice until much later in the term.  In the same assignment, I read <q type="title">Addition and Subtraction</q> by Carpenter and reflected in my notebook upon the main themes and ideas that coursed throughout both texts.</p><p><q type="studentVoice">Understanding the different ways that students solve problems will contribute to my work in helping students refine and concretize their ideas.  This is especially important when students are using ineffective strategies for problems that require larger numbers or grouping.  Being able to highlight certain strategies that "appear" (strategies that are, in reality, coached out of student work) in discussions about different problems will help students acquire more strategies for problem solving. </q></p><p>My response was general and vague; what strategies did I mean?  What does an <q type="quote">ineffective strategy</q> look like?  Generalizations such as creating equal opportunities for students based on the different ways students approach mathematics are present in my reflection, but in September, I was unable to articulate the different ways that I can build upon students' ideas and coax their confidence as mathematical thinkers.</p><p>	A renewed understanding of ways to commit to the achievement of all students came with the student interview(s) I enacted mid-semester.  Having to conduct two interviews was a hidden blessing; I became more aware of the vast differences between my two students in the way that they approached math.  Developmentally, the two students were about equal; they had a good grasp of a one-to-one correspondence between numbers and objects and the basic strategies for addition and rebundling.  However, when I presented more difficult tasks, the outcomes were very different for the two students.  These interviews helped me to realize that in my lessons, I must attend to the existing ideas students have about mathematical concepts in order to build their knowledge, and I must do this in ways that encourage <i>all</i> students to learn.   </p><p>	Another way in which I have grown in the area of committing to the learning and achievement of all students is in my analysis of student errors.  In class, our first analysis of errors was in subtraction, and my responses were, again, vague:  <q type="studentVoice">While it is difficult to see the students' thought process with this problem, it is clear that the student does not have a clear grasp of what answer would make sense.</q>  My analyses of errors in division were more developed and less presumptuous; I approached each problem under the assumption that each student went through the problem in a way that made sense to them, and that I could uncover the meaning behind errors rather than just point out the obvious mistake.  The circulating assignment also helped me to record and reflect on students' individual responses to problems.  I noticed that many of the students seemed disengaged from the math work, either working hurriedly to finish or working nonchalantly and in a disconnected way, while other students were treating the workbook problems as carefully and meticulously as they could.  My records allowed me to look back and see much more than what students accomplished; they show me the students' individual attitudes toward math, and they show me ways that I can best attend to each of their individual needs as a teacher.</p></div><div type="closer"><p/></div></body></text></TEI.2>