<TEI.2><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Lesson reflection (class on cloud types)</title><author>anonymized</author></titleStmt><wordcount>692</wordcount><editionStmt><edition>Version 1.0</edition></editionStmt><extent>insert_extent</extent><publicationStmt><idno>EDU.G0.16.1</idno><publisher>The University of Michigan</publisher><pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan, USA</pubPlace><date>2007</date><availability><p>The MICUSP project is owned by the Regents of the University of Michigan, who hold the copyright. The database has been developed by the English Language Institute. The original text submissions are stored electronically in the English Language Institute and may be consulted by bona fide researchers under special arrangements. The database is available by password on the World Wide Web for study, teaching and research purposes. Copies of the text files may be distributed, as long as either this statement of availability or the citation given below appears in the text. However, if any portion of this material is to be used for commercial purposes, such as for textbooks or tests, permission must be obtained in advance and a license fee may be required. For further information about copyright permissions, please inquire at micusp@umich.edu.</p><p>The recommended citation for MICASE is: Ädel, A., J. M. Swales, and J. Sielaff. (2007) The Michigan Corpus of Upper-level Student Papers. Ann Arbor, MI: The Regents of the University of Michigan.</p></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>The Michigan Corpus of Upper-level Student Papers (MICUSP)</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><p>This document derives from an unpublished, student-authored paper contributed in electronic format.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>For information on corpus compilation and encoding practices, see the MICUSP Handbook.</p></projectDesc><classDecl><taxonomy><category><catDesc>departments</catDesc><category id="BIO"><catDesc>Biology</catDesc></category><category id="CEE"><catDesc>Civil and Environmental Engineering</catDesc></category><category id="CLS"><catDesc>Classical Studies</catDesc></category><category id="ECO"><catDesc>Economics</catDesc></category><category id="EDU"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category id="ENG"><catDesc>English</catDesc></category><category id="IOE"><catDesc>Industrial and Operational Engineering</catDesc></category><category id="LIN"><catDesc>Linguistics</catDesc></category><category id="MEC"><catDesc>Mechanical Engineering</catDesc></category><category id="NRE"><catDesc>Natural Resources</catDesc></category><category id="NUR"><catDesc>Nursing</catDesc></category><category id="PHI"><catDesc>Philosophy</catDesc></category><category id="PHY"><catDesc>Physics</catDesc></category><category id="POL"><catDesc>Political Science</catDesc></category><category id="PSY"><catDesc>Psychology</catDesc></category><category id="SOC"><catDesc>Sociology</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>student levels</catDesc><category id="G0"><catDesc>senior undergraduate</catDesc></category><category id="G1"><catDesc>first-year graduate</catDesc></category><category id="G2"><catDesc>second-year graduate</catDesc></category><category id="G3"><catDesc>third-year graduate and up</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>student-reported text types</catDesc><category id="CaseStudy"><catDesc>case study</catDesc></category><category id="Critique"><catDesc>critique</catDesc></category><category id="LiteratureReview"><catDesc>literature review</catDesc></category><category id="ResearchProposal"><catDesc>research proposal</catDesc></category><category id="ResponsePaper"><catDesc>response paper</catDesc></category><category id="TechnicalOrLabReport"><catDesc>technical report or lab report</catDesc></category><category id="TermPaper"><catDesc>term paper</catDesc></category><category id="OtherTextType"><catDesc>other</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>approximate preparation times</catDesc><category id="OneToThreeDays"><catDesc>1-3 days</catDesc></category><category id="FourToTenDays"><catDesc>4-10 days</catDesc></category><category id="TwoToThreeWeeks"><catDesc>2-3 weeks</catDesc></category><category id="ThreeToSixWeeks"><catDesc>3-6 weeks</catDesc></category><category id="OneFullSemester"><catDesc>one full semester</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>sources of feedback</catDesc><category id="NoFeedback"><catDesc>no feedback from others</catDesc></category><category id="PrimaryInstructor"><catDesc>primary course instructor</catDesc></category><category id="GSI"><catDesc>Graduate Student Instructor (teaching assistant)</catDesc></category><category id="WritingTutor"><catDesc>writing tutor</catDesc></category><category id="FriendOrClassmate"><catDesc>friend or classmate</catDesc></category><category id="OtherFeedback"><catDesc>other</catDesc></category></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><creation>Paper submitted to instructor in Nov 2007</creation><particDesc><person id="P370" sex="f" age="TwentyToTwentyThree"><affiliation>Elementary Education</affiliation><firstLang>English</firstLang><dominantLang>English</dominantLang><englishInPrimarySchool value="YES"/><englishInSecondarySchool value="YES"/><englishInUndergraduate value="YES"/></person></particDesc><textClass><catRef target="EDU G0 ResponsePaper ResponsePaper OneToThreeDays FriendOrClassmate"><classification><primary>Response Paper</primary><secondary/></classification><classification><primary>Response Paper</primary><secondary/></classification><features> </features></catRef></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change><date>2008-10-22</date><respStmt><name>Emily Lin</name><resp>coder</resp></respStmt><item>manual adjustment of tags</item></change><change><date>2007-05-22</date><respStmt><name>Gregory Garretson</name><resp>programmer</resp></respStmt><item>initial (automated) encoding in XML</item></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="opener"><head>Reflection</head><p/></div><div type="main"><p>      The most important criteria in determining the strength of my lesson is whether or not my students learned. In order to determine whether my students met the learning goals of this lesson, I will select a base of worksheets which seem representative of the entire group and analyze them in relation to the learning goals. As a reminder, the learning goals for this lesson are:</p><list><item>1. Students will be able to list certain characteristics of each of the three basic cloud types.</item><item>2. Students will be able to understand why such knowledge is important and relatable to the work of a meteorologist. </item><item>3. Students will be able to make observations about the different cloud shapes and apply them as evidence during assessment. </item></list><p>	In terms of learning goal two, I analyzed this knowledge through an informal verbal assessment. Specifically, during the introduction we had a whole-class discussion as to the purpose for studying clouds and their shape. Here, we came to the conclusion that meteorologists study clouds in order to predict and analyze the weather. Later, during the conclusion of the lesson, we revisited this comment by discussing what we did for science and why. Although not all students specifically stated this purpose, they either gave their own reasonable purposes or a purpose related to that formed in the introduction. Therefore, I have concluded that students did achieve learning goal two.</p><p>	In terms of learning goals one and three, I analyzed this knowledge through a formal assessment within my worksheet. On the student worksheet, I asked children to make their own observations in the spaces allotted as we skimmed through the projections. This would achieve learning goal one in that students were given the opportunity to list their own characteristics of each of the three basic cloud types. However, they were not given any guidance as to what to look for during these observation periods and therefore most observations were not related to the characteristics of the cloud itself. For example, student one wrote observations such as: there are shapes out of them, light blue, and kind of cloudy. Student two appears to have erased her initial observations and replaced them with those written on the chart paper. She wrote: wispy, puffy, and flat. Student three appears to have made the single observation: I see pictures. Later in the lesson, we had a whole-class discussion about the names and characteristics of each type of cloud. Then, students were expected to record and list these on their worksheets. This would achieve learning goal one in that students were given the opportunity to list characteristics of each of the three basic cloud types. Most students listed the cloud-type and their characteristics together (cirrus-wispy, cumulus-puffy, stratus-flat), which would facilitate the association process. For example, students one and two wrote the name and characteristic together in a format such as: cumulus puffy, cirrus wispy, stratus flat. From this evidence, I would conclude that students have learned that there are, in fact, different types of clouds, but are only in the beginning stages of matching cloud type with their defining characteristics. </p><p>	During the conclusion of the main lesson, students were asked to identify the cloud-type depicted in a fourth projection and explain why they reached their particular conclusion. This would achieve learning goal three in that students would apply their learning about cloud types as evidence during a formal assessment. Students were allowed to use the information recorded on their worksheets and resources around the room to reach a conclusion. Students one, two, and three reached the conclusion that a cumulus cloud was shown on the projector, which is correct. However, only student one listed a reason for her answer by writing the word, puffy. So, although many students listed cumulus as their answer, most did not list a reason for their response. From this evidence, I would conclude that students have learned how to apply observations in order to formulate answers, but have not learned how to explain their answers using evidence. Such limited explanations could also be due in part to a lack of emphasis on this task and a limited capacity to put thoughts into words.</p></div><div type="closer"><p/></div></body></text></TEI.2>