<TEI.2><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>A Battle to Remember? Arrian's Ectaxis contra Alanos</title><author>anonymized</author></titleStmt><wordcount>6093</wordcount><editionStmt><edition>Version 1.0</edition></editionStmt><extent>insert_extent</extent><publicationStmt><idno>HIS.G1.09.1</idno><publisher>The University of Michigan</publisher><pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan, USA</pubPlace><date>2007</date><availability><p>The MICUSP project is owned by the Regents of the University of Michigan, who hold the copyright. The database has been developed by the English Language Institute. The original text submissions are stored electronically in the English Language Institute and may be consulted by bona fide researchers under special arrangements. The database is available by password on the World Wide Web for study, teaching and research purposes. Copies of the text files may be distributed, as long as either this statement of availability or the citation given below appears in the text. However, if any portion of this material is to be used for commercial purposes, such as for textbooks or tests, permission must be obtained in advance and a license fee may be required. For further information about copyright permissions, please inquire at micusp@umich.edu.</p><p>The recommended citation for MICASE is: Ädel, A., J. M. Swales, and J. Sielaff. (2007) The Michigan Corpus of Upper-level Student Papers. Ann Arbor, MI: The Regents of the University of Michigan.</p></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>The Michigan Corpus of Upper-level Student Papers (MICUSP)</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><p>This document derives from an unpublished, student-authored paper contributed in electronic format.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>For information on corpus compilation and encoding practices, see the MICUSP Handbook.</p></projectDesc><classDecl><taxonomy><category><catDesc>departments</catDesc><category id="BIO"><catDesc>Biology</catDesc></category><category id="CEE"><catDesc>Civil and Environmental Engineering</catDesc></category><category id="CLS"><catDesc>Classical Studies</catDesc></category><category id="ECO"><catDesc>Economics</catDesc></category><category id="EDU"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category id="ENG"><catDesc>English</catDesc></category><category id="IOE"><catDesc>Industrial and Operational Engineering</catDesc></category><category id="LIN"><catDesc>Linguistics</catDesc></category><category id="MEC"><catDesc>Mechanical Engineering</catDesc></category><category id="NRE"><catDesc>Natural Resources</catDesc></category><category id="NUR"><catDesc>Nursing</catDesc></category><category id="PHI"><catDesc>Philosophy</catDesc></category><category id="PHY"><catDesc>Physics</catDesc></category><category id="POL"><catDesc>Political Science</catDesc></category><category id="PSY"><catDesc>Psychology</catDesc></category><category id="SOC"><catDesc>Sociology</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>student levels</catDesc><category id="G0"><catDesc>senior undergraduate</catDesc></category><category id="G1"><catDesc>first-year graduate</catDesc></category><category id="G2"><catDesc>second-year graduate</catDesc></category><category id="G3"><catDesc>third-year graduate and up</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>student-reported text types</catDesc><category id="CaseStudy"><catDesc>case study</catDesc></category><category id="Critique"><catDesc>critique</catDesc></category><category id="LiteratureReview"><catDesc>literature review</catDesc></category><category id="ResearchProposal"><catDesc>research proposal</catDesc></category><category id="ResponsePaper"><catDesc>response paper</catDesc></category><category id="TechnicalOrLabReport"><catDesc>technical report or lab report</catDesc></category><category id="TermPaper"><catDesc>term paper</catDesc></category><category id="OtherTextType"><catDesc>other</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>approximate preparation times</catDesc><category id="OneToThreeDays"><catDesc>1-3 days</catDesc></category><category id="FourToTenDays"><catDesc>4-10 days</catDesc></category><category id="TwoToThreeWeeks"><catDesc>2-3 weeks</catDesc></category><category id="ThreeToSixWeeks"><catDesc>3-6 weeks</catDesc></category><category id="OneFullSemester"><catDesc>one full semester</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>sources of feedback</catDesc><category id="NoFeedback"><catDesc>no feedback from others</catDesc></category><category id="PrimaryInstructor"><catDesc>primary course instructor</catDesc></category><category id="GSI"><catDesc>Graduate Student Instructor (teaching assistant)</catDesc></category><category id="WritingTutor"><catDesc>writing tutor</catDesc></category><category id="FriendOrClassmate"><catDesc>friend or classmate</catDesc></category><category id="OtherFeedback"><catDesc>other</catDesc></category></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><creation>Paper submitted to instructor in Dec 2008</creation><particDesc><person id="P652" sex="m" age="TwentyFourToThirty"><affiliation>Classical Studies</affiliation><firstLang>English</firstLang><dominantLang>English</dominantLang><englishInPrimarySchool value="NO"/><englishInSecondarySchool value="NO"/><englishInUndergraduate value="NO"/><langKnown>\N</langKnown></person></particDesc><textClass><catRef target="HIS G1 Report TermPaper TwoToThreeWeeks NoFeedback"><classification><primary>Report</primary><secondary/></classification><classification><primary>Report</primary><secondary/></classification><features><feature type="Literature review section"/><feature type="Reference to sources"/></features></catRef></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change><date>2009-07-16</date><respStmt><name>Lucas Jarmin</name><resp>coder</resp></respStmt><item>manual adjustment of tags</item></change><change><date>2007-05-22</date><respStmt><name>Gregory Garretson</name><resp>programmer</resp></respStmt><item>initial (automated) encoding in XML</item></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="opener"><head>﻿A Battle to Remember? Arrian's <i>Ectaxis contra Alanos</i></head><p/></div><div type="main"><p>      Oliver L. Spaulding, Jr., a colonel in the U.S. army specializing in field artillery and a professor of military science at Harvard University, wrote in the early twentieth century about the utility of ancient military treatises in modern warfare.  Napoleon, Spaulding claims, said <q type="quote">that the military art is to be learned from history, not from modern history alone....On unimpeachable authority [i.e., Napoleon’s], then, we may say that there is something in ancient campaigns that is of value to the modern; that there is something immutable in the midst of the changes in the methods of war; that, in fact, <q>plus ça change, plus ça reste la même chose.</q></q><ptr type="footnote" target="fn1"/>  While it is debatable how useful ancient military treatises are for conducting modern warfare, the nature of these works suggests that the Romans, at least, believed that they had <q type="quote">something…of value.</q>  For the Romans regarded both the historical exempla contained in these treatises as well as, to a certain degree, the technical descriptions of maneuvers and tactics as good models for military behavior and generalship.  To what extent these treatises shaped the actual battle tactics of Roman generals is unclear;<ptr type="footnote" target="fn2"/> nevertheless, to suggest that they were merely antiquarian fabrications full of outdated maneuvers and moralistic adages may be somewhat misleading.</p><p>      In his overview of surviving works of ancient military writers, Spaulding passes over one piece of literature which other scholars have tended to group with military handbooks.  While far from being a normal didactic technical treatise on tactics or generalship, the <i type="title">Order of Battle against the Alani</i> (Ἒκταξις κατὰ Ἀλανῶν), written by L. Flavius Arrianus in c.135 CE, nevertheless offers a unique insight on the Roman army.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn3"/>  A brief piece, full of frustrating lacunae, the <i type="title">Ectaxis</i> provides the marching order and disposition of Roman troops as they prepare to engage an oncoming assault of enemy cavalry.  The work has generated a strong debate among scholars regarding its literary nature, its purpose, and its implication for the history of Roman military tactical development.  It is the goal of this paper to consider these questions, to explore the historical background of the <i type="title">Ectaxis</i>, and to investigate to what extent it can tell us about the Roman army in the second century CE.  While no clear consensus has emerged regarding these difficult questions, nevertheless most scholars agree that Arrian’s <i type="title">Ectaxis</i>, the only surviving detailed account of the disposition of troops written by a Roman military commander, remains an essential source for an insider’s look at Roman warfare.  </p><div type="head_1"><head>The author and his work</head><p>      The <i type="title">Ectaxis contra Alanos</i> was written by Arrian in c.135 CE while he was serving as governor-legate of Cappadocia.  Before obtaining this position in c.131 CE, Arrian led a remarkable career for a Greek provincial in the Roman administration.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn4"/>  Born and raised in Nicomedia, the capital of the province of Bithynia in Asia Minor, Lucius Flavius Arrianus grew up in family of wealth and influence, probably associated with the municipal aristocracy.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn5"/>  His family most likely had obtained Roman citizenship through the influence of L. Flavius, a suffect consul in 33 BCE and a follower of Mark Antony in the east.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn6"/>  Born between 85 and 90 CE, Arrian studied under the Stoic philosopher Epictetus at Nicopolis in Epirus, probably at age eighteen. During his time there, or perhaps a bit later, Arrian collected and published the talks of his master.  Of this collection of eight books, only four survive today.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn7"/></p><p>	Following his time in Epirus, the exact path of Arrian’s career becomes unclear.  He probably held some sort of military position as a young man, perhaps serving as an equestrian <i type="foreign">praefectus cohortis</i> or legionary tribune during Trajan’s Dacian Wars.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn8"/>  He may also have served in Trajan’s army in Armenia and Parthia; however, the source for this conjecture is less than perfect.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn9"/>  Arrian seems to have been adlected into the Roman senate soon after Hadrian became emperor, perhaps due to an earlier meeting in Athens c.112/113 CE.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn10"/>  It is also possible that his father had been a member of the senate and that Arrian simply followed the normal <i type="foreign">cursus honorum</i>.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn11"/>  During Hadrian’s reign, Arrian obtained the praetorship, and sometime after, perhaps c.125 CE, he held the propraetorship of the unarmed province of Baetica in Spain.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn12"/>  He then served as suffect consul in 129 or 130 CE.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn13"/>  Due in part to his prior military service, as well as his connection to the emperor, Arrian became governor (<i type="foreign">legatus Augusti pro praetore</i>) of Cappadocia and held office from c.131 to 137 CE.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn14"/></p><p>      Cappadocia, located along the northeast frontier of the empire, bordered the Caucasus Mountains and the Black Sea in the north, the Euphrates in the east, and Syria in the south.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn15"/>  The province bordered on the client kingdoms of Armenia, Iberia, and Albania, as well as the Parthian Empire to the south and east.  To the north, in the Caucasus Mountains, numerous mountain tribes dwelled, and beyond the mountains was the homeland of the Sarmatian tribe, the Alani.  As legate of this frontier province, Arrian had the task of defending the borders from any incursions.  To accomplish this, Arrian held two legions under his command, XV Apollinaris (stationed at Satala) and XII Fulminata (stationed at Melitene), as well as auxiliaries and natives troops.<ptr type="foreign" target="fn16"/></p><p>      In addition to serving as general of the military forces of the province, another task of the governor was to inspect the troops and various outposts throughout the region.  Hadrian himself had done this, and Arrian took up where the emperor had left off.  As shown in his <i type="title">Periplus Ponti Euxini</i> (<i type="title">Circumnavigation of the Black Sea</i>), Arrian had sailed north and east from Trapezus along the coast of the Black Sea, going as far as Dioscurias Sebastopolis, during which time he stopped at various forts, inspected troops, talked to client tribes, and took note of interesting works of art.  He returned to the heart of his province upon hearing of the death of the Bosporan king Cotys (131/32 CE).  Arrian reported his findings to the emperor, in Latin;<ptr type="footnote" target="fn17"/> however, he also included the <i type="title">Periplus</i>, a literary supplement written in Greek, which was <q type="quote">written in a more personal tone than one would expect in an official report, omitting details of the results of the inspection, but adding information on the rest of the circuit of the sea, and sent in the form of a letter.</q>18  It has been suggested that the <i type="title">Ectaxis</i>, like the <i type="title">Periplus</i>, was also a literary accompaniment to an official report.19  This and other possibilities for the nature of the <i type="title">Ectaxis</i> will be analyzed below.  First, let us turn to Arrian’s encounter (if any) with the Alani.</p></div><div type="head_1"><head>The <q>invasion</q> of the Alani</head><p>      Our main source for the Alani assault on Roman territory is provided by Cassius Dio:</p><p><q type="quote">The war of the Jews ended at this time [summer 135 CE], but another war, this one of the Alani (they are Massagetai), was incited by Pharasmanes [II, king of Iberia]. The war greatly harassed Albania and Media [Atropatene], touching upon Armenia and Cappadocia. Then, since the Alani were persuaded by the bribes of Vologaeses [II of Parthia], and since they were also afraid of Flavius Arrianus, the governor of Cappadocia, the war ended.</q><ptr type="footnote" target="fn20"/></p><p>There is no hint here that the Alani made any major incursion into Cappadocia.  Rather, it seems as if Arrian scared them away before they could cause major damage.  Arrian’s <q type="quote">battle</q> might have merely been a show of force rather than a major encounter.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn21"/>  The Alani were not a major threat to Rome; in fact, it seems as though the Alani only caused trouble when bribed by others.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn22"/>  Rome had been in contact with the kingdoms of the Caucasus region, including Armenia, Albania, and Iberia, since at the least the time of Pompey.  By the reign of Trajan, Rome controlled the Caucasus kingdoms with puppet kings.  However, with the death of Trajan and the withdrawal of the empire in the East, Pharasmanes II, king of Iberia, became more independent, refusing to meet with Hadrian when the emperor was touring Cappadocia in 131 CE.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn23"/>  The king’s boldness induced him to seek the help of the Alani in raiding his neighbors, perhaps as a way to test the extent of Rome’s influence in the region.  However, neither Parthia nor Rome would allow this incursion to continue, and the Alani threat was quelled by a simple bribe and a show of force.</p><p>	Arrian describes what this <q type="quote">show of force</q> may have looked like in the <i type="title">Ectaxis</i>.  The work is divided into three main parts.  The first part outlines the marching order of the army (1-11).  The second part describes the disposition of the forces as they ready for battle (11-24).  The third part shows what should happen in battle during the expected cavalry frontal assault (24-6).  The plan calls for this assault to be routed, leading to a pursuit of the enemy (26-29), but, if the enemy should try to outflank the troops, the plan outlines how the reserve troops, particularly the auxiliary cavalry, should respond (30-1).  Unfortunately the text breaks off here.  It is difficult to determine how much of the text is missing, and it is also recognized that the text is quite lacunose.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn24"/></p><p>	  The army described by Arrian consisted of the legion XV Apollinaris, a <i type="foreign">vexillatio</i> of the legion XII Fulminata, various groups of auxiliary, as well as local militia from Lesser Armenia, Trapezus, Colchis, and Rhizus.  The military force totaled anywhere between 11,000 to 28,000 men.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn25"/>  Nearly all of the legions and auxiliary forces can be identified with some certainty.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn26"/>  Where the battle was to take place is unclear; the text only suggests that the forces were arranged in a wide, flat area, with higher ground on either flank of the main force.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn27"/>  Since the Alani were coming from Albania and Media, it seems prudent to suggest that Arrian had his forces aligned somewhere near the border, perhaps on a road in a mountain pass near Satala in Lesser Armenia, where the legion XV Apollinaris was stationed.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn28"/></p><p>	While it is correct to keep in mind that an army’s marching disposition tended to reflect the climate, terrain, and tactical needs of the time,<ptr type="footnote" target="fn29"/> the marching order outlined by Arrian seems generally to correspond with other accounts of Roman marches.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn30"/>  Nevertheless, there are some differences.  Arrian has the main column of infantry surrounded by parallel lines of cavalry in order to protect the flanks.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn31"/>  He also has archers placed at the head of each group.  This disposition of cavalry and archers, combined with the infantry marching at four men abreast,<ptr type="footnote" target="fn32"/> suggests that Arrian was concerned with being outflanked or ambushed.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn33"/>  Arrian also arranged the infantry in this way to facilitate the shift from a marching column to a battle line. The first half of the marching order for each legion and auxiliary unit were long-range fighters, either archers or spearmen, while the second half were short-range fighters, such as heavy infantry.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn34"/>  In case of an attack, or when the army finally reached its destination, the first half of each respective group could easily halt and get into position, while the second half, the short-range fighters, would then line up parallel in front of them, with the result being four ranks of short-range fighters, followed by four ranks of long-range fighters.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn35"/>  This could easily be accomplished in short order by using signals and/or words of command.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn36"/></p><p>	Once in position, Arrian’s army was ready to withstand a frontal assault of heavy cavalry.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn37"/>  The Sarmatian Alani tended to attack on horseback, wear heavy armor, and use lances or broadswords.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn38"/>  Arrian planned to arrange his troops with such an attack in mind, with the two legions of heavy infantry positioned in the center and acting as a defensive base (<i type="foreign">probole</i>), backed by foot and cavalry archers, as well as artillery.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn39"/>  The auxiliary units were positioned similarly on the wings, with infantry in the front, archers/spearman in the back.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn40"/> These units were ordered to maintain the high ground on each wing and to shower the enemy with arrows and spears, thereby forcing the oncoming enemy straight into the wall of legionaries.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn41"/>  Cavalry also guarded the wings, in case the oncoming enemy attempted to circle around the front line; if they did, the cavalry were to attack with melee weapons, striking at the unprotected thighs and bellies of the Alani riders and their horses.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn42"/>  Arrian’s expectation was for the long-range missile attacks of spears, stones, catapults, and arrows to deter the cavalry from even making it to the line, as the heavily concentrated rain of projectiles would <q type="quote">throw the horses into confusion and bring destruction to the enemy cavalry.</q><ptr type="footnote" target="fn43"/>  Once the enemy was repelled and began to retreat, the infantry lines would open up, allowing half of the cavalry to pursue the fleeing Alani at full speed, the other half to follow in good order.  At the same time, archers and spearmen would advance at a run, with the infantry following at a quick walk, in order to provide a defensive base in case the enemy doubled-back.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn44"/></p><p>      Whether or not this battle order actually went into action, of course, cannot be proven.  However, as suggested by Dio, it seems that Alani were repulsed in some way, most likely through a show of force on Arrian’s part.  It has been suggested that Arrian may have used this opportunity to settle affairs with the Iberian kingdom, in order to make the region more <q type="quote">receptive</q> to Roman hegemony.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn45"/>  Pharasmanes, the king of Iberia, appears to be more subservient after this incident; in return for his obeisance, he gets the <q type="quote">privilege</q> of supporting a <i type="foreign">quingenaria cohors</i> in his kingdom.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn46"/>  A bilingual inscription (Greek and Aramaic) found at Mcheta (Harmozica), in ancient Iberia, points to a man with a Roman name serving as a high official in the court of the Pharasmanes, suggesting an even greater Roman influence during or after Arrian’s tenure.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn47"/>  It was the expansion of influence in the Caucasus kingdoms, rather than the defeat of the Alani, that seems to be Arrian’s main achievement as governor.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn48"/></p></div><div type="head_1"><head>Arrian’s tactics?</head><p>	A few scholars argue, some more vehemently than others, that Arrian’s infantry tactics are evidence of the Roman army’s occasional use of a phalangical formation, similar to, but not necessarily based on, that of the Macedonian army of Alexander the Great.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn49"/>  The use of this formation can be traced back to Republican times, similar, in essence, to the <i type="foreign">testudo</i><q type="term">turtleshell</q> formation used by Crassus at Carrhae and Antony in his Parthian campaign.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn50"/>  Arrian, in an unusual fashion, calls his legion a phalanx,<ptr type="footnote" target="fn51"/> and his <q type="quote">closely packed</q> (πυκνὴ) formation of eight ranks deep<ptr type="footnote" target="fn52"/> is highly suggestive of the <i type="foreign">puknosis</i> of the Hellenistic phalanx, while his <q type="quote">most concentrated</q> (πυκνοτάτη) formation, with the men standing shoulder to shoulder, with shields locked together,<ptr type="footnote" target="fn53"/> is suggestive of the <i type="foreign">synaspimos</i> of the Hellenistic phalanx.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn54"/>  Unlike the Hellenistic phalanx, however, it appears that Arrian’s <q type="quote">most concentrated</q> formation is primarily a defensive maneuver, used particularly against cavalry charges.  Also, the infantry are not uniformly equipped, with the front four ranks using pikes (κοντοί) and the back four ranks using spears or javelins (λογχοί).<ptr type="footnote" target="fn55"/>  Nevertheless, this close formation did not prevent flexibility, for if the enemy were to flee, the infantry could easily shift out of this close formation, ready to reform it at a moment’s notice.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn56"/></p><p>	While I tend to agree with Campbell that Wheeler goes <q type="quote">too far</q> to find phalangical tactics in the Republican and Imperial periods,<ptr type="footnote" target="fn57"/> I also find Wheeler’s basic argument quite appealing. Wheeler rightfully stresses that, as shown in the <i type="title">Ectaxis</i>, the Roman army most likely had various tactical arrangements to draw on other the traditional Caesarian, <i type="foreign">pilum</i>-hurling, sword-slashing legionary maneuvers.  The choice of tactics depended on the enemy, the terrain, and (to a smaller degree) the commander’s preference.  This is not to say that Arrian is a tactical genius or even that he was <q type="soCalled">experimenting</q> with the phalanx.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn58"/>  Rather, these tactics were developed slowly overtime and were perpetuated mostly by word-of-mouth rather than written treatises.  This does not conflict with Campbell’s argument that military treatises were used (to a certain extent) by military commanders, particularly in training.  Tradition, experience, and written manuals all had a role in the tactical education of military leadership.  Nevertheless, Bosworth rightfully points out that Arrian’s decision to use such a close, phalangical formation most likely was due, in the short term, to the fact that the legion XV Apollinaris had served in the Dacian and Parthian Wars under Trajan.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn59"/>  It was with Trajan that the legion perfected, but did not necessarily invent, this particular formation, either in battles against the Parthian cavalry or by incorporating the tactics of indigenous tribes on the frontiers. It was only by chance that these tactics resembled a Macedonian phalanx.</p></div><div type="head_1"><head>The nature and purpose of the <i>Ectaxis</i></head><p>	How accurately Arrian’s depiction of his battle formation reflects normal Roman tactics of the second century is debatable.  A conclusive answer to this question is further complicated by the literary style of the work, which is very unusual.  The <i type="title">Ectaxis</i> is written as a series of commands that alternate between third-person imperatives and accusatives + infinitives.  This is a style that is rarely seen in Greek literature.  Therefore, the <i type="title">Ectaxis</i> is not a hastily written report from a general stationed on the frontier.  If he were writing to the emperor to simply explain his actions against the Alani, Arrian most likely would have written in normal, indicative Latin sentences, using accurate military terms.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn60"/>  Instead, he wrote a highly polished essay of some literary quality in Greek.  His vocabulary is literary, almost archaic: he calls a legion a phalanx instead of other normal Greek equivalents, and he prepares for an encounter against the <q type="quote">Scythians</q> instead of the Alani.  Arrian does not use technical terms for groups in the army.  He also includes unnecessary explanatory phrases in his battle orders, such as his description of the <i type="foreign">kontoi</i> as having long, thin points.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn61"/></p><p>	The original publication of the <i type="title">Ectaxis</i> is also difficult to determine.  Was it a separate piece?  Or perhaps part of a larger work?  Scholars have argued for both, <q type="quote">equally dogmatically and equally inconclusively.</q><ptr type="footnote" target="fn62"/>  It is obvious that the work derives, in part, from Arrian’s encounter (in whatever sense) with the Alani.  Arrian most likely wrote a simple report for the emperor, in Latin, describing his military maneuvers.  The <i type="title">Ectaxis</i> is a later revision of this report, polished for publication, and it would have performed a similar role as the <i type="title">Periplus</i> did for Arrian’s expedition around the Black Sea.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn63"/>  This literary essay could then have also served as a private memoir or even a military handbook.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn64"/>  Others have suggested that the <i type="title">Ectaxis</i> was part of the <i type="title">Alanike</i>, a lost work only referenced by later authors.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn65"/>  This is unlikely, as no other historical work has had a section written in such a style or length as the <i type="title">Ectaxis</i>.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn66"/></p><p>	A possible answer can be found by considering which authors had a literary influence on Arrian.  Bosworth rightfully points out Arrian’s use of Alexander historians for his technical language, as well as his heavy reliance on Xenophon.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn67"/>  Arrian’s minor works can all be seen as directly related to the work of Xenophon: Arrian’s <i type="title">Diatribes</i> of Epictetus is similar to Xenophon’s <i type="title">Apology</i> of Socrates; Xenophon’s description of the march of the Ten Thousand serves as a foil for Arrian’s <i type="title">Periplus</i>; and Arrian’s <i type="title">Cynegeticus</i> is a commentary on Xenophon’s piece of the same name.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn68"/>  In addition, in Xenophon’s <i type="title">Cyropaedia</i>, we find a detailed order of march, very similar to Arrian’s in the <i type="title">Ectaxis</i>.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn69"/>  Cyrus, speaking to his troops, addresses them in the third person imperative, just as Arrian does.  He lists troops by their national origins and explains the reasons for their various dispositions, such as why heavy infantry should march in the front of the column.  Arrian, too, uses nationalities to describe troops, addressing them in an abbreviated form (e.g., <q type="quote">the Italians</q>) instead of using the official form (<i type="foreign">cohors I Italica</i>).<ptr type="footnote" target="fn70"/>  He also offers explanatory statements, such as the fact that the <i type="foreign">kontos</i> will bend upon hitting the enemy cavalrymen.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn71"/>  Both generals list various commanders and officers, addressing them individually by name.  Also, both generals are portrayed as great leaders; they inspect their troops, make sure men stay in formation, and praise those who marched in good order.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn72"/></p><p>      By drawing on the style and themes of Xenophon’s <i type="title">Cyropaedia</i>, while also expanding their application from marching orders to battle arrangement, Arrian constructs himself as the ideal commander.  Denied the chance to depict a glorious victory over the Alani, Arrian nevertheless uses their <q type="quote">incursion</q> to describe his abilities and leadership, even though he seemingly never had the opportunity to put them into use.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn73"/>  The <i type="title">Ectaxis</i> is more than a mere literary accompaniment to an official report sent to please the emperor; in fact, it is an <q type="quote">emphatic self-advertisement conveyed in a very sophisticated literary form.</q><ptr type="footnote" target="fn74"/>  It should also be seen as a work united in theme and conception with Arrian’s other military writings, that is, his <i type="title">Tactica</i> and also his lost work on Roman infantry maneuvers.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn75"/>  All three works were written not only to praise the emperor and his recent military reforms, but also to demonstrate Arrian’s literary talent and military abilities, particularly in his defense of Cappadocia from the Alani threat.  What Arrian’s exact goals were in writing these works is difficult to determine,<ptr type="footnote" target="fn76"/> but it is clear that Arrian had more in mind than merely pleasing the fancy of some antiquarian, armchair military historian.  Arrian’s military writings, while highly literary, are carefully crafted works shaped by politics and designed as an attempt to gain favor with the biggest military buff of them all: Hadrian.</p></div><div type="head_1"><head>Arrian and ancient warfare</head><p>      In a recent colloquium held at the University of Michigan, Prof. Eugenia Kiesling of the History Department at the U.S. Military Academy reflected on how the military approaches history as a series of <q type="quote">lessons learned</q>.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn77"/>  Similar to Spaulding’s view seventy-five years ago, the U.S. military continues to see history as a practical means of learning about military leadership and strategy.  While it is unlikely that the Marines will adopt the Hellenistic phalanx anytime soon, it is clear that many people today still believe that history has some value in determining proper actions in the contemporary world.</p><p>      Arrian, too, appreciated the value of military history.  A writer of a military handbook himself, Arrian believed in the practical (if limited) application of such works for a general.  He himself may have utilized such treatises in his plan of defense against the Alani in 135 CE.  However, he also had read literature that offered the great model generals of history, such as Alexander the Great and Cyrus.  The experience troops of his legions may also have aided Arrian in his preparations for his encounter with the Alani.  It was a combination of all three, plus his own innate abilities, which allowed Arrian to devise such tactics.</p><p>      Arrian’s <i type="title">Ectaxis</i> shows an author who inhabited a multi-cultural world, one in which a Greek provincial, learned in literature and philosophy, could rise up to be a powerful general and administrator in the Roman Empire.  Through an application of experience, literature, and tactical theory, Arrian created a fresh <i type="foreign">exemplum</i> for future generals.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn78"/>  Whether later soldiers of the Roman army utilized his work in their training is unclear, yet it is certain that another emperor may have felt that the <i type="title">Ectaxis</i> deserved to be published with other great works of military theory.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn79"/>  Arrian’s <i type="title">Ectaxis</i> remains an important work for both understanding the Roman army as well as the cultural fusion that was the Empire.  Through a close investigation of its literary and historical context, one may better appreciate this fragmentary, <q type="soCalled">minor</q> work of one of the most interesting characters of Roman history.</p></div></div><div type="closer"><div type="bibliography"><head>Bibliography</head><listBibl><bibl>Bertrandy, F. and Rémy, B. (2000), "Légio XII Fulminata", in Y. Le Bohec and C. Wolff (eds.), Les Légions de Rome sous le haut-empire: actes du congrès de Lyon (17-19 septembre 1998) (Collection du Centre d’études romaines et gallo-romaines, nouv. sér., no. 20; Paris: Diffusion de Boccard), 255-59.</bibl><bibl>Bosworth, A.B. (1977), "Arrian and the Alani", HSPh 81: 217-51.</bibl><bibl>--- (1993), "Arrian and Rome: The Minor Works", ANRW II.34.1: 226-75.</bibl><bibl>Campbell, J.B. (1987), "Teach yourself how to be a general", JRS 77: 13-29.</bibl><bibl>--- (2002), War and society in imperial Rome, 31 BC-AD 284 (Warfare and history; London and New York: Routledge).</bibl><bibl>--- (2004), Greek and Roman military writers: selected readings (Routledge classical translations; London and New York: Routledge).</bibl><bibl>Devine, A.M. (1993), "Arrian's 'Tactica'", ANRW II.34.1: 312-37.</bibl><bibl>Kiesling, E. (2008), paper presented at Invasion: The Use and Abuse of Comparative History, (University of Michigan, Ann Arbor; 21 Nov 2008).</bibl><bibl>Lee, J.W.I. (2007), A Greek army on the march: soldiers and survival in Xenophon's Anabasis (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press).</bibl><bibl>Patterson, M.R. (2008), "Oliver Lyman Spaulding, Colonel, United States Army &amp; Member of Congress", (updated 12 Sept 2006) &lt;http://www.arlingtoncemetery.net/ospauld.htm&gt;, accessed 4 Dec 2008.</bibl><bibl>Pelham, H.F. (1896), "Arrian as Legate of Cappadocia", EHR 11: 625-40 (= Essays (1911): 212-233).</bibl><bibl>Ritterling, E. (1902), "Zur Erklärung von Arrians ektaxis kata Alanon", WS 24: 359-72.</bibl><bibl>Roos, A.G. (ed.), (1968), Flavii Arriani quae extant omnia, II: Scripta Minora et Fragmenta (2nd edn., 1928 orig. pub., 2002 repr., addenda et corrigenda adiecit G. Wirth; Leipzig: K.G. Saur).</bibl><bibl>Saxtorph, N.M. (2002), "'Acies contra Alanos': Arian on military tactics / transl. of Arrian's text by Christian Gorm Tortzen", in K. Ascani, et al. (eds.), Ancient history matters: studies presented to Jens Erik Skydsgaard on his seventieth birthday (Analecta Romana Instituti Danici Supllementum 30; Roma: L'Erma di Bretschneider), 221-26.</bibl><bibl>Schwartz, E. (1895), "Arrianus, Flavius (9)", RE II.1: 1230-47.</bibl><bibl>Spaulding Jr., O.L. (1933), "The ancient military writers", CJ 28: 657-69.</bibl><bibl>Stadter, P.A. (1980), Arrian of Nicomedia (Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press).</bibl><bibl>Stein, M.T. (2008), "Oliver Lyman Spaulding, Jr., Brigadier General, United States Army", (updated 7 Jan 2008) &lt;http://www.arlingtoncemetery.net/ospauldingjr.htm&gt;, accessed 4 Dec 2008.</bibl><bibl>Syme, R. (1982), "The Career of Arrian", HSPh 86: 181-211.</bibl><bibl>Wheeler, E.L. (1978), "The Occasion of Arrian's Tactica", GRBS 19: 351-65.</bibl><bibl>--- (1979), "The Legion as Phalanx", Chiron 9: 303-18.</bibl><bibl>--- (2000), "Legio XV Apollinaris: From Carnuntum to Satala -- and beyond", in Y. Le Bohec and C. Wolff (eds.), Les Légions de Rome sous le haut-empire: actes du congrès de Lyon (17-19 septembre 1998) (Collection du Centre d’études romaines et gallo-romaines, nouv. sér., no. 20; Paris: Diffusion de Boccard), 259-308.</bibl><bibl>--- (2004a), "The Legion as Phalanx in the Late Empire (I)", in Y. Le Bohec and C. Wolff (eds.), L'armée Romaine de Dioclétin à Valentinien 1er: actes du Congrès de Lyon (12-14 septembre 2002) (Collection du Centre d'études romaines et gallo-romaines, nouv. sér., no. 26; Paris: Diffusion de Boccard), 309-58.</bibl><bibl>--- (2004b), "The Legion as Phalanx in the Late Empire (II)", Revue des Études Militaires Anciennes 1: 147-75.</bibl></listBibl></div><div type="footnotes"><note type="footnote" id="fn1">1 Spaulding Jr. (1933): 657. Spaulding had an interesting career. His father was a colonel in the Union Army, a trustee of the University of Michigan, a Congressman, and an Assistant Secretary of the Treasury. See Patterson (2006). Spaulding, Jr., served with the Artillery Corps in multiple locations (including Alaska, China, the Philippines, Panama, and the AEF during World War I) and was an instructor at the Army War College intermittently until the beginning of World War II. See Stein (2008). He also wrote multiple treatises of his own on field artillery. For some of his lectures, see “Infantry and Cavalry School Lectures 1898-1910” &lt;http://cgsc.leavenworth.army.mil/carl/resources/archival/lectures.asp&gt;.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn2">2 Campbell (1987), cautiously suggests that, partly due to the lack of formal military schooling, these handbooks played a role, if merely a limited one, in the preparation and training of Roman military commanders.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn3">3 The text can be found in Roos (1968): 177-85. Campbell (2004): no. 164-165, offers a useful translation, although I do not agree with it in its entirety. The translation provided by Tortzen in Saxtorph (2002) is wrought with errors, due in part because it is based on Jacoby’s text (FGrH 156 Arrianos F 12). Testimonia to the life of Arrian are collected by Roos (1968): lviii-lxv. They are cited by T followed by the number. Fragments of lost works also are cited by the number in Roos (1968).</note><note type="footnote" id="fn4">4 The standard work on Arrian’s career is Stadter (1980), but see also Schwartz (1895), Pelham (1896), and Syme (1982).</note><note type="footnote" id="fn5">5 Arrian had served as a priest of the goddesses Demeter and Kore at Nicomedia (Photius, Bibliotheca cod. 93 = Bithyniaca F1 = T3).</note><note type="footnote" id="fn6">6 Syme (1982): 184; Dio 49.44.3.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn7">7 Stadter 1980: 5.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn8">8 Devine (1993): 313; Bosworth (1993): 229.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn9">9 It confuses Trajan and Hadrian (Joh. Lyd. De mag. 3.48, p. 142.6 = T14).</note><note type="footnote" id="fn10">10 Bosworth (1993): 229.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn11">11 Stadter (1980): 6.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn12">12 Based on an inscription found in Cordoba (AE 1974.370). See Stadter (1980): 10 and n. 61.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn13">13 His name was found as part of a consular date on brick stamps in Ostia and in Leptis Magna in Africa (CIL XV, 244 and 552 = T7).</note><note type="footnote" id="fn14">14 For evidence for his legateship, see IGRR III, 111 (= T17), AE 1905.175 (= T11). See also Syme (1982): 200.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn15">15 Stadter (1980) provides a very useful map of this region.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn16">16 For XV Apollinaris, see Wheeler (2000). For XII Fulminata, see Bertrandy and Rémy (2000).</note><note type="footnote" id="fn17">17 Arr. Per. 6.2, 10.1.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn18">18 Stadter (1980): 12. For a detailed analysis of the literary quality and peculiarity of the Periplus, see Bosworth (1993): 242-53.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn19">19 Bosworth (1977): 247.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn20">20 ὁ μὲν οὖν τῶν Ἰουδαίων πόλεμος ἐς τοῦτο ἐτελεύτησεν, ἕτερος δὲ ἐξ Ἀλανῶν (εἰσὶ δὲ Μασσαγέται) ἐκινήθη ὑπὸ Φαρασμάνου, καὶ τὴν μὲν Ἀλβανίδα καὶ τὴν Μηδίαν ἰσχυρῶς ἐλύπησε, τῆς δ’ Ἀρμενίας τῆς τε Καππαδοκίας ἁψάμενος, ἔπειτα τῶν Ἀλανῶν τὰ μὲν δώροις ὑπὸ τοῦ Οὐολογαίσου πεισθέντων, τὰ δὲ καὶ Φλάουιον Ἀρριανὸν τὸν τῆς Καππαδοκίας ἄρχοντα φοβηθέντων, ἐπαύσατο (Cass. Dio 69.15.1 = T12). I base my analysis on Bosworth (1977): 218-220.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn21">21 Bosworth (1977): 220. Wheeler (1978): 352, asserts that whether the battle between Arrian and the Alani actually occurred cannot be proven, based on Dio’s account as well as the fact that there is no evidence of any official recognition or public praise for Arrian’s actions.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn22">22 Bosworth (1977): 220-224.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn23">23 HA Hadr. 13.9; Bosworth (1977): 224-228.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn24">24 The archetype manuscript is “a sadly mutilated torso,” Bosworth (1977): 232.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn25">25 Wheeler (2004a): 310. Ec. 15 seems to suggest that XV Apollinaris had far more troops than XII Fulminata. Also, Ec. 5 shows that only the first legion had its legate present; the other legion only had military tribunes. This, combined with archaeological evidence, suggests that the legate of XII Fulminata was away with a detachment in Judaea, or perhaps still in Melitene as a reserve force. See Bosworth (1977): 233-234; Bertrandy and Rémy (2000).</note><note type="footnote" id="fn26">26 Ritterling (1902). Roos (1968) includes these identifications in his app. crit. Bosworth (1977): 233, persuasively amends the military units “Aplanoi” to “Apulanoi” (Ec. 7, 14).</note><note type="footnote" id="fn27">27 Ec. 11-12, 14, 25, 30.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn28">28 Bosworth (1977): 234. This could not have been a narrow pass, as having nearly two legions (plus auxiliaries) lined up in ranks eight-men-deep (Ec. 15) would require the formation to be about 1200-men-wide, which, at intervals of about three feet, would spread nearly 600 yards wide.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn29">29 Lee (2007): 141.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn30">30 Such as Vespasian’s march into Galilee, Jos. BJ 3.115-126. Bosworth (1977): 236.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn31">31 Ec. 4, 9.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn32">32 Ec. 4, 5, 6.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn33">33 Bosworth (1977): 236.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn34">34 Ec. 3-6.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn35">35 Ec. 15-18.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn36">36 Arr. Tact. 27, 32 = Campbell (2004), no. 28-29.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn37">37 For a helpful diagram of Arrian’s battle formation, see Campbell (2002): 55, fig. 3.2.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn38">38 Arr. Tact. 4.3; cf. 4.7; 11.2; 44.1; see also Tacitus’ description of Sarmatians, Tac. Hist. 1.79.2-3; cf. Ann. 6.35.1-2 describing Alani in 35 CE. Bosworth (1977): 234.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn39">39 Ec. 15-18.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn40">40 Ec. 12-14.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn41">41 It is unclear how steep the high ground was (or was expected to be). In order for this arrangement to be truly effective, the terrain must have been sufficiently steep enough to prevent, or at least hinder, a direct cavalry assault against the wings of Arrian’s army.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn42">42 Ec. 20-21, 30-31; Bosworth (1977): 236.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn43">43 Ec. 25-6 (trans. Campbell (2004)).</note><note type="footnote" id="fn44">44 Ec. 27-29.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn45">45 Bosworth (1977): 229-232. Themistius, Orat. 34.8 = T13 (late 4th c. CE) says that after the Alani were defeated, Arrian crossed the Caspian Gates and also regulated the boundaries between the Iberian and Armenian kingdoms.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn46">46 Perhaps a garrison in disguise? Dio 69.15.3; HA Hadr. 17.11-12.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn47">47 SEG XVI 781 (Greek only). See also Bosworth (1977): 230 n. 56. Bosworth suggests that Arrian himself installed this man, acting, in a way, like Alexander the Great installing Macedonians alongside native satraps. This is an appealing, yet still unproved, suggestion.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn48">48 Bosworth (1977): 232.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn49">49 Wheeler (1979), (2004a), (2004b).</note><note type="footnote" id="fn50">50 Crassus: Plut. Crass. 24.3, Dio 40.22.2; Antony: Plut. Ant. 45.2-3, Dio 49.29.2-30.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn51">51 Ec. 6. Wheeler (2004a): 311 n. 8 maintains that Arrian’s use of phalanx for legion is not unprecedented. Cf. Jos. BJ 3.95.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn52">52 Ec. 15.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn53">53 Ec. 26.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn54">54 Arr. Tact. 11.3-4 (= Campbell (2004), no. 167). In this passage, Arrian compares the synaspismos formation to the testudo formation of the Roman army. Whether or not he equates them is unclear.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn55">55 Wheeler (2004b): 151-159 argues at length about the nature of the kontos. He concludes that it was hasta used only for thrusting. Bosworth (1993): 270, esp. n. 224, claims that the kontos is “a specialised, prosaic word” and should not be equated with the hasta. He also retracts his earlier argument ((1977): 240-1) about the third and the fourth rank. Rather than “jabbing and wounding” (παίειν ἢ ἀκοντίζειν)  the horses with their kontoi (as Campbell translates), they instead act as some kind of reserve with their kontoi in crouched position ready for throwing (ἀκοντίζειν) at any convenient target. He argues that the kontos could be used for throwing (for short distances) or for impaling. This confusion is due, in part, to lacunae in the text.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn56">56 Ec. 29.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn57">57 Campbell (1987): 26 n. 83</note><note type="footnote" id="fn58">58 Ibid.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn59">59 Bosworth (1977): 244-245. Arrian, too, may have served on the Daccian frontier at one point.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn60">60 Arrian wrote an “official report”, the Romaika grammata, soon after his inspection of troops and forts during his trip along the Black Sea coast (Peri. 6.2, 10.1).</note><note type="footnote" id="fn61">61 Stadter (1980): 46.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn62">62 Bosworth (1977): 247. His note 124 lists the following: E. Schwartz, RE II 1233: a sidepiece to a Latin report to Hadrian; K. Hartmann, "Flavius Arrianus und Kaiser Hadrian," Progr. Augsburg, 1907, 24: a separate monograph; F. Jacoby, FGrH II B 563: a portion of the Alanike; Roos (1968) xxi: a manual for the use of the Cappadocian army.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn63">63 Bosworth (1993): 243, 266; (1977): 247-8; Scwartz (1895).</note><note type="footnote" id="fn64">64 Campbell (1987): 27 n. 88.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn65">65 Wheeler (1979): 301 n. 1; Saxtorph (2002). The Alanike is mentioned by John Lydus in the 6th c. (De mag. 3.53 = Arr. Parth. F6) and Photius in the 9th c. (Bibl. 58 = Arr. Parth. F1). See Roos (1968) xxx-xxxi. Stadter (1980): 163 believes that the Alanike “implies a geographical and ethnographical work like the Indike…[it] possibly contained an account of Arrian's confrontation with the tribe when it attacked Cappadocia in 135…[and it] undoubtedly [was] composed as a result of the Alan attack.”</note><note type="footnote" id="fn66">66 Stadter (1980): 45; Bosworth (1993): 266; (1977): 247.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn67">67 For Alexander historians, see Bosworth (1977): 248-243. Also, “Xenophon had become more than a simple literary inspiration. He was now a model for action, a constant point of reference for the presentation and propagating of Arrian's own image” (1993): 275. Arrian calls himself “Xenophon” in some of his works (e.g., Ec. 10), although Bosworth doubts this was part of his real name (1993): 273 n. 230, contra Stadter (1980): 2-3.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn68">68 Bosworth (1993): 272-275.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn69">69 Xen. Cyrop. 5.3.34-45. See Bosworth (1993): 264-267.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn70">70 Ec. 3.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn71">71 Ec. 17.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn72">72 Ec. 10; Xen. Cyrop. 5.3.55.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn73">73 Granted, the text of the Ectaxis breaks off abruptly. Could there have been a description of the rout of the Alani? No later author seems to mention it. We can only assume that Arrian never actually fought with Alani, or at least never described it.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn74">74 Bosworth (1993): 267.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn75">75 Stadter (1980): 46. Wheeler (1978): 356 denies that any such ‘lost’ work actually existed, as the passage (Tact. 32.3) is highly problematic. He claims that the Tactica was most likely written in celebration of Hadrian’s vicennalia in 136 CE.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn76">76 I’m not as confident as Wheeler (1978) to suggest that any of these works was Arrian’s attempt to prolong his military career. If it was, it obviously failed, as we have no record of Arrian receiving any further military command. Perhaps he preferred to retire to Athens instead, where he was elected archon in 145/6 CE. See Stadter (1980): 13-18.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn77">77 Kiesling (2008).</note><note type="footnote" id="fn78">78 Campbell (1987): 27.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn79">79 Cod. Laurentianus gr. 55.4 is the archetype manuscript for the work. Dated from time of Constantine VII Porphyrogenitus (r. 912-959), an emperor with tastes similar to Hadrian, the manuscript contains three separate collections of almost exclusively tactical works. The first and third collections are Byzantine, but the second collections containins Hellenistic and Roman military treatises by Asclepiodotus, Aelian, Aeneas Tacticus, Arrian (Tactia and Ectaxis), and Onasander, as well as the “rhetorica militaris” and Sextus Julius Africanus. See Devine (1993).</note></div></div></body></text></TEI.2>