<TEI.2><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Bear Valley Structural Analysis</title><author>anonymized</author></titleStmt><wordcount>758</wordcount><editionStmt><edition>Version 1.0</edition></editionStmt><extent>insert_extent</extent><publicationStmt><idno>NRE.G0.09.1</idno><publisher>The University of Michigan</publisher><pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan, USA</pubPlace><date>2007</date><availability><p>The MICUSP project is owned by the Regents of the University of Michigan, who hold the copyright. The database has been developed by the English Language Institute. The original text submissions are stored electronically in the English Language Institute and may be consulted by bona fide researchers under special arrangements. The database is available by password on the World Wide Web for study, teaching and research purposes. Copies of the text files may be distributed, as long as either this statement of availability or the citation given below appears in the text. However, if any portion of this material is to be used for commercial purposes, such as for textbooks or tests, permission must be obtained in advance and a license fee may be required. For further information about copyright permissions, please inquire at micusp@umich.edu.</p><p>The recommended citation for MICASE is: Ädel, A., J. M. Swales, and J. Sielaff. (2007) The Michigan Corpus of Upper-level Student Papers. Ann Arbor, MI: The Regents of the University of Michigan.</p></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>The Michigan Corpus of Upper-level Student Papers (MICUSP)</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><p>This document derives from an unpublished, student-authored paper contributed in electronic format.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>For information on corpus compilation and encoding practices, see the MICUSP Handbook.</p></projectDesc><classDecl><taxonomy><category><catDesc>departments</catDesc><category id="BIO"><catDesc>Biology</catDesc></category><category id="CEE"><catDesc>Civil and Environmental Engineering</catDesc></category><category id="CLS"><catDesc>Classical Studies</catDesc></category><category id="ECO"><catDesc>Economics</catDesc></category><category id="EDU"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category id="ENG"><catDesc>English</catDesc></category><category id="IOE"><catDesc>Industrial and Operational Engineering</catDesc></category><category id="LIN"><catDesc>Linguistics</catDesc></category><category id="MEC"><catDesc>Mechanical Engineering</catDesc></category><category id="NRE"><catDesc>Natural Resources</catDesc></category><category id="NUR"><catDesc>Nursing</catDesc></category><category id="PHI"><catDesc>Philosophy</catDesc></category><category id="PHY"><catDesc>Physics</catDesc></category><category id="POL"><catDesc>Political Science</catDesc></category><category id="PSY"><catDesc>Psychology</catDesc></category><category id="SOC"><catDesc>Sociology</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>student levels</catDesc><category id="G0"><catDesc>senior undergraduate</catDesc></category><category id="G1"><catDesc>first-year graduate</catDesc></category><category id="G2"><catDesc>second-year graduate</catDesc></category><category id="G3"><catDesc>third-year graduate and up</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>student-reported text types</catDesc><category id="CaseStudy"><catDesc>case study</catDesc></category><category id="Critique"><catDesc>critique</catDesc></category><category id="LiteratureReview"><catDesc>literature review</catDesc></category><category id="ResearchProposal"><catDesc>research proposal</catDesc></category><category id="ResponsePaper"><catDesc>response paper</catDesc></category><category id="TechnicalOrLabReport"><catDesc>technical report or lab report</catDesc></category><category id="TermPaper"><catDesc>term paper</catDesc></category><category id="OtherTextType"><catDesc>other</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>approximate preparation times</catDesc><category id="OneToThreeDays"><catDesc>1-3 days</catDesc></category><category id="FourToTenDays"><catDesc>4-10 days</catDesc></category><category id="TwoToThreeWeeks"><catDesc>2-3 weeks</catDesc></category><category id="ThreeToSixWeeks"><catDesc>3-6 weeks</catDesc></category><category id="OneFullSemester"><catDesc>one full semester</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>sources of feedback</catDesc><category id="NoFeedback"><catDesc>no feedback from others</catDesc></category><category id="PrimaryInstructor"><catDesc>primary course instructor</catDesc></category><category id="GSI"><catDesc>Graduate Student Instructor (teaching assistant)</catDesc></category><category id="WritingTutor"><catDesc>writing tutor</catDesc></category><category id="FriendOrClassmate"><catDesc>friend or classmate</catDesc></category><category id="OtherFeedback"><catDesc>other</catDesc></category></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><creation>Paper submitted to instructor in Oct 2008</creation><particDesc><person id="P591" sex="f" age="TwentyToTwentyThree"><affiliation>Physics and Geosciences</affiliation><firstLang>English</firstLang><dominantLang>English</dominantLang><englishInPrimarySchool value="NO"/><englishInSecondarySchool value="NO"/><englishInUndergraduate value="NO"/><langKnown>\N</langKnown></person></particDesc><textClass><catRef target="NRE G0 Report TechnicalOrLabReport FourToTenDays PrimaryInstructor"><classification><primary>Report</primary><secondary>Research Paper</secondary></classification><classification><primary>Report</primary><secondary/></classification><features><feature type="Abstract"/><feature type="Methodology section"/><feature type="Tables, graphs or figures"/></features></catRef></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change><date>2009-06-04</date><respStmt><name>Geoffrey Ho</name><resp>coder</resp></respStmt><item>manual adjustment of tags</item></change><change><date>2007-05-22</date><respStmt><name>Gregory Garretson</name><resp>programmer</resp></respStmt><item>initial (automated) encoding in XML</item></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="opener"><head>﻿Bear Valley Structural Analysis</head><p/><div type="abstract"><head>Abstract</head><p>Measurements of bedding, joint, fault and slickenside attitudes were made at the Bear Valley Strip Mine south of Shamokin, PA.  A basic geology history of the region was derived, along with a description of the structural geometry through a combination of direct observation and stereonet analysis.</p></div></div><div type="main"><div type="head_1"><head>Introduction</head><p>	The Bear Valley Strip Mine lies in the Valley and Ridge province of the Appalachian foreland fold and thrust belt.  The bedding consists primarily of Pennsylvanian shales and sandstones and is rich in anthracite coal.  The strip mine is an excellent exposure of third order folds, which also display other features like joints and faults.  One aim of this study is to characterize the geometry of the region.  Additionally, a brief structural history is outlined based on observation and stereonet analysis. </p></div><div type="head_1"><head>Methods</head><p>	Field measurements were made using a Brunton compass and an air photo.  We focused on attitude measurements of bedding, fault planes, slickensides and joints.  These measurements were then plotted and analyzed on an equal area stereonet using Rich Allmendinger’s Stereonet program.</p></div><div type="head_1"><head>Fold Geometry</head><p>	There are two main anticline-syncline pairs in the Bear Valley Strip Mine.  We used the bedding attitude of the fold limbs to determine the plunge and trend of their fold axes.  </p><p>Fig. 1:  Bear Valley Strip Mine (photo courtesy of Eric Portenga) </p><gap desc="figure"/></div><div type="head_1"><head>Fig. 2:  North Anticline bedding surfaces</head><gap desc="figure"/><p>       Based on stereonet analysis, the North Anticline appears to be a symmetric fold with a fold axis trending 254o and plunging 2o.  The fold axis of the North Syncline also trends 254o and plunges 2o.  However, the southern wall of the North Syncline dips at a much greater angle than the northern side, indicating an asymmetric fold with vergence to the south. </p><p>       </p><gap desc="figure"/></div><div type="head_1"><head>Fig. 3:  North Syncline bedding surfaces</head><p>	The Whaleback Anticline trends 252o and plunges 15o.  The difference in dip with respect to the North Anticline is attributed to the locations of measurements made on the fold.  Most of the North Anticline attitudes were taken near the crest of the fold, whereas many of the Whaleback bedding attitudes were measured far down the limbs of the fold.</p><gap desc="figure"/></div><div type="head_1"><head>Fig. 4:  Whaleback Anticline bedding surfaces</head><p>The North facing limb of the Whaleback is steeper than the southern side, indicating a top to the North vergence.  The syncline south of the Whaleback also shows bottom to the South vergence and has a fold axis of attitude 248o, 13o.</p><gap desc="figure"/></div><div type="head_1"><head>Fig. 5:  Whaleback Syncline bedding surfaces</head><gap desc="figure"/><p>Fig. 6:  Schematic N-S cross section showing top to the north vergence on the Whaleback anticline (WB A).</p></div><div type="head_1"><head>Joint Orientations</head><p>	By measuring the attitudes of joints and the attitudes of folds we can <q type="soCalled">unfold</q> the bedding to return the joints to their original orientation.  </p><gap desc="figure"/></div><div type="head_1"><head>Fig. 7:  Joint orientations after unfolding of bedding</head><p>	After rotating the joints back to horizontal many of their orientations match up well with the regional joint sets, as shown below.   This indicates that the joints occurred before the strata were folded.</p><p>Table 1: Comparison of measured joint strikes to regional joints from Nickelsen and Hough</p><gap desc="table"/></div><div type="head_1"><head>Slickenside Orientations</head><p>	Similar to the joints, the slickenside orientations can be rotated back to horizontal by unfolding the bedding.  If the rotated slickenside points are clustered on the stereonet, then faulting occurred before folding.  On the other hand, faulting occurred post-folding if the rotated slickensides are spread out over the stereonet.  </p><p>	The slickensides measured at the Bear Valley Strip Mine show that faulting may have occurred both before and after the folding event.  The cluster of rotated slickensides in the lower half of the stereonet may represent pre-folding compressional faults.  </p><p>	The circled points on the plot mark the extensional faults observed on the surface of the Whaleback Anticline.  These faults most likely occurred after or during the folding, and could be the result of buckling as the beds were folded.</p></div><div type="head_1"><head>Conclusions</head><p>	A brief geologic history of the area can be drawn from this analysis.  The regional jointing most likely formed first, possibly followed by compressional faulting as the Alleghanian orogeny began.  The beds were then folded into a widespread set of synclinorium.  This resulted in extensional faulting along the outer surfaces of folds.  This hypothesis could be confirmed by going back to the field site and making more measurements of slickensides and joints.  We could also look for other exposures of folds in area to characterize their geometry and geologic history.</p><gap desc="figure"/><p>Fig. 8:  Stereonet of slickensides.  Red points are unrotated, blue lines are rotated.  Circled points correspond to extensional faults observed in the field.</p><gap desc="figure"/><p>Fig. 9: Air photo of Bear Valley Strip Mine</p></div></div><div type="closer"><p/></div></body></text></TEI.2>