<TEI.2><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Coal-to-Liquids Policy Memo</title><author>anonymized</author></titleStmt><wordcount>4722</wordcount><editionStmt><edition>Version 1.0</edition></editionStmt><extent>insert_extent</extent><publicationStmt><idno>NRE.G1.01.1</idno><publisher>The University of Michigan</publisher><pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan, USA</pubPlace><date>2007</date><availability><p>The MICUSP project is owned by the Regents of the University of Michigan, who hold the copyright. The database has been developed by the English Language Institute. The original text submissions are stored electronically in the English Language Institute and may be consulted by bona fide researchers under special arrangements. The database is available by password on the World Wide Web for study, teaching and research purposes. Copies of the text files may be distributed, as long as either this statement of availability or the citation given below appears in the text. However, if any portion of this material is to be used for commercial purposes, such as for textbooks or tests, permission must be obtained in advance and a license fee may be required. For further information about copyright permissions, please inquire at micusp@umich.edu.</p><p>The recommended citation for MICASE is: Ädel, A., J. M. Swales, and J. Sielaff. (2007) The Michigan Corpus of Upper-level Student Papers. Ann Arbor, MI: The Regents of the University of Michigan.</p></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>The Michigan Corpus of Upper-level Student Papers (MICUSP)</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><p>This document derives from an unpublished, student-authored paper contributed in electronic format.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>For information on corpus compilation and encoding practices, see the MICUSP Handbook.</p></projectDesc><classDecl><taxonomy><category><catDesc>departments</catDesc><category id="BIO"><catDesc>Biology</catDesc></category><category id="CEE"><catDesc>Civil and Environmental Engineering</catDesc></category><category id="CLS"><catDesc>Classical Studies</catDesc></category><category id="ECO"><catDesc>Economics</catDesc></category><category id="EDU"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category id="ENG"><catDesc>English</catDesc></category><category id="IOE"><catDesc>Industrial and Operational Engineering</catDesc></category><category id="LIN"><catDesc>Linguistics</catDesc></category><category id="MEC"><catDesc>Mechanical Engineering</catDesc></category><category id="NRE"><catDesc>Natural Resources</catDesc></category><category id="NUR"><catDesc>Nursing</catDesc></category><category id="PHI"><catDesc>Philosophy</catDesc></category><category id="PHY"><catDesc>Physics</catDesc></category><category id="POL"><catDesc>Political Science</catDesc></category><category id="PSY"><catDesc>Psychology</catDesc></category><category id="SOC"><catDesc>Sociology</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>student levels</catDesc><category id="G0"><catDesc>senior undergraduate</catDesc></category><category id="G1"><catDesc>first-year graduate</catDesc></category><category id="G2"><catDesc>second-year graduate</catDesc></category><category id="G3"><catDesc>third-year graduate and up</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>student-reported text types</catDesc><category id="CaseStudy"><catDesc>case study</catDesc></category><category id="Critique"><catDesc>critique</catDesc></category><category id="LiteratureReview"><catDesc>literature review</catDesc></category><category id="ResearchProposal"><catDesc>research proposal</catDesc></category><category id="ResponsePaper"><catDesc>response paper</catDesc></category><category id="TechnicalOrLabReport"><catDesc>technical report or lab report</catDesc></category><category id="TermPaper"><catDesc>term paper</catDesc></category><category id="OtherTextType"><catDesc>other</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>approximate preparation times</catDesc><category id="OneToThreeDays"><catDesc>1-3 days</catDesc></category><category id="FourToTenDays"><catDesc>4-10 days</catDesc></category><category id="TwoToThreeWeeks"><catDesc>2-3 weeks</catDesc></category><category id="ThreeToSixWeeks"><catDesc>3-6 weeks</catDesc></category><category id="OneFullSemester"><catDesc>one full semester</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>sources of feedback</catDesc><category id="NoFeedback"><catDesc>no feedback from others</catDesc></category><category id="PrimaryInstructor"><catDesc>primary course instructor</catDesc></category><category id="GSI"><catDesc>Graduate Student Instructor (teaching assistant)</catDesc></category><category id="WritingTutor"><catDesc>writing tutor</catDesc></category><category id="FriendOrClassmate"><catDesc>friend or classmate</catDesc></category><category id="OtherFeedback"><catDesc>other</catDesc></category></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><creation>Paper submitted to instructor in Dec 2007</creation><particDesc><person id="P280" sex="m" age="TwentyToTwentyThree"><affiliation>Natural Resources</affiliation><firstLang>English</firstLang><dominantLang>English</dominantLang><englishInPrimarySchool value="YES"/><englishInSecondarySchool value="YES"/><englishInUndergraduate value="YES"/></person></particDesc><textClass><catRef target="NRE G1 Report OtherTextType TwoToThreeWeeks GSI"><classification><primary>Report</primary><secondary>Proposal</secondary></classification><classification><primary>Report</primary><secondary>Proposal</secondary></classification><features><feature type="Reference to sources"/></features></catRef></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change><date>2008-12-11</date><respStmt><name>Geoffrey Ho</name><resp>coder</resp></respStmt><item>manual adjustment of tags</item></change><change><date>2007-05-22</date><respStmt><name>Gregory Garretson</name><resp>programmer</resp></respStmt><item>initial (automated) encoding in XML</item></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="opener"><head>Introducing coal-to-liquids incentives into the compromise H.R. 6 bill</head><p/></div><div type="main"><div type="head_1"><head>Executive Summary</head><p>	The United States is in the midst of a national security, energy, and climate crisis that demands significant attention from elected leaders.  In the past, the U.S. has made attempts to use its huge coal reserves (more than a quarter of total world reserves)<ptr type="footnote" target="fn1"/> to create liquid fuels to solve energy problems and their attendant national security issues.  However, all political attempts to create a coal-to-liquids (CTL) industry have failed.  Just this year, your joint offering of CTL incentives, S. 133, with Jim Bunning has not been passed and a number of related amendments in both the House and Senate have failed as well.  The reasons so far appear to be Democratic energy leadership's unwillingness to consider the issue before the fall and disagreement over the requirements to capture and sequester CO<ptr type="footnote" target="fn2"/> from the process and the mechanisms involved in the incentives. However, 69 Senators voted for one of the two CTL amendments to H.R. 6 in June, suggesting that this issue has legs.</p><p>	As a result, you should seize this opportunity to negotiate a bipartisan supported set of incentives intended to promote an environmentally friendly CTL industry to include in the final H.R. 6 bill (see Appendix II for details).  Doing so will allow you to take serious steps towards solving national security and climate change problems and achieve major political gains that will be invaluable in your bid for the presidency.</p><p>	On the technical side, CTL has the ability to replace up to 30% of imported oil by 2030, putting us on the way to independence from foreign oil.2  CTL also has the ability to reduce CO2 emissions when paired with carbon capture and sequestration (CCS) and a biomass (non-food) co-feed.  RAND predicts that with a 50%-50% mix of coal to biomass and CCS that emissions could actually be negative.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn3"/> In addition, CTL can enable biomass-to-liquids (BTL), which will be able to take advantage of the negative emissions from biomass earlier than cellulosic ethanol.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn4"/>  The overarching barrier to CTL producers is the high amounts cost of market entry and their inability to obtain it from lenders.  Carefully crafted government incentives would help to eliminate this problem and incentivize environmentally beneficial configurations of CTL.</p><p>	On the political side, the gains would be tremendous for your presidential campaign.  Negotiating a bipartisan supported set of CTL incentives would enhance your status as a consensus builder, boost your credibility on national security issues, and allow you to take credit for economic expansion.  This last piece will especially help you in coal swing states, which account for 149 electoral votes, and in the primary in Iowa, which has significant coal and biomass.  Adding CTL may also help to overcome opposition to the bill by Republican lawmakers and the President by appealing to coal interests, allowing you to take some credit for its passage.  You will likely take a hit from environmental groups, which oppose CTL of any kind, but framing the issue around CO2 emissions reductions and BTL should help.</p><p>	CTL incentives will face implementation problems, however.  The purpose of the incentives could be unclear to the Department of Energy (DOE), operational demands will be high and could interfere with DOE standard operating procedures, monitoring lifecycle CO2 emissions will require significant DOE resources in the form of staff, expertise, and equipment, the incentives will depend on future politicians to continue them, and the measures will likely be challenged in court.  However, these problems can be overcome with clear directives, Congressional review, additional funding, and building up political support within the policy community for CTL incentives.</p></div><div type="head_1"><head>Background</head><p>	The United States is in the midst of a national security, energy, and climate crisis that demands significant attention from elected leaders.  In the past, the U.S. has made attempts to use its huge coal reserves (more than a quarter of total world reserves)<ptr type="footnote" target="fn5"/> to create liquid fuels to solve energy problems and their attendant national security issues.  Such efforts began in 1944 with the U.S. Synthetic Liquid Fuels Act, which authorized the Secretary of the Interior to construct synthetic liquid fuel plants to aid in the prosecution of WWII.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn6"/>  In 1980, Congress created the U.S. Synthetic Fuels Corporation, which was disbanded in 1985, to financially assist companies in the creation of coal-to-liquids (CTL).<ptr type="footnote" target="fn7"/>  Finally, two years ago, the Energy Policy Act of 2005 included initiatives allowing the Secretary of Defense to create a CTL policy, directing the Department of Energy to evaluate production of CTL from Illinois Basin coal (a product of Obama's fine efforts), and authorizing the Secretary of Energy to provide loan guarantees to CTL companies.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn8"/>  All of these failed, the most recent because of a lack of dedicated funding.</p><p>	This year has been no different.  Barack Obama's joint offering with Jim Bunning (R-KY), S. 133, attempted to establish CTL incentives totaling around $8 billion, though with no stipulations on CO2 emissions.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn9"/>  Since in its pure form, CTL could create close to twice the lifecycle CO2 emissions of regular gasoline, environmental groups such as the Sierra Club came out against the bill.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn10"/>  As Obama has since qualified his support for the bill, it has gone nowhere.  In the House, a number of amendments to energy legislation over the summer were rejected because of Democratic leadership's wish to consider the issue in the fall.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn11"/>  In the Senate, during consideration of H.R. 6 (The CLEAN Energy Act) in June, two amendments promoting CTL were defeated because of partisan disagreements over requirements to capture and sequester CO2 and mechanisms to promote CTL productions.  Both called for a 20% reduction in lifecycle CO2 emissions, but the Republican proposal would have created a 6 billion gallon CTL mandate by 2022, while the Democratic proposal would have required 75% of the production CO2 to be captured and sequestered and provided only $10 million in loans.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn12"/>  69 Senators voted for at least one of the amendments, however, implying that the issue has legs.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn13"/></p><p>	After a lengthy delay, Democrats have finally reached an agreement on fuel efficiency standards to be included in the final version of H.R. 6.  The House expects to vote on the bill sometime during the week of December 3rd and the Senate timeline has not been determined.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn14"/>  While the current compromise bill does not currently contain anything on CTL, there is still time to influence negotiations.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn15"/>  Many, including Senator Charles Grassley (R-IA), view the inclusion of CTL as necessary to actually pass the bill.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn16"/></p></div><div type="head_1"><head>Recommendation</head><p>	Obama should seize this opportunity to negotiate a bipartisan supported set of incentives intended to promote an environmentally friendly CTL industry to include in the final H.R. 6 bill (see Appendix II for details).  Doing so will allow Obama to take serious steps towards solving national security and climate change problems and achieve major political gains that will be invaluable in his bid for the presidency.</p></div><div type="head_1"><head>Technical Feasibility</head><p>	CTL has the potential to play a substantial role in solving national security problems, as well as in reducing U.S. CO2 emissions.  Many current national security problems are caused or are being exacerbated by reliance on foreign oil.  Money from oil purchases in the Persian Gulf directly funds terrorist networks.  Continued American presence in the Gulf region serves as a recruitment tool for Al-Qaeda.  Oil-exporting states have significant leverage over the U.S.  Democratic institutions are undermined by oil rents.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn17"/>  Fortunately, according to the July 2006 American Energy Security Study of the Southern States Energy Board (a non-profit organization representing the governors of 16 southern states from Virginia to Texas), nearly 30% of oil imports could be replaced with CTL by 2030.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn18"/>  Although the study was 40% funded by Peabody Energy, the world's largest coal company, and the National Mining Association<ptr type="footnote" target="fn19"/>, any reduction of oil imports by close to that amount would yield huge national security gains.</p><p>	Further, contrary to popular belief, CTL can help in the fight against climate change.  Though CTL would entail an increase in the amount of coal mining, which entails a number of negative environmental effects, the fuels produced would be ultra-low sulfur (since it must be removed during the liquefaction process) and can have lower lifecycle CO2 emissions than gasoline.  When CTL is created without any CCS or biomass co-feed, a group at the Princeton Environmental Institute found that it produces around 1.77 times the lifecycle CO2 of gasoline.  However, when CCS is used, the level is 1.08 and when CCS and biomass (non-food) co-feed are used, the level is 0.21.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn20"/>  RAND, a non-profit think-tank, has found that with a 40%-60% mix of coal to biomass, CTL lifecycle CO2 emissions would be roughly equivalent to normal gasoline and a 50%-50% mix with CCS would yield negative emissions.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn21"/> The technology for CTL is mature, but the process of introducing biomass as a co-feed is less so.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn22"/></p><p>	Finally, CTL would help to <q type="soCalled">enable</q> the production of biomass-to-liquids (BTL).  BTL will likely be commercially viable in a shorter time frame (5 years) than cellulosic ethanol (10+ years).<ptr type="footnote" target="fn23"/>  Using biomass in biomass-to-liquids would, therefore, help to capture the benefits of biomass (negative lifecycle emissions) earlier.  Using coal and biomass together would reduce fuel delivery costs inherent to BTL, allow large plants for increased benefits of economies of scale, and reduce uncertainty of BTL feedstock supply, since biomass would be vulnerable to weather fluctuations.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn24"/></p><p>	The overarching problem with capturing these benefits of CTL is the huge cost of market entry.  To build a factory producing 30,000 to 40,000 barrels of liquid fuels per day costs $3 to $6 billion dollars.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn25"/>  With such high sums required, it appears unlikely that private industry will be able to obtain the necessary funding because of three uncertainties: cost and performance of CTL facilities, future oil prices, and how CO2 will be regulated in the U.S.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn26"/>  To mitigate these risks and achieve the technical gains listed above, government incentives, such as loan guarantees and production incentives, will be necessary.  These incentives can be scaled to lifecycle CO2 emissions reductions to incentivize environmentally beneficial CTL configurations.</p></div><div type="head_1"><head>Political Feasibility</head><p>	Obviously, Obama's major political concern has shifted from maintaining his Senate career to achieving the Presidency.  According to the most recent USA Today/Gallup poll, Hillary Clinton (D-NY) still maintains a large lead in the primary campaign (39% to 24% for Obama).<ptr type="footnote" target="fn27"/>  With less than a month to go before the first primary, the time for bold steps is now.</p><p>	As stated earlier, there is already fertile ground for action on CTL.  Something on CTL will most likely come out of this Congress, it is just a question of how it is shaped and who will do it.  If Obama were to seize the issue, he could point CTL in a politically beneficial direction and capture most of the benefits.  Immediately upon achieving a bipartisan agreement on incentives, Obama could hold the achievement up as an example of how he is a consensus builder and a new breed of politician.  Further, it would show that he is willing to take significant steps towards greater national security.  A Rasmussen Reports poll shows that national security/war on terror is very or somewhat important to 88% of voters, and only 44% of voters trust Democrats more than Republicans on the issue (46% feel the opposite).<ptr type="footnote" target="fn28"/>  This suggests that there is still valuable room for Democrats in general to improve on this issue.  Finally, Obama could take credit for the significant economic development that a CTL program would produce.  A CTL industry would create skilled jobs and help to alleviate economic hardships in depressed coal regions, as Rentech (a nascent CTL company) is planning to do in areas of Mississippi and Illinois.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn29"/>  By eliminating a substantial portion of oil payments going overseas and directing them to U.S. energy companies, Obama could take credit for economic expansion within the country (and within his own coal-rich state of Illinois).  Further, coal companies have had an increasingly difficult time selling high-priced, high-sulfur coal from Central Appalachia to electric utilities because of federal acid rain regulations.  Utilities, instead, have been turning to lower-priced coal in the West that contains less sulfur.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn30"/>  CTL would create vast new markets for this coal.  The economy, as it always is, remains important in the minds of Americans, as a Rasmussen Reports poll shows that 97% of respondents view the economy as very or somewhat important in the coming elections.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn31"/>  All of these points should figure prominently in both the primary and general Presidential elections.</p><p>	More specifically, these economic gains would be extremely helpful in securing votes for the general election (as well as in the primaries) from swing states with coal reserves such as Arkansas, Colorado, Indiana, Iowa, Kentucky, Michigan, Missouri, New Mexico, Ohio, Pennsylvania, Tennessee, Virginia, and West Virginia.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn32"/>  Together these states account for 149 of the 538 total delegates of the Electoral College.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn33"/>  Capturing these states should be high priority in what could be a tight general election.</p><p>Even more important, however, may be the potential political gains in Iowa.  Though there currently is no coal mining in Iowa, the state used to maintain a thriving coal industry, which declined during the 1980s following the country's shift to western coal,<ptr type="footnote" target="fn34"/> and contains over 1.1 billion short tons of recoverable reserves.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn35"/>  In addition, Iowa ranks first in raw biomass production across the nation and can produce 32.7 million dry tons of biomass per year,<ptr type="footnote" target="fn36"/> making it a prime target for a coal+biomass-to-liquids industry.  It goes without saying that the state is also extremely important in the Democratic primaries, as it has the first.  Given Clinton's large national lead, many believe that Iowa to be the best opportunity for Obama to make up ground.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn37"/>  This race is much closer than the national election, thankfully, with a Rasmussen Reports poll showing Hillary with a slim lead of 27% vs. 25% for Obama.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn38"/>  Framing this decision as a job creating opportunity for Iowa could help boost Obama's chances in the state.</p><p>Further, if Obama is able to negotiate a compromise on CTL, it could help to actually get H.R. 6 passed and he could claim much of the success.  After the announcement of a deal on the general framework of H.R. 6, a number of Republican lawmakers and the President's economic advisor, Al Hubbard came out against the compromise.  A source of much of the opposition is the inclusion of a Renewable Portfolio Standard (RPS), which would mandate increasing generation of renewable electricity.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn39"/>  Adding a CTL provision, however, could help tip the scales in favor of passage.  The Southern States Energy Board has come out dramatically in favor CTL, suggesting that the represented states, which are against RPS because of a perceived lack of renewable sources, would benefit from CTL provisions.  Also, the President has previously supported CTL<ptr type="footnote" target="fn40"/> and its inclusion could make the bill easier for him to sign.  Achieving these goals would increase Obama's standing in national politics, further show that he is a <q type="soCalled">new breed</q> of politician, and allow him to take greater credit for the political success of the entire energy bill. </p><p>	Despite these gains, however, Obama will likely take a hit from environmental groups as a result of his stance.  Some groups, such as the Natural Resources Defense Council, have argued that the environmental impacts of coal mining are too great to allow any CTL development.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn41"/>  In addition, some groups, such as the Center for American Progress have argued that CCS, because of its expense, should be put to use in more efficient ways, such as in electricity generation.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn42"/>  Finally, over the summer, 14 environmental groups signed and circulated a letter this summer calling any provision for CTL <q type="quote">a poison pill that would make any bill totally unacceptable.</q><ptr type="footnote" target="fn43"/>  In general, therefore, it should be noted that environmental groups are against any form of CTL.  Even so, Obama should pursue this course of action.  His League of Conservation Voters rating is 100 for 2006, meaning he already has a lot of environmental political capital and can afford to take a hit.  In addition, Obama should frame his decision in a positive environmental light.  Since the big environmental issue of the moment is climate change (and not the environmental impacts of coal mining), he could point out the potential lifecycle CO2 reductions from the many configurations of CTL mentioned above and argue that by taking control of the issue, he is better able to direct CTL towards those configurations.  Most importantly, he should emphasize the ability of CTL to enable BTL.  Finally, he could point out in his defense that, in June, his main competitor, Hillary Clinton, voted for the Democratic amendment to H.R. 6 promoting CTL (as did Obama).<ptr type="footnote" target="fn44"/>  This should provide him with some political cover.</p></div><div type="head_1"><head>Administrative Feasibility</head><p>It is important to note, however, that this program of CTL incentives (see Appendix II for details) could face a number of significant implementation problems, spanning communications, operational demands, resources, and shared authority.  In terms of communications problems, the Department of Energy (DOE) could be unclear of the purpose of these programs, given that there would be little legislative record, such as committee reports, to explain the motivations behind the incentives.  For example, it is possible that the DOE would emphasize production in its distribution of incentive payments and ignore environmental protection because of confusion over its mandate.  It would be useful, therefore, to include a statement of purpose in the compromise bill or in a following resolution to ensure that the DOE knows that its purpose lies beyond simply ramping up production of CTL, but to also require compliance to CO2 lifecycle requirements.</p><p>	The operational demands of the proposed measures will likely be high.  To qualify for incentives under the proposed measures, a company must attain a lifecycle CO2 reduction of 20%.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn45"/>  DOE will need to first evaluate whether proposed project plans will achieve those reductions and then perform follow up monitoring to ensure that those reductions have actually been met.  This will be a very difficult task, as it involves complex lifecycle analysis that may need to be refined for these purposes.  In addition, the activity of monitoring environmental impacts (in this case CO2 emissions) before distributing production incentives may well run counter to DOE's standard operating procedures (SOPs).  DOE is certainly not the EPA and may well find its new task onerous and contrary to their usual goal of increasing energy production, leading to resistance to implementation.  These two problems can be managed, however, if DOE is directed (with appropriate additional funding) to create a standard lifecycle analysis model within a year and if Congress follows up with regular review of the implementation, using funding cuts as a potential stick.</p><p>	This required monitoring, however, will also create resource problems.  To perform this analysis of CTL projects, DOE will need significant numbers of expert staff members and additional equipment.  This could be helped along with additional funding for the hiring and training of experts in CTL technology, as well as for the purchase of required equipment.  Further, CTL projects that would qualify for incentives will likely emerge slowly, giving DOE time to develop the expertise needed to fully implement the program.</p><p>	Finally, implementation of CTL incentives will create significant shared authority problems.  DOE will be dependent on Congressional and Presidential support to receive future funding for these programs.  To create a truly robust CTL industry, incentives will have to last beyond a single election cycle.  In addition, environmentalist groups may try to block the implementation of CTL incentives by taking DOE to court, tying up the already busy agency in court battles and possibly delaying the process of implementation.  To overcome these will require personal action on the part of Obama and other CTL stakeholders to generate widespread and long lasting support within the policy community.  Only such support will sustain the policies through multiple election cycles and lengthy court battles.</p></div><div type="head_1"><head>Conclusion</head><p>	Overall, therefore, Barack Obama should negotiate a bipartisan compromise on CTL incentives within the compromise H.R. 6 bill.  In doing so, he can help to solve the national security and climate problems, as well as seize a number of political benefits, including electoral boosts from his new brand of consensus politics, national security strength, economic foresight, and environmental stewardship.  It should also help to simply pass the bill.  Though such a policy program will likely face hard implementation problems across the spectrum, sufficient mandates and funding should compel DOE to implement efficiently.  Now is the time for action.</p></div></div><div type="closer"><div type="appendix"><p rend="head_1">Appendix I</p><p>In this paper, Barack Obama (D-IL) is advised on the subject of coal-to-liquids (CTL) incentives.  He is the junior senator from Illinois, elected in November 2004 after a seven year stint in the Illinois State Senate.  He won 70% of the vote in a landslide victory after the Republican candidate, Jack Ryan, was forced to withdraw following a sex scandal.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn46"/>  He is currently pursuing the Democratic nomination for president, polling second behind Hillary Clinton with 24% to her 39%.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn47"/>  He was involved in promoting his state's struggling coal industry as a state senator and introduced the American Fuels Act, which did not include environmental safeguards, on January 4, 2007 to promote CTL. <ptr type="footnote" target="fn48"/>  Since that time, he has received significant criticism from environmental groups and now states that he will only support CTL incentives with a 20% decrease in lifecycle CO2 emissions relative to gasoline.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn49"/>  In June, he voted for an amendment to H.R. 6 that would have created incentives with a 20% decrease in lifecycle CO2 emissions.  The League of Conservation Voters awarded him a 95 rating in 2005 and 100 in 2006, generally approving of his environmental policies.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn50"/>  He is not heavily funded by energy interests ($489,909 of a total of $59,661,650)<ptr type="footnote" target="fn51"/>, though the 6th largest donor ($194,750) to his presidential campaign is the Illinois utility Exelon<ptr type="footnote" target="fn52"/>, which could conceivably receive CTL incentives.</p><p>The decision presented takes place early in the week of December 3rd, 2007.  The deal over CAFÉ standards within the H.R. 6 compromise bill has been reached, but the full compromise bill has not been finalized, nor has it been voted on.  The decision will be made within the informal negotiations that went on in lieu of a formal conference between the House and Senate.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn53"/></p><p rend="head_1">Appendix II</p><p rend="head_2">Brief Outline of CTL Incentives</p><p>Requirement: In order to receive these incentives, CTL companies must achieve a reduction in lifecycle CO2 emissions of 20% relative to conventional gasoline.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn54"/></p><p>Funding sources: All funding for incentives is incremental to DOE's existing budget.</p><p>Purpose statement: These provisions are for the creation of a robust coal-to-liquids (CTL) industry within the United States with the purpose of increasing energy independence, strengthening national security, and reducing emissions of energy related greenhouse gases.</p><list><item>I.) The Department of Energy will make available loan guarantees for CTL projects.</item><item>II.) The Department of Energy will provide production subsidies for CTL scaled to the price of oil.</item><item>III.) The Department of Energy will provide larger loan guarantees and production subsidies for CTL producers that achieve even greater lifecycle CO2 emissions reductions than required.</item><item>IV.) The Department of Energy will be allocated funds for and mandated to create a lifecycle CO2 analysis method for use within one year.</item><item>V.) The Department of Energy will be allocated funds for hiring and training staff and purchasing equipment for the monitoring of lifecycle CO2 emissions from CTL projects.</item></list><p>Note: This outline is only one of a number of possible outcomes.  The exact funding and measures to be enacted will emerge from bipartisan negotiation.</p></div><div type="footnotes"><note type="footnote" id="fn1">1 World Energy Council. “Reserves-Coal,” February, 10, 2007, http://www.worldenergy.org/documents/coal_1_1.pdf, accessed 12/6/2007.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn2">2 Southern States Energy Board, “Building a Bridge to Energy Independence and to a Sustainable Energy Future,” July 2006, http://www.americanenergysecurity.org/AES%20Report.pdf, accessed on 10/16/2007.  132.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn3">3 Bartis, James. “Research and Development Issues for Producing Liquid Fuels from Coal,” September 2007, http://democrats.science.house.gov/Media/File/Commdocs/hearings/2007/energy/05sept/bartis_testimony.pdf, accessed 11/7/2007.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn4">4 Ibid.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn5">5 World Energy Council. “Reserves-Coal,” February, 10, 2007, http://www.worldenergy.org/documents/coal_1_1.pdf, accessed 12/6/2007.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn6">6 Andrews, Anthony. “Liquid Fuels from Coal, Natural Gas, and Biomass: Background and Policy,” August 15, 2007, http://opencrs.cdt.org/rpts/RL34133_20070815.pdf, accessed on 10/16/2007. 17.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn7">7 Ibid, 18.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn8">8 Ibid, 19.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn9">9 MacGillis, Alec and Mufson, Steven. “Coal Fuels a Debate Over Obama,” Washington Post, June 24, 2007, http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2007/06/23/AR2007062301424_pf.html, accessed on 12/4/2007.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn10">10 Ibid.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn11">11 Geman, Ben. “Energy Policy: House panel approves climate, biofuels, solar bills,” June 28, 2007, http://www.eenews.net.proxy.lib.umich.edu/EEDaily/2007/06/28/archive/4?terms=coal+to+liquids, accessed 10/16/2007.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn12">12 Kaplun, Alex. “Energy Policy: Senate shoots down pair of coal-to-liquids amendments,” June 19, 2007, http://www.eenews.net.proxy.lib.umich.edu/eenewspm/coal_liquids/2007/06/19/1, accessed 10/16/2007.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn13">13 Swibel, Matthew. “Coal's Many Friends,” Forbes, June 27, 2007, http://www.forbes.com/2007/06/26/coal-energy-congress-biz-beltway_cz_ms_0627beltway.html, accessed 10/16/2007.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn14">14 Geman, Ben and Kaplun, Alex. “Energy Policy: White House attacks energy bill compromise,” December 3, 2007, http://www.eenews.net/eenewspm/2007/12/03/archive/1?terms=energy+legislation, accessed 12/3/2007.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn15">15 Ibid. For example, the Renewable Portfolio Standard was still being negotiated.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn16">16 Geman, Ben. “Energy Policy: Grassley says oil industry taxes are key to energy deal,” November 14, 2007, http://www.eenews.net/EEDaily/2007/11/14/archive/3?terms=coal+to+liquids, accessed 11/20/2007.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn17">17 Sandalow, David. Freedom from Oil. New York: McGraw Hill, 2008. 21-25.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn18">18 Southern States Energy Board, “Building a Bridge to Energy Independence and to a Sustainable Energy Future,” July 2006, http://www.americanenergysecurity.org/AES%20Report.pdf, accessed on 10/16/2007.  132.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn19">19 Andrews, Edmund. “Lawmakers Push for Big Subsidies for Coal Producers,” The New York Times, May 28, 2007, http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/29/business/29coal.html?pagewanted=1, accessed 10/16/2007.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn20">20 Williams, Robert; Larson, Eric and Jin, Haiming, “F-T Liquids Production from Coal and Coal + Biomass with CO2 Capture and Alternative Storage Options: Aquifer CO2 Storage vs CO2-Enhanced Oil Recovery,” January 13, 2006, http://www.colorado.edu/law/eesi/Background_Paper.pdf, accessed 12/5/2007.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn21">21 Bartis, James. “Research and Development Issues for Producing Liquid Fuels from Coal,” September 2007, http://democrats.science.house.gov/Media/File/Commdocs/hearings/2007/energy/05sept/bartis_testimony.pdf, accessed 11/7/2007.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn22">22 Geman, Ben. “Coal: CTL promoters add biomass to curb emissions, boost image,” September 25, 2007, http://www.eenews.net/Greenwire/2007/09/25/archive/1?terms=coal+to+liquids, accessed 10/16/07.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn23">23 Bartis, James. “Research and Development Issues for Producing Liquid Fuels from Coal,” September 2007, http://democrats.science.house.gov/Media/File/Commdocs/hearings/2007/energy/05sept/bartis_testimony.pdf, accessed 11/7/2007.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn24">24 Ibid.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn25">25 Freerks, Robert. “The Benefits and Challenges of Producing Liquid Fuel from Coal: The Role of Federal Research,” September 5, 2007, http://democrats.science.house.gov/Media/File/Commdocs/hearings/2007/energy/05sept/freerks_testimony.pdf, accessed on 12/5/2007.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn26">26 Bartis, James. “Research and Development Issues for Producing Liquid Fuels from Coal,” September 2007, http://democrats.science.house.gov/Media/File/Commdocs/hearings/2007/energy/05sept/bartis_testimony.pdf, accessed 11/7/2007.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn27">27Jones, Jeffrey. “Clinton Still has Big Lead Despite Drop in Support,” December 4, 2007, http://www.gallup.com/poll/103042/Clinton-Still-Has-Big-Lead-Despite-Drop-Support.aspx, accessed 12/5/2007.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn28">28 Rasmussen Reports. “Trust &amp; Importance on Issues,” November 2007, http://www.rasmussenreports.com/public_content/politics/issues__1/trust_importance_on_issues, accessed 12/4/2007.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn29">29 Freerks, Robert. “The Benefits and Challenges of Producing Liquid Fuel from Coal: The Role of Federal Research,” September 5, 2007, http://democrats.science.house.gov/Media/File/Commdocs/hearings/2007/energy/05sept/freerks_testimony.pdf, accessed on 12/5/2007.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn30">30 Lavelle, Marianne. “Coal-to-Liquid Technology Entices Congress,” U.S. News &amp; World Report, June 13, 2007, http://www.usnews.com/usnews/biztech/articles/070613/13coal.htm, accessed 10/16/2007.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn31">31 Rasmussen Reports. “Trust &amp; Importance on Issues,” November 2007, http://www.rasmussenreports.com/public_content/politics/issues__1/trust_importance_on_issues, accessed 12/4/2007.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn32">32 Obtained by comparing the map from Wikipedia. “Swing States,” http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Swing_states, accessed 12/6/2007; to the data from National Mining Assocation. “U.S. Coal Reserves by State and Type – 2006,” November 2007, http://www.nma.org/pdf/c_reserves.pdf, accessed 12/6/2007.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn33">33 Wikipedia, “United States Electoral College,” http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/U.S._Electoral_College, accessed 12/6/2007.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn34">34 Iowa Department of Natural Resources. “Iowa Coal Geology,” http://www.igsb.uiowa.edu/inforsch/coalkyst.htm, accessed 12/5/2007.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn35">35 National Mining Assocation. “U.S. Coal Reserves by State and Type – 2006,” November 2007, http://www.nma.org/pdf/c_reserves.pdf, accessed 12/6/2007.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn36">36 Iowa Caucus 2008. “Iowa Renewable Energy Facts,” 2007, http://www.iowacaucus.org/renewableenergy.html accessed 12/6/2007.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn37">37 Jones, Jeffrey. “Clinton Still has Big Lead Despite Drop in Support,” December 4, 2007, http://www.gallup.com/poll/103042/Clinton-Still-Has-Big-Lead-Despite-Drop-Support.aspx, accessed 12/5/2007.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn38">38 RasmussenReports. “Democratic Iowa Caucus,” November 29, 2007, accessed 12/6/2007.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn39">39 Geman, Ben and Kaplun, Alex. “Energy Policy: White House attacks energy bill compromise,” December 3, 2007, http://www.eenews.net/eenewspm/2007/12/03/archive/1?terms=energy+legislation, accessed 12/3/2007.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn40">40 Geman, Ben. “Energy Policy: White House letter outlines veto threshold on energy,” October 16, 2007, http://www.eenews.net/EEDaily/2007/10/16/archive/1, accessed 12/5/2007.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn41">41 Hawkins, David. “Hearing on benefits and Challenges of Producing Liquid Fuel from Coal,” September 5, 2007, http://democrats.science.house.gov/Media/File/Commdocs/hearings/2007/energy/05sept/hawkins_testimony.pdf, accessed 10/16/2007.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn42">42 Romm, Joseph. “Statement of Dr. Joseph Romm,” September 5, 2007, http://democrats.science.house.gov/Media/File/Commdocs/hearings/2007/energy/05sept/romm_testimony.pdf,  accessed 10/16/2007.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn43">43 Mufson, Steve. “Democrats Push Coal-to-Liquids Energy Plan,” Washington Post, June 13, 2007, http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2007/06/12/AR2007061202127.html, accessed 10/16/2007.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn44">44 Hurowitz, Glenn. “Flirting with Liquid Coal,” June 26, 2007, http://www.prospect.org/cs/articles?article=flirting_with_liquid_coal, accessed 10/16/2007.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn45">45 This is the level that Obama requires for support of CTL incentives, per phone interview of Obama LC Amrit Mehra on December 6, 2007.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn46">46 Wikipedia. “United States Senate elections, 2004,” http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_Senate_elections,_2004, accessed 12/6/2007; and Wikipedia. “Jack Ryan (Senate Candidate),” http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jack_Ryan_%28Senate_candidate%29, accessed 12/6/2007.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn47">47 Jones, Jeffrey. “Clinton Still has Big Lead Despite Drop in Support,” December 4, 2007, http://www.gallup.com/poll/103042/Clinton-Still-Has-Big-Lead-Despite-Drop-Support.aspx, accessed 12/5/2007.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn48">48 MacGillis, Alec and Mufson, Steven. “Coal Fuels a Debate Over Obama,” Washington Post, June 24, 2007, http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2007/06/23/AR2007062301424_pf.html, accessed on 12/4/2007.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn49">49 Phone Interview with Obama Legislative Correspondent, Amrit Mehra, December 6, 2007.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn50">50 League of Conservation Voters, “Senator Barack Obama (D),” http://presidentialprofiles2008.org/Obama/tab1.html, accessed 12/6/2007.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn51">51 Opensecrets.org. “Contributions by Sector,” http://www.opensecrets.org/pres08/sector.asp?id=N00009638&amp;cycle=2008, accessed on 12/5/2007.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn52">52 Opensecrets.org. “Top Contributors,” http://www.opensecrets.org/pres08/contrib.asp?id=N00009638&amp;cycle=2008, accessed on 12/5/2007.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn53">53 Mufson, Steven. “Pelosi Plans Informal Negotiations on Energy Bill,” Washington Post, October 11, 2007, http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2007/10/10/AR2007101002399.html, accessed 12/6/2007.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn54">54 This is the level that Obama requires for support of CTL incentives, per phone interview of Obama LC Amrit Mehra on December 6, 2007.</note></div></div></body></text></TEI.2>