<TEI.2><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Paper review for Fluvial Ecosystems</title><author>anonymized</author></titleStmt><wordcount>858</wordcount><editionStmt><edition>Version 1.0</edition></editionStmt><extent>insert_extent</extent><publicationStmt><idno>NRE.G1.22.2</idno><publisher>The University of Michigan</publisher><pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan, USA</pubPlace><date>2007</date><availability><p>The MICUSP project is owned by the Regents of the University of Michigan, who hold the copyright. The database has been developed by the English Language Institute. The original text submissions are stored electronically in the English Language Institute and may be consulted by bona fide researchers under special arrangements. The database is available by password on the World Wide Web for study, teaching and research purposes. Copies of the text files may be distributed, as long as either this statement of availability or the citation given below appears in the text. However, if any portion of this material is to be used for commercial purposes, such as for textbooks or tests, permission must be obtained in advance and a license fee may be required. For further information about copyright permissions, please inquire at micusp@umich.edu.</p><p>The recommended citation for MICASE is: Ädel, A., J. M. Swales, and J. Sielaff. (2007) The Michigan Corpus of Upper-level Student Papers. Ann Arbor, MI: The Regents of the University of Michigan.</p></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>The Michigan Corpus of Upper-level Student Papers (MICUSP)</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><p>This document derives from an unpublished, student-authored paper contributed in electronic format.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>For information on corpus compilation and encoding practices, see the MICUSP Handbook.</p></projectDesc><classDecl><taxonomy><category><catDesc>departments</catDesc><category id="BIO"><catDesc>Biology</catDesc></category><category id="CEE"><catDesc>Civil and Environmental Engineering</catDesc></category><category id="CLS"><catDesc>Classical Studies</catDesc></category><category id="ECO"><catDesc>Economics</catDesc></category><category id="EDU"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category id="ENG"><catDesc>English</catDesc></category><category id="IOE"><catDesc>Industrial and Operational Engineering</catDesc></category><category id="LIN"><catDesc>Linguistics</catDesc></category><category id="MEC"><catDesc>Mechanical Engineering</catDesc></category><category id="NRE"><catDesc>Natural Resources</catDesc></category><category id="NUR"><catDesc>Nursing</catDesc></category><category id="PHI"><catDesc>Philosophy</catDesc></category><category id="PHY"><catDesc>Physics</catDesc></category><category id="POL"><catDesc>Political Science</catDesc></category><category id="PSY"><catDesc>Psychology</catDesc></category><category id="SOC"><catDesc>Sociology</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>student levels</catDesc><category id="G0"><catDesc>senior undergraduate</catDesc></category><category id="G1"><catDesc>first-year graduate</catDesc></category><category id="G2"><catDesc>second-year graduate</catDesc></category><category id="G3"><catDesc>third-year graduate and up</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>student-reported text types</catDesc><category id="CaseStudy"><catDesc>case study</catDesc></category><category id="Critique"><catDesc>critique</catDesc></category><category id="LiteratureReview"><catDesc>literature review</catDesc></category><category id="ResearchProposal"><catDesc>research proposal</catDesc></category><category id="ResponsePaper"><catDesc>response paper</catDesc></category><category id="TechnicalOrLabReport"><catDesc>technical report or lab report</catDesc></category><category id="TermPaper"><catDesc>term paper</catDesc></category><category id="OtherTextType"><catDesc>other</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>approximate preparation times</catDesc><category id="OneToThreeDays"><catDesc>1-3 days</catDesc></category><category id="FourToTenDays"><catDesc>4-10 days</catDesc></category><category id="TwoToThreeWeeks"><catDesc>2-3 weeks</catDesc></category><category id="ThreeToSixWeeks"><catDesc>3-6 weeks</catDesc></category><category id="OneFullSemester"><catDesc>one full semester</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>sources of feedback</catDesc><category id="NoFeedback"><catDesc>no feedback from others</catDesc></category><category id="PrimaryInstructor"><catDesc>primary course instructor</catDesc></category><category id="GSI"><catDesc>Graduate Student Instructor (teaching assistant)</catDesc></category><category id="WritingTutor"><catDesc>writing tutor</catDesc></category><category id="FriendOrClassmate"><catDesc>friend or classmate</catDesc></category><category id="OtherFeedback"><catDesc>other</catDesc></category></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><creation>Paper submitted to instructor in Oct 2008</creation><particDesc><person id="P613" sex="f" age="TwentyFourToThirty"><affiliation>Natural Resources</affiliation><firstLang>English</firstLang><dominantLang>English</dominantLang><englishInPrimarySchool value="NO"/><englishInSecondarySchool value="NO"/><englishInUndergraduate value="NO"/><langKnown/></person></particDesc><textClass><catRef target="NRE G1 Essay TermPaper OneToThreeDays NoFeedback"><classification><primary>Argumentative Essay</primary><secondary>Report</secondary></classification><classification><primary>Argumentative Essay</primary><secondary/></classification><features><feature type="Reference to sources"/></features></catRef></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change><date>2009-05-29</date><respStmt><name>Emily Lin</name><resp>coder</resp></respStmt><item>manual adjustment of tags</item></change><change><date>2007-05-22</date><respStmt><name>Gregory Garretson</name><resp>programmer</resp></respStmt><item>initial (automated) encoding in XML</item></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="opener"><p/></div><div type="main"><p>﻿The paper <i type="title">Basic Principles and Ecological Consequences of Altered Flow Regimes in Biodiversity</i> by Bunn and Arthington (2002) condenses a great deal of information about the effects of altered flow regimes on biodiversity into one comprehensive literature review. The paper gives an overview of the current body of knowledge on the topic, suggests gaps in the understanding, and indicates further research needed to effectively manage changing flow regimes to best protect biological diversity. Overall it is a useful summary of the relationship between flow regime change and biodiversity, but it’s somewhat limited scope means that it should be used together with other information to develop further research and management agendas.</p><p>The authors’ objectives are clearly articulated in the papers introduction, stating that <q type="quote">the primary goal of the review is to illustrate how altering flow regime affects aquatic biodiversity in streams and rivers.</q> The introduction highlights the significant influence of flow regime on lotic habitats and stresses its important influence on the system’s biological diversity. However, an argument for maintaining biological diversity is less explicit. Although the need to preserve biodiversity is almost universally accepted, it may be useful to describe more general implications for the information in the introduction to keep the study’s overall importance in context.</p><p>Because this is a literature review, the methods are brief and included in the introduction rather than in a section of their own. Although it can be difficult to quantify literature review methods, this characteristic lends itself to criticism because it circumvents the basic scientific requisite of study repeatability. Without a way to standardize a review there is no way to prove that the study has looked at all relevant literature on the topic, and there may be bias in the results. For instance, an author can select only literature that supports the point they want to make, while ignoring other relevant literature that may not support their objective. With such a broad topic it can be difficult to use a standardized method (such as using meta-analysis to combine similar data from many different studies.) However, there has been a recent movement in conservation and ecological management toward standardizing systematic review methods to strengthen the utility of such reviews in policy and management situations. This standardized system is based on methods used in the health services sector and uses consistent search methods, evaluates the quality of studies referenced, and provides quantitative analysis of the collected literatures’ results. (University of Birmingham, 2006) Using a method like this would strengthen the paper’s arguments, making the paper a stronger tool for river management decisions.</p><p>Methods aside, the literature review is well organized and clearly addresses the objectives of the study, illustrating the mechanisms by which altered flow regimes affect biodiversity. Splitting the flow regime’s effect on biodiversity into four principle mechanisms is effective, breaking down the issues into separate and understandable pieces. In addition the support from the literature is diverse, providing ample evidence of how change in flow regime affects each aspect of the habitat over a wide range of geography and scale, giving the paper broad applicability. Figure one is especially helpful in relating the four principle effects of flow change to each aspect of an organism’s needs, providing a graphical representation of this information. The paper also provides lists of all effects addressed in the reviewed literature, providing useful organization of the information for quick and comprehensive future reference. </p><p>However, by using a limited selection of literature it is possible that the authors have not explored every influence of flow regime change on biological diversity. For instance, they did not look at the fact that there is often a change in natural equilibrium between moving water and moving sediment due to human induced flow change (Dunne and Leopold, 1978) which could potentially influence success of organisms and thus the biological diversity of an altered system. Also, it would have been helpful to compare anthropocentric flow change with naturally occurring flow change and its broad effects on community structure (Poff and Ward, 1989.)</p><p>Although the authors did not provide an exhaustive evaluation of all possible biotic effects of flow change, they did provide a broad overview of the impacts change has on biological diversity. Their discussion of the difficulty with separating flow regime change from other human driven impacts is important, and they make an excellent assertion that future manipulative research is needed to separate these variables. Overall the paper gives a good background of flow change and its impact on biological diversity, providing an important tool for management and research. However, as is not completely comprehensive it should not be used alone, but also with other resources to determine best management practices in instances where flow regime changes are necessary.</p></div><div type="closer"><div type="bibliography"><head>References:</head><listBibl><bibl>Bunn, S.E., and A.H. Arthington.&#160;2002.&#160;Basic principles and ecological consequences of altered flow regimes for aquatic biodiversity.&#160;Environmental Management 30:492-507.</bibl><bibl>Dunne, T., and L.B. Leopold.&#160;1978.&#160;Water in environmental planning.&#160;W.H. Freeman and Co., New York.</bibl><bibl>Poff, N.L., and J.V. Ward.&#160;1989.&#160;Implications of streamflow variability and predictability for lotic community structure: a regional analysis of streamflow patterns.&#160;Canadian </bibl><bibl>University of Birmingham, Centre for Evidence Based Conservation. Guidelines for Systematic Review in Conservation and Environmental Management. Version 2.0, August 2006.</bibl></listBibl></div></div></body></text></TEI.2>