<TEI.2><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Review of Zheng: Optimality of (S,s) Policies</title><author>anonymized</author></titleStmt><wordcount>609</wordcount><editionStmt><edition>Version 1.0</edition></editionStmt><extent>insert_extent</extent><publicationStmt><idno>IOE.G2.02.1</idno><publisher>The University of Michigan</publisher><pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan, USA</pubPlace><date>2007</date><availability><p>The MICUSP project is owned by the Regents of the University of Michigan, who hold the copyright. The database has been developed by the English Language Institute. The original text submissions are stored electronically in the English Language Institute and may be consulted by bona fide researchers under special arrangements. The database is available by password on the World Wide Web for study, teaching and research purposes. Copies of the text files may be distributed, as long as either this statement of availability or the citation given below appears in the text. However, if any portion of this material is to be used for commercial purposes, such as for textbooks or tests, permission must be obtained in advance and a license fee may be required. For further information about copyright permissions, please inquire at micusp@umich.edu.</p><p>The recommended citation for MICASE is: Ädel, A., J. M. Swales, and J. Sielaff. (2007) The Michigan Corpus of Upper-level Student Papers. Ann Arbor, MI: The Regents of the University of Michigan.</p></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>The Michigan Corpus of Upper-level Student Papers (MICUSP)</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><p>This document derives from an unpublished, student-authored paper contributed in electronic format.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>For information on corpus compilation and encoding practices, see the MICUSP Handbook.</p></projectDesc><classDecl><taxonomy><category><catDesc>departments</catDesc><category id="BIO"><catDesc>Biology</catDesc></category><category id="CEE"><catDesc>Civil and Environmental Engineering</catDesc></category><category id="CLS"><catDesc>Classical Studies</catDesc></category><category id="ECO"><catDesc>Economics</catDesc></category><category id="EDU"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category id="ENG"><catDesc>English</catDesc></category><category id="IOE"><catDesc>Industrial and Operational Engineering</catDesc></category><category id="LIN"><catDesc>Linguistics</catDesc></category><category id="MEC"><catDesc>Mechanical Engineering</catDesc></category><category id="NRE"><catDesc>Natural Resources</catDesc></category><category id="NUR"><catDesc>Nursing</catDesc></category><category id="PHI"><catDesc>Philosophy</catDesc></category><category id="PHY"><catDesc>Physics</catDesc></category><category id="POL"><catDesc>Political Science</catDesc></category><category id="PSY"><catDesc>Psychology</catDesc></category><category id="SOC"><catDesc>Sociology</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>student levels</catDesc><category id="G0"><catDesc>senior undergraduate</catDesc></category><category id="G1"><catDesc>first-year graduate</catDesc></category><category id="G2"><catDesc>second-year graduate</catDesc></category><category id="G3"><catDesc>third-year graduate and up</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>student-reported text types</catDesc><category id="CaseStudy"><catDesc>case study</catDesc></category><category id="Critique"><catDesc>critique</catDesc></category><category id="LiteratureReview"><catDesc>literature review</catDesc></category><category id="ResearchProposal"><catDesc>research proposal</catDesc></category><category id="ResponsePaper"><catDesc>response paper</catDesc></category><category id="TechnicalOrLabReport"><catDesc>technical report or lab report</catDesc></category><category id="TermPaper"><catDesc>term paper</catDesc></category><category id="OtherTextType"><catDesc>other</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>approximate preparation times</catDesc><category id="OneToThreeDays"><catDesc>1-3 days</catDesc></category><category id="FourToTenDays"><catDesc>4-10 days</catDesc></category><category id="TwoToThreeWeeks"><catDesc>2-3 weeks</catDesc></category><category id="ThreeToSixWeeks"><catDesc>3-6 weeks</catDesc></category><category id="OneFullSemester"><catDesc>one full semester</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>sources of feedback</catDesc><category id="NoFeedback"><catDesc>no feedback from others</catDesc></category><category id="PrimaryInstructor"><catDesc>primary course instructor</catDesc></category><category id="GSI"><catDesc>Graduate Student Instructor (teaching assistant)</catDesc></category><category id="WritingTutor"><catDesc>writing tutor</catDesc></category><category id="FriendOrClassmate"><catDesc>friend or classmate</catDesc></category><category id="OtherFeedback"><catDesc>other</catDesc></category></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><creation>Paper submitted to instructor in Sep 2004</creation><particDesc><person id="P218" sex="m" age="TwentyFourToThirty"><affiliation>IOE</affiliation><firstLang>English</firstLang><dominantLang>English</dominantLang><englishInPrimarySchool value="YES"/><englishInSecondarySchool value="YES"/><englishInUndergraduate value="YES"/></person></particDesc><textClass><catRef target="IOE G2 Report LiteratureReview OneToThreeDays NoFeedback"><classification><primary>Report</primary><secondary>Response Paper</secondary></classification><classification><primary>Report</primary><secondary>Response Paper</secondary></classification><features/></catRef></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change><date>2008-03-28</date><respStmt><name>Geoffrey Ho</name><resp>coder</resp></respStmt><item>manual adjustment of tags</item></change><change><date>2008-08-04</date><respStmt><name>Beilei Zhang</name><resp>coder</resp></respStmt><item>manual adjustment of tags</item></change><change><date>2007-05-22</date><respStmt><name>Gregory Garretson</name><resp>programmer</resp></respStmt><item>initial (automated) encoding in XML</item></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="opener"><p/></div><div type="main"><p>In his paper <i type="title">A simple proof for optimality of (S, s) policies</i>, Yu-Sheng Zheng calls upon the results of stationary optimal solutions to infinite-horizon inventory management problems to simplify previously complicated proofs of optimality.  Referring mainly to the seminal work of Inglehart, Zheng reports that earlier proofs of the optimality of a stationary (S, s) policy were unnecessarily tedious because their authors depended upon the results of the finite-horizon case.  The problem arose because in the finite horizon case, one must account for end-of-horizon effects, and therefore the proofs were <q type="quote">capable of characterizing only the <i>form</i> of an optimal policy, rather than the optimal policy <i>itself</i>.</q>  Zheng uses Markov decision process theory to show that the optimal policy consists of just two parameters: S* and s*, and that it holds for the case with fixed-plus linear ordering costs and quasiconvex holding and shortage costs.  He is able to derive the proof for both the discounted and the average cost models.</p><p>An (S, s) policy stipulates that a decision maker need not order any additional units if the inventory level lies between two integers s and S, S &gt; s; if the inventory level falls below s, then he should reorder a quantity such that the new inventory level becomes S.  Hence, the range of possible inventory positions is bounded above by S and unbounded below.  The goal of such a policy is to simultaneously minimize the costs of carrying too much or too little inventory and the cost of reordering.</p><p>Because the problem is over an infinite horizon, it is not necessary to formulate a dynamic programming functional equation.  Rather, Zheng gives the total expected <gap desc="formula"/>-discounted cost with initial inventory level <i>i</i> as a function of the policy (s, S):</p><gap desc="formula"/><p>where <gap desc="formula"/> represents the expected <gap desc="formula"/>-discounted inventory and holding costs until the inventory level drops to or below s given initial inventory <i>i</i>, and <gap desc="formula"/> represents the expected discounted time to deplete <i>j</i> units of inventory.</p><p>The challenge then becomes how to classify the values s and S that minimize the above function.  Zheng first shows that there do exist parameters S* and s* which bound a region of inventory levels producing minimal expected costs.  Then, using such an S* and s*, he shows case-wise (where the cases are for initial inventories at or below s*, between S* and s*, and greater than S*) that <gap desc="formula"/> satisfies the optimality equation </p><gap desc="formula"/><p>After having then shown that <gap desc="formula"/> satisfies the optimality equation for all possible initial inventory positions, he concludes that there exists an optimal stationary (s, S) policy.</p><p>He lastly turns his attention to the average cost model.  To make the costs bounded, he relaxes the problem to one where inventory can in fact take on values greater than S and thus allowing for negative orders.  However, he is quick to point out that intuitively, this would never happen optimally.</p><p>Personally, I didn't find Zheng's proofs to be <q type="soCalled">simple</q> as he called them.  Perhaps that is because we skipped (S, s) policies and spent little time on average cost models in my IOE 512 course.  However, I do appreciate the strength of the arguments that come by being able to use a stationary policy in the infinite horizon problem.  The paper assumes that the reader is familiar with the cost models used in a paper by Wagner and Veinott, which I was not, and also does a poor job of explaining the relationships between the cost models, which makes the proofs mildly inaccessible in my opinion.  Nevertheless, if Zheng's claim that all previous attempts at proofs of the infinite horizon (S, s) model rely on finite horizon results, then this paper is indeed significant.</p></div><div type="closer"><p/></div></body></text></TEI.2>