<TEI.2><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Design development for the Wight-Green Building</title><author>anonymized</author></titleStmt><wordcount>630</wordcount><editionStmt><edition>Version 1.0</edition></editionStmt><extent>insert_extent</extent><publicationStmt><idno>CEE.G0.05.2</idno><publisher>The University of Michigan</publisher><pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan, USA</pubPlace><date>2007</date><availability><p>The MICUSP project is owned by the Regents of the University of Michigan, who hold the copyright. The database has been developed by the English Language Institute. The original text submissions are stored electronically in the English Language Institute and may be consulted by bona fide researchers under special arrangements. The database is available by password on the World Wide Web for study, teaching and research purposes. Copies of the text files may be distributed, as long as either this statement of availability or the citation given below appears in the text. However, if any portion of this material is to be used for commercial purposes, such as for textbooks or tests, permission must be obtained in advance and a license fee may be required. For further information about copyright permissions, please inquire at micusp@umich.edu.</p><p>The recommended citation for MICASE is: Ädel, A., J. M. Swales, and J. Sielaff. (2007) The Michigan Corpus of Upper-level Student Papers. Ann Arbor, MI: The Regents of the University of Michigan.</p></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>The Michigan Corpus of Upper-level Student Papers (MICUSP)</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><p>This document derives from an unpublished, student-authored paper contributed in electronic format.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>For information on corpus compilation and encoding practices, see the MICUSP Handbook.</p></projectDesc><classDecl><taxonomy><category><catDesc>departments</catDesc><category id="BIO"><catDesc>Biology</catDesc></category><category id="CEE"><catDesc>Civil and Environmental Engineering</catDesc></category><category id="CLS"><catDesc>Classical Studies</catDesc></category><category id="ECO"><catDesc>Economics</catDesc></category><category id="EDU"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category id="ENG"><catDesc>English</catDesc></category><category id="IOE"><catDesc>Industrial and Operational Engineering</catDesc></category><category id="LIN"><catDesc>Linguistics</catDesc></category><category id="MEC"><catDesc>Mechanical Engineering</catDesc></category><category id="NRE"><catDesc>Natural Resources</catDesc></category><category id="NUR"><catDesc>Nursing</catDesc></category><category id="PHI"><catDesc>Philosophy</catDesc></category><category id="PHY"><catDesc>Physics</catDesc></category><category id="POL"><catDesc>Political Science</catDesc></category><category id="PSY"><catDesc>Psychology</catDesc></category><category id="SOC"><catDesc>Sociology</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>student levels</catDesc><category id="G0"><catDesc>senior undergraduate</catDesc></category><category id="G1"><catDesc>first-year graduate</catDesc></category><category id="G2"><catDesc>second-year graduate</catDesc></category><category id="G3"><catDesc>third-year graduate and up</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>student-reported text types</catDesc><category id="CaseStudy"><catDesc>case study</catDesc></category><category id="Critique"><catDesc>critique</catDesc></category><category id="LiteratureReview"><catDesc>literature review</catDesc></category><category id="ResearchProposal"><catDesc>research proposal</catDesc></category><category id="ResponsePaper"><catDesc>response paper</catDesc></category><category id="TechnicalOrLabReport"><catDesc>technical report or lab report</catDesc></category><category id="TermPaper"><catDesc>term paper</catDesc></category><category id="OtherTextType"><catDesc>other</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>approximate preparation times</catDesc><category id="OneToThreeDays"><catDesc>1-3 days</catDesc></category><category id="FourToTenDays"><catDesc>4-10 days</catDesc></category><category id="TwoToThreeWeeks"><catDesc>2-3 weeks</catDesc></category><category id="ThreeToSixWeeks"><catDesc>3-6 weeks</catDesc></category><category id="OneFullSemester"><catDesc>one full semester</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>sources of feedback</catDesc><category id="NoFeedback"><catDesc>no feedback from others</catDesc></category><category id="PrimaryInstructor"><catDesc>primary course instructor</catDesc></category><category id="GSI"><catDesc>Graduate Student Instructor (teaching assistant)</catDesc></category><category id="WritingTutor"><catDesc>writing tutor</catDesc></category><category id="FriendOrClassmate"><catDesc>friend or classmate</catDesc></category><category id="OtherFeedback"><catDesc>other</catDesc></category></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><creation>Paper submitted to instructor in Mar 2008</creation><particDesc><person id="P330" sex="f" age="TwentyToTwentyThree"><affiliation>Civil Engineering</affiliation><firstLang>English</firstLang><dominantLang>English</dominantLang><englishInPrimarySchool value="YES"/><englishInSecondarySchool value="YES"/><englishInUndergraduate value="YES"/></person></particDesc><textClass><catRef target="CEE G0 Report TechnicalOrLabReport OneToThreeDays PrimaryInstructor"><classification><primary>Report</primary><secondary>Response Paper</secondary></classification><classification><primary>Report</primary><secondary/></classification><features> </features></catRef></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change><date>2008-10-06</date><respStmt><name>Geoffrey Ho</name><resp>coder</resp></respStmt><item>manual adjustment of tags</item></change><change><date>2007-05-22</date><respStmt><name>Gregory Garretson</name><resp>programmer</resp></respStmt><item>initial (automated) encoding in XML</item></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="opener"><head>50% Design Development for Wight-Green Building</head><div type="introduction"><p>This document is to serve as the intermediate report of the design development for the Wight-Green Building, which is scheduled to be constructed in Ann Arbor, Michigan. ﻿</p></div></div><div type="main"><div type="head_1"><head>1.0 Summary of Completed Work</head><p>Wolverine Consultants has been working with the structural, environmental and geotechnical consultants, to gather design data and we are now at the 50% stage of the design development for the Wight-Green Building. Thus far the project has been phased for fast tracking and the building should ready for move in October 14, 2009. The projected project budget is currently just under $9.5 million, including the requested addition of a Starbucks on the first floor. A fit and finish package has been put together to address the needs of this 3000 ft2 retail space. A finalized construction management plan, including bid market analysis and packaging has also been completed, along with recommendations for the MEP system.</p></div><div type="head_1"><head>2.0 Preliminary Conclusions</head><div type="head_2"><head>2.1 Construction Management Plan</head><p>Wolverine Consultants had put together a construction management plan that will guide the team throughout the design and construction of the Wight-Green Building. We will be monitoring milestones in design and bidding, as well as construction, to keep the project on schedule. A packaging strategy has been developed that will include four phases; foundation systems, building frames systems, MEP systems and interior finishes. A strategy has also been developed for compliance and permitting through the city of Ann Arbor. A commissioning plan and turn over program are both being implemented to verify the installation of all systems in the building and to hand it over to the owner upon completion.</p></div><div type="head_2"><head>2.2 Budget</head><p>The projected project budget is currently just under $9.5 million.  This is up slightly from the interim report, where the budget was estimated to be $9 million. However, there is $600,000 contingency built into the budget, so that if any unforeseen events or difficulties arise during construction there is a considerable amount of protection from cost overruns.  There is still some uncertainty in areas such as the MEP system, glazing and earthwork, which can affect our budget. We will continue to monitor all components with expected variability and work with the other consultants to finalize the design and minimize this uncertainty. Consequently, we are still confident that the project can be completed for less than the requested budget of $10 million.</p></div><div type="head_2"><head>2.3 Schedule</head><p>The schedule has been phased for fast tracking. This will allow for construction documentation and bidding to occur simultaneously. According to our schedule the final design is expected to be completed April 15, 2008 and earthwork will commence June 13, 2008. The building is set for move in on October 14th 2009.</p></div><div type="head_2"><head>2.3 MEP Recommendation</head><p>Three systems were evaluated for the heating and cooling systems in the Wight-Green Building. Theses systems included a four-pipe fan coil system, water source heat pump system and a ground source closed loop geothermal system. After analysis, a ground source closed loop heat pump is recommended. This system is expected to have double first costs than the traditional systems, however with its energy savings and greater efficiency, a short pay back period is expected and well as increased occupant comfort.</p></div></div><div type="head_1"><head>3.0 Further Action</head><p>Thus far we have not come across any unforeseen problems that have put the project schedule and or budget outside the owner’s criteria. We will continue to work with the other consulting firms to complete the design and to keep the project on schedule and budget. The next planned deliverable will be the completion of the design development April 15, 2008.</p><p>We are enjoying working with you on this project and appreciate your business. If there are any questions you have for my team, please feel free to contact me at my office</p><p>Sincerely,</p><p>Project Manager</p></div></div><div type="closer"><p/></div></body></text></TEI.2>