<TEI.2><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>In what ways do spatial environments affect health?</title><author>anonymized</author></titleStmt><wordcount>369</wordcount><editionStmt><edition>Version 1.0</edition></editionStmt><extent>insert_extent</extent><publicationStmt><idno>SOC.G1.08.1</idno><publisher>The University of Michigan</publisher><pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan, USA</pubPlace><date>2007</date><availability><p>The MICUSP project is owned by the Regents of the University of Michigan, who hold the copyright. The database has been developed by the English Language Institute. The original text submissions are stored electronically in the English Language Institute and may be consulted by bona fide researchers under special arrangements. The database is available by password on the World Wide Web for study, teaching and research purposes. Copies of the text files may be distributed, as long as either this statement of availability or the citation given below appears in the text. However, if any portion of this material is to be used for commercial purposes, such as for textbooks or tests, permission must be obtained in advance and a license fee may be required. For further information about copyright permissions, please inquire at micusp@umich.edu.</p><p>The recommended citation for MICASE is: Ädel, A., J. M. Swales, and J. Sielaff. (2007) The Michigan Corpus of Upper-level Student Papers. Ann Arbor, MI: The Regents of the University of Michigan.</p></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>The Michigan Corpus of Upper-level Student Papers (MICUSP)</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><p>This document derives from an unpublished, student-authored paper contributed in electronic format.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>For information on corpus compilation and encoding practices, see the MICUSP Handbook.</p></projectDesc><classDecl><taxonomy><category><catDesc>departments</catDesc><category id="BIO"><catDesc>Biology</catDesc></category><category id="CEE"><catDesc>Civil and Environmental Engineering</catDesc></category><category id="CLS"><catDesc>Classical Studies</catDesc></category><category id="ECO"><catDesc>Economics</catDesc></category><category id="EDU"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category id="ENG"><catDesc>English</catDesc></category><category id="IOE"><catDesc>Industrial and Operational Engineering</catDesc></category><category id="LIN"><catDesc>Linguistics</catDesc></category><category id="MEC"><catDesc>Mechanical Engineering</catDesc></category><category id="NRE"><catDesc>Natural Resources</catDesc></category><category id="NUR"><catDesc>Nursing</catDesc></category><category id="PHI"><catDesc>Philosophy</catDesc></category><category id="PHY"><catDesc>Physics</catDesc></category><category id="POL"><catDesc>Political Science</catDesc></category><category id="PSY"><catDesc>Psychology</catDesc></category><category id="SOC"><catDesc>Sociology</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>student levels</catDesc><category id="G0"><catDesc>senior undergraduate</catDesc></category><category id="G1"><catDesc>first-year graduate</catDesc></category><category id="G2"><catDesc>second-year graduate</catDesc></category><category id="G3"><catDesc>third-year graduate and up</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>student-reported text types</catDesc><category id="CaseStudy"><catDesc>case study</catDesc></category><category id="Critique"><catDesc>critique</catDesc></category><category id="LiteratureReview"><catDesc>literature review</catDesc></category><category id="ResearchProposal"><catDesc>research proposal</catDesc></category><category id="ResponsePaper"><catDesc>response paper</catDesc></category><category id="TechnicalOrLabReport"><catDesc>technical report or lab report</catDesc></category><category id="TermPaper"><catDesc>term paper</catDesc></category><category id="OtherTextType"><catDesc>other</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>approximate preparation times</catDesc><category id="OneToThreeDays"><catDesc>1-3 days</catDesc></category><category id="FourToTenDays"><catDesc>4-10 days</catDesc></category><category id="TwoToThreeWeeks"><catDesc>2-3 weeks</catDesc></category><category id="ThreeToSixWeeks"><catDesc>3-6 weeks</catDesc></category><category id="OneFullSemester"><catDesc>one full semester</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>sources of feedback</catDesc><category id="NoFeedback"><catDesc>no feedback from others</catDesc></category><category id="PrimaryInstructor"><catDesc>primary course instructor</catDesc></category><category id="GSI"><catDesc>Graduate Student Instructor (teaching assistant)</catDesc></category><category id="WritingTutor"><catDesc>writing tutor</catDesc></category><category id="FriendOrClassmate"><catDesc>friend or classmate</catDesc></category><category id="OtherFeedback"><catDesc>other</catDesc></category></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><creation>Paper submitted to instructor in Nov 2007</creation><particDesc><person id="P273" sex="f" age="TwentyFourToThirty"><affiliation>Social Work and Sociology</affiliation><firstLang>English</firstLang><dominantLang>English</dominantLang><englishInPrimarySchool value="YES"/><englishInSecondarySchool value="YES"/><englishInUndergraduate value="YES"/></person></particDesc><textClass><catRef target="SOC G1 ResponsePaper ResponsePaper OneToThreeDays NoFeedback"><classification><primary>Response Paper</primary><secondary/></classification><classification><primary>Response Paper</primary><secondary>Argumentative Essay</secondary></classification><features/></catRef></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change><date>2009-02-04</date><respStmt><name>Geoffrey Ho</name><resp>coder</resp></respStmt><item>manual adjustment of tags</item></change><change><date>2007-05-22</date><respStmt><name>Gregory Garretson</name><resp>programmer</resp></respStmt><item>initial (automated) encoding in XML</item></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="opener"><head>In what ways do spatial environments affect health?  What kinds of policy implications are suggested by research on neighborhood effects?</head><p/></div><div type="main"><p/><p>      The quality of spatial environments has serious implications for health at both an individual and collective level.  Sociologists have demonstrated that the meso-level  impacts health across the lifespan from birth weight (Morenoff) to mortality in elderly populations (Klinenberg).  These effects are produced not by the individuals who inhabit different neighborhoods but by institutional and structural features of neighborhoods themselves.  In a review of the literature on <q type="quote">neighborhood effects</q> and social processes, Robert Sampson, Jeffery Morenoff and Thomas Gannon-Rowley note that meso-level social problems are often interrelated.  Poverty, crime, educational advancement, joblessness, and health interact dynamically—creating neighborhood <q type="quote">hot spots</q> where the sum total of these effects can often mean poor health at best and death at worst for those that inhabit them.  </p><p>      Klinenberg describes how neighborhood factors combined to create a perfect storm for the elderly, urban, poor during the Chicago heatwave  of 1995. The majority of these deaths were preventable simply by an air conditioner (and the ability to pay for its attendant costs). Yet, over 700 people died than normally do during this time of year. Social isolation resulting from neighborhood demographic changes, fear of the devastating financial and/or physical effects of crime in violent neighborhoods, lack of safe public spaces, and changes in the provision of social services resulted in the high death toll of seniors.  </p><p>      For example, seniors that lived in violent and even marginal neighborhoods were afraid to go out on the street because they knew that an attack, however unlikely, could result in death given their fragile health status. Along these lines, a robbery could have devastating financial consequences for those living on a limited income. Seniors that had access to shared public space that they perceived as safe where they could go to stay cool were more likely to survive. In this way, the conditions of the neighborhood had a clear causal influence on the whether a senior was able to survive the heatwave. </p><p>      James Kirby’s work further supports the link between health and spatial environments by demonstrating that access to health care is related to the rate of flux in neighborhood populations. </p></div><div type="closer"><p/></div></body></text></TEI.2>