<TEI.2><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Throwing Caution to the Wind</title><author>anonymized</author></titleStmt><wordcount>566</wordcount><editionStmt><edition>Version 1.0</edition></editionStmt><extent>insert_extent</extent><publicationStmt><idno>PSY.G0.19.2</idno><publisher>The University of Michigan</publisher><pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan, USA</pubPlace><date>2007</date><availability><p>The MICUSP project is owned by the Regents of the University of Michigan, who hold the copyright. The database has been developed by the English Language Institute. The original text submissions are stored electronically in the English Language Institute and may be consulted by bona fide researchers under special arrangements. The database is available by password on the World Wide Web for study, teaching and research purposes. Copies of the text files may be distributed, as long as either this statement of availability or the citation given below appears in the text. However, if any portion of this material is to be used for commercial purposes, such as for textbooks or tests, permission must be obtained in advance and a license fee may be required. For further information about copyright permissions, please inquire at micusp@umich.edu.</p><p>The recommended citation for MICASE is: Ädel, A., J. M. Swales, and J. Sielaff. (2007) The Michigan Corpus of Upper-level Student Papers. Ann Arbor, MI: The Regents of the University of Michigan.</p></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>The Michigan Corpus of Upper-level Student Papers (MICUSP)</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><p>This document derives from an unpublished, student-authored paper contributed in electronic format.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>For information on corpus compilation and encoding practices, see the MICUSP Handbook.</p></projectDesc><classDecl><taxonomy><category><catDesc>departments</catDesc><category id="BIO"><catDesc>Biology</catDesc></category><category id="CEE"><catDesc>Civil and Environmental Engineering</catDesc></category><category id="CLS"><catDesc>Classical Studies</catDesc></category><category id="ECO"><catDesc>Economics</catDesc></category><category id="EDU"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category id="ENG"><catDesc>English</catDesc></category><category id="IOE"><catDesc>Industrial and Operational Engineering</catDesc></category><category id="LIN"><catDesc>Linguistics</catDesc></category><category id="MEC"><catDesc>Mechanical Engineering</catDesc></category><category id="NRE"><catDesc>Natural Resources</catDesc></category><category id="NUR"><catDesc>Nursing</catDesc></category><category id="PHI"><catDesc>Philosophy</catDesc></category><category id="PHY"><catDesc>Physics</catDesc></category><category id="POL"><catDesc>Political Science</catDesc></category><category id="PSY"><catDesc>Psychology</catDesc></category><category id="SOC"><catDesc>Sociology</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>student levels</catDesc><category id="G0"><catDesc>senior undergraduate</catDesc></category><category id="G1"><catDesc>first-year graduate</catDesc></category><category id="G2"><catDesc>second-year graduate</catDesc></category><category id="G3"><catDesc>third-year graduate and up</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>student-reported text types</catDesc><category id="CaseStudy"><catDesc>case study</catDesc></category><category id="Critique"><catDesc>critique</catDesc></category><category id="LiteratureReview"><catDesc>literature review</catDesc></category><category id="ResearchProposal"><catDesc>research proposal</catDesc></category><category id="ResponsePaper"><catDesc>response paper</catDesc></category><category id="TechnicalOrLabReport"><catDesc>technical report or lab report</catDesc></category><category id="TermPaper"><catDesc>term paper</catDesc></category><category id="OtherTextType"><catDesc>other</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>approximate preparation times</catDesc><category id="OneToThreeDays"><catDesc>1-3 days</catDesc></category><category id="FourToTenDays"><catDesc>4-10 days</catDesc></category><category id="TwoToThreeWeeks"><catDesc>2-3 weeks</catDesc></category><category id="ThreeToSixWeeks"><catDesc>3-6 weeks</catDesc></category><category id="OneFullSemester"><catDesc>one full semester</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>sources of feedback</catDesc><category id="NoFeedback"><catDesc>no feedback from others</catDesc></category><category id="PrimaryInstructor"><catDesc>primary course instructor</catDesc></category><category id="GSI"><catDesc>Graduate Student Instructor (teaching assistant)</catDesc></category><category id="WritingTutor"><catDesc>writing tutor</catDesc></category><category id="FriendOrClassmate"><catDesc>friend or classmate</catDesc></category><category id="OtherFeedback"><catDesc>other</catDesc></category></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><creation>Paper submitted to instructor in Sep 2006</creation><particDesc><person id="P164" sex="f" age="TwentyToTwentyThree"><affiliation>Psychology</affiliation><firstLang>English</firstLang><dominantLang>English</dominantLang><englishInPrimarySchool value="YES"/><englishInSecondarySchool value="YES"/><englishInUndergraduate value="YES"/></person></particDesc><textClass><catRef target="PSY G0 ResponsePaper ResponsePaper OneToThreeDays FriendOrClassmate"><classification><primary>Response Paper</primary><secondary/></classification><classification><primary>Response Paper</primary><secondary/></classification><features/></catRef></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change><date>2009-08-11</date><respStmt><name>Lucas Jarmin</name><resp>coder</resp></respStmt><item>manual adjustment of tags</item></change><change><date>2007-11-09</date><respStmt><name>Yung-Hui Chien</name><resp>coder</resp></respStmt><item>manual adjustment of tags</item></change><change><date>2007-05-22</date><respStmt><name>Gregory Garretson</name><resp>programmer</resp></respStmt><item>initial (automated) encoding in XML</item></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="opener"><head>Throwing Caution to the Wind</head><p/></div><div type="main"><p>	Glancing at the VIA Signature Strengths survey I thought there were only 24 questions.  Honestly, I thought the 240 questions description in the introductory paragraph was a typo.  Alas, I went through the survey and in the end I am glad that there were ten questions for each strength.  In class we discussed how truthful the data from some of the other surveys could be, especially when a five-item questionnaire was supposed to show how satisfied with life a person is.  This survey, despite its length, examined more aspects of each item and I found that a little more reassuring when the final results were displayed.</p><p>	I was not surprised by my top strengths or my bottom strengths.  I was a little more confused by my results for the middle section.  Do I really have more optimism than love for learning?  I think I have more gratitude than zest, at least sometimes.  And why was my caution rating so low?  I have always considered myself to be a fairly caution individual and to be careful when taking risks, not to jump into situations unprepared.  As someone interested in quantitative psychology, I would have enjoyed seeing a scale for each response, similar to the other surveys we have taken.  That way it would be easier to interpret how the scale measures each item and how much differently the strengths were rated.  I felt that I had given pretty similar answers for some of the items and wondered if their ranking wasn't just arbitrary since they might have had the same overall score.  </p><p>	One aspect of the survey that I found very helpful was the description on the scores page.  The last sentence, <q type="quote">your top five, especially those marked as Signature Strengths, are the ones to pay attention to and find ways to use more often,</q> really struck out to me as a defining aspect of positive psychology.  Focus on the positive!  This statement reminded me of the article we read for this week, <q type="title">The Felicity of Virtue</q>.  It correlates with the idea that it is easier and more productive to focus on your strengths and to start making yourself a better person by working on traits that you already possess.  Instead of showing what your lowest strengths (seems like an oxymoron anyways…) are, the survey results displays the top five and urges the survey-taker to look at those and try to improve their daily life by using them more often.  </p><p>	In the same article the author concludes his first section by questioning whether the happiness hypothesis will be left to the cynic and to follow the Machiavellian and to fake it until you make it (pg. 158), roughly speaking using an AA saying and self-help guru mantra.   While I think the rest of the article brushes off the idea that this is the future of becoming a virtuous person, it's an interesting position to consider.  What are the benefits of faking it: you could be being nicer and helping others, other people could appreciate your efforts; you can start to examine your own mode of thinking and analyze your current actions; and you can practice a skill you want to master.  To me, that doesn't sound too bad.  Granted, you're being <q type="soCalled">fake</q> and <q type="soCalled">not real</q>, but if the goal is to become a greater person, I think the means justify the ends.  </p></div><div type="closer"><p/></div></body></text></TEI.2>