<TEI.2><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Mn (III) TPPS4: A Metallophorphryin Used for Tumor Identification in MRI</title><author>anonymized</author></titleStmt><wordcount>1509</wordcount><editionStmt><edition>Version 1.0</edition></editionStmt><extent>insert_extent</extent><publicationStmt><idno>BIO.G0.05.1</idno><publisher>The University of Michigan</publisher><pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan, USA</pubPlace><date>2007</date><availability><p>The MICUSP project is owned by the Regents of the University of Michigan, who hold the copyright. The database has been developed by the English Language Institute. The original text submissions are stored electronically in the English Language Institute and may be consulted by bona fide researchers under special arrangements. The database is available by password on the World Wide Web for study, teaching and research purposes. Copies of the text files may be distributed, as long as either this statement of availability or the citation given below appears in the text. However, if any portion of this material is to be used for commercial purposes, such as for textbooks or tests, permission must be obtained in advance and a license fee may be required. For further information about copyright permissions, please inquire at micusp@umich.edu.</p><p>The recommended citation for MICASE is: Ädel, A., J. M. Swales, and J. Sielaff. (2007) The Michigan Corpus of Upper-level Student Papers. Ann Arbor, MI: The Regents of the University of Michigan.</p></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>The Michigan Corpus of Upper-level Student Papers (MICUSP)</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><p>This document derives from an unpublished, student-authored paper contributed in electronic format.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>For information on corpus compilation and encoding practices, see the MICUSP Handbook.</p></projectDesc><classDecl><taxonomy><category><catDesc>departments</catDesc><category id="BIO"><catDesc>Biology</catDesc></category><category id="CEE"><catDesc>Civil and Environmental Engineering</catDesc></category><category id="CLS"><catDesc>Classical Studies</catDesc></category><category id="ECO"><catDesc>Economics</catDesc></category><category id="EDU"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category id="ENG"><catDesc>English</catDesc></category><category id="IOE"><catDesc>Industrial and Operational Engineering</catDesc></category><category id="LIN"><catDesc>Linguistics</catDesc></category><category id="MEC"><catDesc>Mechanical Engineering</catDesc></category><category id="NRE"><catDesc>Natural Resources</catDesc></category><category id="NUR"><catDesc>Nursing</catDesc></category><category id="PHI"><catDesc>Philosophy</catDesc></category><category id="PHY"><catDesc>Physics</catDesc></category><category id="POL"><catDesc>Political Science</catDesc></category><category id="PSY"><catDesc>Psychology</catDesc></category><category id="SOC"><catDesc>Sociology</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>student levels</catDesc><category id="G0"><catDesc>senior undergraduate</catDesc></category><category id="G1"><catDesc>first-year graduate</catDesc></category><category id="G2"><catDesc>second-year graduate</catDesc></category><category id="G3"><catDesc>third-year graduate and up</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>student-reported text types</catDesc><category id="CaseStudy"><catDesc>case study</catDesc></category><category id="Critique"><catDesc>critique</catDesc></category><category id="LiteratureReview"><catDesc>literature review</catDesc></category><category id="ResearchProposal"><catDesc>research proposal</catDesc></category><category id="ResponsePaper"><catDesc>response paper</catDesc></category><category id="TechnicalOrLabReport"><catDesc>technical report or lab report</catDesc></category><category id="TermPaper"><catDesc>term paper</catDesc></category><category id="OtherTextType"><catDesc>other</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>approximate preparation times</catDesc><category id="OneToThreeDays"><catDesc>1-3 days</catDesc></category><category id="FourToTenDays"><catDesc>4-10 days</catDesc></category><category id="TwoToThreeWeeks"><catDesc>2-3 weeks</catDesc></category><category id="ThreeToSixWeeks"><catDesc>3-6 weeks</catDesc></category><category id="OneFullSemester"><catDesc>one full semester</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>sources of feedback</catDesc><category id="NoFeedback"><catDesc>no feedback from others</catDesc></category><category id="PrimaryInstructor"><catDesc>primary course instructor</catDesc></category><category id="GSI"><catDesc>Graduate Student Instructor (teaching assistant)</catDesc></category><category id="WritingTutor"><catDesc>writing tutor</catDesc></category><category id="FriendOrClassmate"><catDesc>friend or classmate</catDesc></category><category id="OtherFeedback"><catDesc>other</catDesc></category></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><creation>Paper submitted to instructor in Apr 2005</creation><particDesc><person id="P75" sex="f" age="TwentyToTwentyThree"><affiliation>Biochemistry</affiliation><firstLang>English</firstLang><dominantLang>Mandarin</dominantLang><englishInPrimarySchool value="YES"/><englishInSecondarySchool value="YES"/><englishInUndergraduate value="YES"/></person></particDesc><textClass><catRef target="BIO G0 Report LiteratureReview TwoToThreeWeeks FriendOrClassmate"><classification><primary>Report</primary><secondary/></classification><classification><primary>Report</primary><secondary/></classification><features><feature type="Methodology section"/><feature type="Discussion of results section"/><feature type="Tables, graphs or figures"/><feature type="Reference to sources"/></features></catRef></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change><date>2007-05-24</date><respStmt><name>Jesse Sielaff</name><resp>coder</resp></respStmt><item>manual adjustment of tags</item></change><change><date>2009-07-23</date><respStmt><name>Beilei Zhang</name><resp>coder</resp></respStmt><item>manual adjustment of tags</item></change><change><date>2007-05-22</date><respStmt><name>Gregory Garretson</name><resp>programmer</resp></respStmt><item>initial (automated) encoding in XML</item></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="opener"><head>Mn (III) TPPS4: A metallophorphryin used for tumor identification in MRI</head><p/></div><div type="main"><p>From as early as 1948, scientists have studied the potential of porphryins and metalloporphyrins in cancer detection and therapy. For reasons unknown then, these compounds had high affinities for neoplasms (tumors) when injected into mice.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn1"/> In fact, porphyrin concentration was highest in and near necrotic areas (unprogrammed cell death). The potential for metalloporphyrins in tumor identification was further uncovered with the effects of paramagnetic substances on proton relaxation time of surrounding tissues.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn2"/> While X-ray imaging is used for bony, dense structures, Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI), an application of Nuclear Magnetic Resonance, has been used with soft tissues for decades.  The magnetic moments of paramagnetic species such as MnTPPS4 significantly enhance MRI signal in the soft tissues to which it is bound, making it an optimal contrast agent.</p><div type="head_1"><head>Synthesis</head><p>MnTPPS4 can be synthesized by heating meso-tetra(4-sulfonatophenyl)porphine (H2TPPS4) and manganese (II) acetate in acetic acid under reflux for 8 hours.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn4"/> Air bubbling through the reflux solution oxidizes Mn(II) to Mn(III). </p><gap desc="formula"/><p>The presence of MnTPPS4 and disappearance of H2TPPS4 can be confirmed with UV spectroscopy:</p><gap desc="figure"/><p rend="caption">Figure 1: Absorption spectra of equimolar aqueous solutions of H2TPPS4 (full line) and MnTPPS4 (dotted line) <ptr type="footnote" target="fn2"/></p><p>Additionally, the absorbance maxima of Mn(III)TPPS4 occur at 465, 561, and 593 nm, while the absorbance maxima of Mn(II)TPPS4 are at 434, 572, and 612 nm.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn3"/></p><p>While the synthesis of MnTPPS4 has been documented since the 1960's, and it is commercially available, it is a very polar molecule and is thus often contaminated with un-identified by- product. Bockhorst and coworkers<ptr type="footnote" target="fn4"/> proposed an optimized purification method: washing the product multiple times with hot </p><p>acetic acid, then hot ethanol, and dissolving in aqueous Na2CO3.</p><p>The solution is then filtered, acidified with HCl, centrifuged and dried; this procedure is done twice.  Finally, drying over KOH in a desiccator gives the desired product, a dark green, metallic solid, at 98% purity.  </p><p>Tetraphenylporphine sulfonate, TPPS4 can be synthesized by heating meso-tetraphenylporphine with concentrated sulfuric acid over a steam bath for 4h.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn5"/> Meso-tetraphenylporphine can be prepared by refluxing pyrrole and benzaldehyde in propionic acid.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn6"/></p></div><div type="head_1"><head>Structure</head><gap desc="figure"/><p>Figure 2: Mn(III)-tetrakis(4-sulfonatophenyl)porphin (MnTPPS4) Mol. Formula: MnC44H24N4O12S4ClNa4, MW=1111.3 g/mol *</p><p>*the ligands on the product from the synthesis described are SO3H instead of SO3 - Na+</p><p>Tetraphenylsulfonyl is a hydrophilic water-soluble porphryin with a highly developed π-conjugation system.  Its Mn(III) complex has been extensively studied as an MRI contrast agent. Mn(III) is a high spin d4 transition metal ion that has four unpaired electrons; it is thus paramagnetic. The geometry of the molecule is square planar, with the Mn(III) chelated by the four nitrogen atoms of a porphine that has four attached sulfonyl groups.</p></div><div type="head_1"><head>Discussion</head><p>Nuclear Magnetic Resonance is the observation of the frequency at which magnetic nuclei in molecules come into resonance with an externally applied electromagnetic field. The signal depends on a variety of factors, including field strength and</p><p>concentration. It follows that Magnetic Resonance Imaging is essentially a measure of proton density. When the magnetic field varies linearly across an object, the signal intensity is proportional to proton concentration.  Tumor identification is possible because of differences in relaxation rates of bulk water of normal tissues and tumors.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn3"/>   However, the difference is usually no more than 2-3 fold. T1, longitudinal relaxation time, is the taken by a proton to align with the external magnetic field.  As referenced by Runge and coworkers,<ptr type="footnote" target="fn7"/> longitudinal relation rate (1/T1) can be described by the following equation:</p><gap desc="formula"/><p>where ε is the viscosity of the solvent, k is the Boltzman constant, N is the concentration of ions,  T is the absolute temperature, and γ is the gyromagnetic ratio for the hydrogen nucleus.  The variable of interest is μ, the effective magnetic moment. As the equation shows, spin lattice rate (another name for 1/T1) is directly proportional to the square of μ. Paramagnetic species alter the local magnetic field to enhance proton relaxation (spin-lattice T1 and spin-spin relaxation T2 rates) of neighboring nuclei. T2, transverse magnetization time, is also tissue specific; it depends on the exchange of energy and interaction of spins with neighboring nuclei.  In essence, T2 measures decay of magnetization perpendicular to the main magnetic field. Through a complex set of equations, it can be determined that paramagnetic species also shortens T2.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn7"/> This is unfavorable, as a decrease in T2 weakens signal.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn7"/> An optimal contrast agent would therefore reduce T1, increasing spin lattice relaxation rate, without significantly compromising T2.</p><p>In the presence of an externally applied magnetic field, the magnetic moments of MnTPPS4 that were previously randomly aligned become preferentially aligned with the field.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn7"/> This local magnetic field produced by the paramagnetic species shortens T1 and T2 of surrounding protons in the tumor. This paramagnetic effect decreases with distance: </p><gap desc="formula"/><p>where r is the mean distance from paramagnetic center to the proton.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn3"/></p><p>Thus, an effective paramagnetic contrast agent should include a high spin, metal ion with a large magnetic moment and easily accessible axial coordination sites. Chen and coworkers<ptr type="footnote" target="fn3"/> demonstrated that spin lattice relaxation rate (1/T1) increases linearly with concentration of various metallo-TPPS4 complexes.  Of these, the slope is steepest with Mn(III) compared to various other ions and metallo-TPPS4 complexes (Figure 2).  It is the most effective in enhancing proton relaxation due to its four unpaired electrons and ability to coordinate axial ligands. While Mn(II) would have five unpaired electrons and theoretically induce an even shorter T1, Mn(II)TPPS4 is not as stable in solution as Mn(III)TPPS4  because it is readily oxidized.</p><p>A variety of paramagnetic species have been considered for use as MRI contrast agents - both free and chelated metal ions.  Aside from enhancing relaxation rates as determined in vitro, toxicity, stability in human plasma and at various pH, clearance from blood, and tissue distribution must also be taken into account when examining an MRI contrast agent.  NMR contrast media can also be classified by method of uptake into body: oral, intravenous, inhalational. Furthermore, blood transport bio distribution and relaxation efficiency are related to differences in binding and aggregation properties of the metalloporphyrin that</p><gap desc="figure"/><p>Figure 2: Spin lattice relaxation rate (l/Tr) of water as a function of concentration of metal ion or metallo-TPPS4 complex. Lines are least square fits: (___) Mn,  (- - -) Fe, (__  __) Cu. Symbols are for experimental data:(•) Mn(III) TPPS, (o) Mn(OAc) 3, () MnC12, () Fe(III)TPPS4, () FeCl3, () FeEDTA, () Cu(II)TPPS4, () CuC12 or CuSO4, () Cu(II)TPPS4-CH3.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn3"/></p><p>are dose dependent. For example, Fe(III) transforms into low spin dimers at physiological pH. It also aggregates on the surface of bovine serum albumin (mimicking human plasma) 5-7 times more than MnTPPS4; antiferromagnetic coupling between metals ions in the aggregates disables proton relaxation enhancement ability.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn8"/> Also, the dose of metal ions needed for clinical efficiency as a contrast agent is very toxic; chelating the ion significantly lowers toxicity.</p><p>Perhaps the most fundamental quality of any tumor identification/contrast agent is the ability to localize in tumors. This selective retention of porphyrins in tumors makes it of special interest in deep tumor detection. Figge and coworkers found that when porphryin was injected into tumor-bearing mice, most of it migrated to the tumor within 24-48 hours.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn9"/>  Porphyrin localization was directly observable by the red fluorescence in the tumors that lasted 10-14 days.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn9"/> It has been suggested that porphyrin aggregation is involved with tumor localization.10 Fiel and coworker also found that porphyrins tend to be localized mostly in soluble and stromal fractions (connective tissue).<ptr type="footnote" target="fn10"/> Mn(III)TPPS4 accumulated in tumors at ratios as high as 1.0:0.3:0.01 (tumor:liver:muscle). In analyzing subcelleular distribution of Mn(III)TPPS4, it was found that accumulation occurs mostly in the extracellular compartments of the tumor, possibly due to mechanism of localization that depends on volume; interstitial space in tumors is large enough to favor retention of large sized porphryins.  Finally, Figge and coworkers also noted that while hydrophobic porphyrins would be transported across cell membranes more easily, charged porphyrins (like Mn(III)TPPS4) would remain extracellular. <ptr type="footnote" target="fn10"/></p></div><div type="head_1"><head>Conclusion </head><p>Mn(III)TPPS4 has been extensively studied for its use as an MRI contrast agent.  Its paramagnetism gives it the ability to enhance proton relaxation time and enhance MRI signal, and its porphryin component is useful in tumor detection in that it is selectively retained in those tissues. Of various metallo-TPPS4 compounds studied, it is the most stable in vivo and thus an optimal contrast agent for detection of deep tumors.</p></div></div><div type="closer"><div type="footnotes"><note type="footnote" id="fn1">1 Figge, F.; Weiland, G.; Manangiello, L. Proc. Soc. Exptl. Biol. Med. 1948, 68, 640-641.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn2">2 Runge, V.M.; Clanton, J.A.; Lukehart, C.M.; Partain, C.L.; James, A.E. Jr. AJR. 1983, 141, 1209-1215.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn3">3 Chen, C; Cohen, J.S.; Myers, C.E.; Sohn, M. FEBS Lett. 1984, 168, 70-74.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn4">4 Bockhorst, K.; Hoehn-Beriage, M. Tetrahedron. 1994, 50, 8657.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn5">5 Srivastava, T.S.; Tsutsui, M. J. Org. Chem. 1973, 38, 2103.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn6">6 Adler, A.D.; Longo, F.R.; Finarelli, J.D.; Goldmacher, J.; Assour, J.; Korsakoff, L. J. Org. Chem. 1967, 32, 476.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn7">7 Runge, V.M.; Clanton, J.A.; Lukehart, C.M.; Partain, C.L.; James, A.E. Jr. AJR. 1983, 141, 1209-1215.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn8">8 Yushmanov, V.E.; Tominaga, T.T.; Borissevitch, I.E.; Imasato, H.; Tabak, M. MRI. 1996, 14, 255-261.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn9">9 Kessel, D. Biochem. Pharm. 1984, 33, 1389-1393.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn10">10 Fiel R.J.; Button, T.M.; Gilani, S.; Mark, E.H.; Musser, D.A. Cancer Letters. 1988, 40, 23-32.</note></div></div></body></text></TEI.2>