<TEI.2><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Plant Pollination Systems: Evolutionary Trends in Generalization and Specialization</title><author>anonymized</author></titleStmt><wordcount>622</wordcount><editionStmt><edition>Version 1.0</edition></editionStmt><extent>insert_extent</extent><publicationStmt><idno>BIO.G0.02.3</idno><publisher>The University of Michigan</publisher><pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan, USA</pubPlace><date>2007</date><availability><p>The MICUSP project is owned by the Regents of the University of Michigan, who hold the copyright. The database has been developed by the English Language Institute. The original text submissions are stored electronically in the English Language Institute and may be consulted by bona fide researchers under special arrangements. The database is available by password on the World Wide Web for study, teaching and research purposes. Copies of the text files may be distributed, as long as either this statement of availability or the citation given below appears in the text. However, if any portion of this material is to be used for commercial purposes, such as for textbooks or tests, permission must be obtained in advance and a license fee may be required. For further information about copyright permissions, please inquire at micusp@umich.edu.</p><p>The recommended citation for MICASE is: Ädel, A., J. M. Swales, and J. Sielaff. (2007) The Michigan Corpus of Upper-level Student Papers. Ann Arbor, MI: The Regents of the University of Michigan.</p></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>The Michigan Corpus of Upper-level Student Papers (MICUSP)</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><p>This document derives from an unpublished, student-authored paper contributed in electronic format.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>For information on corpus compilation and encoding practices, see the MICUSP Handbook.</p></projectDesc><classDecl><taxonomy><category><catDesc>departments</catDesc><category id="BIO"><catDesc>Biology</catDesc></category><category id="CEE"><catDesc>Civil and Environmental Engineering</catDesc></category><category id="CLS"><catDesc>Classical Studies</catDesc></category><category id="ECO"><catDesc>Economics</catDesc></category><category id="EDU"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category id="ENG"><catDesc>English</catDesc></category><category id="IOE"><catDesc>Industrial and Operational Engineering</catDesc></category><category id="LIN"><catDesc>Linguistics</catDesc></category><category id="MEC"><catDesc>Mechanical Engineering</catDesc></category><category id="NRE"><catDesc>Natural Resources</catDesc></category><category id="NUR"><catDesc>Nursing</catDesc></category><category id="PHI"><catDesc>Philosophy</catDesc></category><category id="PHY"><catDesc>Physics</catDesc></category><category id="POL"><catDesc>Political Science</catDesc></category><category id="PSY"><catDesc>Psychology</catDesc></category><category id="SOC"><catDesc>Sociology</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>student levels</catDesc><category id="G0"><catDesc>senior undergraduate</catDesc></category><category id="G1"><catDesc>first-year graduate</catDesc></category><category id="G2"><catDesc>second-year graduate</catDesc></category><category id="G3"><catDesc>third-year graduate and up</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>student-reported text types</catDesc><category id="CaseStudy"><catDesc>case study</catDesc></category><category id="Critique"><catDesc>critique</catDesc></category><category id="LiteratureReview"><catDesc>literature review</catDesc></category><category id="ResearchProposal"><catDesc>research proposal</catDesc></category><category id="ResponsePaper"><catDesc>response paper</catDesc></category><category id="TechnicalOrLabReport"><catDesc>technical report or lab report</catDesc></category><category id="TermPaper"><catDesc>term paper</catDesc></category><category id="OtherTextType"><catDesc>other</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>approximate preparation times</catDesc><category id="OneToThreeDays"><catDesc>1-3 days</catDesc></category><category id="FourToTenDays"><catDesc>4-10 days</catDesc></category><category id="TwoToThreeWeeks"><catDesc>2-3 weeks</catDesc></category><category id="ThreeToSixWeeks"><catDesc>3-6 weeks</catDesc></category><category id="OneFullSemester"><catDesc>one full semester</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>sources of feedback</catDesc><category id="NoFeedback"><catDesc>no feedback from others</catDesc></category><category id="PrimaryInstructor"><catDesc>primary course instructor</catDesc></category><category id="GSI"><catDesc>Graduate Student Instructor (teaching assistant)</catDesc></category><category id="WritingTutor"><catDesc>writing tutor</catDesc></category><category id="FriendOrClassmate"><catDesc>friend or classmate</catDesc></category><category id="OtherFeedback"><catDesc>other</catDesc></category></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><creation>Paper submitted to instructor in Nov 2004</creation><particDesc><person id="P43" sex="m" age="TwentyToTwentyThree"><affiliation>Zoological Anthropology, Biopsychology</affiliation><firstLang>English</firstLang><dominantLang>English</dominantLang><englishInPrimarySchool value="YES"/><englishInSecondarySchool value="YES"/><englishInUndergraduate value="YES"/></person></particDesc><textClass><catRef target="BIO G0 Report ResponsePaper OneToThreeDays NoFeedback"><classification><primary>Report</primary><secondary/></classification><classification><primary>Report</primary><secondary/></classification><features><feature type="Reference to sources"/></features></catRef></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change><date>2007-05-23</date><respStmt><name>Jesse Sielaff</name><resp>coder</resp></respStmt><item>manual adjustment of tags</item></change><change><date>2009-07-21</date><respStmt><name>Beilei Zhang</name><resp>coder</resp></respStmt><item>manual adjustment of tags</item></change><change><date>2007-05-22</date><respStmt><name>Gregory Garretson</name><resp>programmer</resp></respStmt><item>initial (automated) encoding in XML</item></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="opener"><head>PLANT POLLINATION SYSTEMS: EVOLUTIONARY TRENDS IN GENERALIZATION AND SPECIALIZATION</head><p/></div><div type="main"><p>      Perhaps one of the most intriguing varieties of mutualism is the relationship between angiosperms and their pollinators.  The evolutionary forces at work in these systems continue to both intrigue and perplex botanists and evolutionary biologists.  In a relatively recent paper, Johnson &amp; Steiner (2000) explore the common theories, misconceptions, and research methodologies that are used in the study of plant-pollinator relationships.  They challenge some long held ideas about the nature of specialization and generalization of floral complexes, and suggest that the cause of these trends may be more complex than current thinking predicates.  In addition, they explore the implications of ecosystem alterations and the threat of extinction on the more specialized mutualists.</p><p>      Theoretically, specialization and generalization of plants to pollinators offers some mutually exclusive advantages.  These advantages stem form the observation of Stebbin that specialization is best when the most effective pollinator's availability is reliable, whereas generalization should be favored when pollinator availability is irregular.  From this theoretical framework many hypotheses have been forwarded and tested concerning these systems.  In their review Johnson &amp; Steiner reconsider some of the theories.  For example, plants which cover a large range should favor specialization for particularly specific insects who are themselves specialized to the plants - because excess pollen for a variety of other plant species might <q type="soCalled">clog-up</q> their reproductive bits.  In addition to this observation, Johnson &amp; Steiner explore a host of other ideas about these systems, such as: the impact of plant life-histories, colonization practices, and breeding systems on the tendency to generalize or specialize.</p><p>     From this theoretical base the authors then explore and intriguing cause of convergence present in the plant world - which they refer to as pollination syndromes.  These syndromes, it is argued, are driven by similar needs for similar pollinator types.  For example, large pollinators - such as butterflies - may prefer larger flowers with specific colors, whereas smaller pollinators may favor smaller flowers with alternative colorings.  One well studied instance of this type of favoring has been documented in the <i type="term"> Mumulus </i>(monkeyflower).  It is thought that the preferential dispositions of these animals drives convergence in unrelated genera of plants.  Therefore, the penchant of evening or night pollination by moths, would drive plants to have syndromes that make pollination more easy for these pollinators.  The authors question, however, the simplistic causal relationship within theses systems.  They argue that some theoretical evidence denies, for example, some common notions about these systems: such as, the importance of flower coloring as a  mode of specialization.  This is important from an evolutionary biologists standpoint because often these syndromes are seen as an isolating mechanism in sympatry.  However, since the casual relationship is often unclear, the authors argue prudence when exploring speciation events based on these traits.  Furthermore, they argue that geographic trends might also play a large role in the specialization or generalization of plants.  Since ecosystems are notably different in northern and southern climates, they authors argue that other abiotic factors maybe driving the trends of specialization and generalization.   </p><p>     Finally, then, the authors explore the implications of the budding quantity of evidence on efforts for conservation.  They observe that the lifespan of plants versus pollinators, may give false impressions about the intrinsic link between pollinators and their plants; since some plants may survive long after their specific pollinator is gone, we may witness a delayed extinction in these species.  It seems that as the study of these amazing systems grows, so will are our understanding of evolutionary convergence and speciation, and our best means of species protection and management. </p></div><div type="closer"><div type="bibliography"><head>THIS TEXTS REFERS TO:</head><listBibl><bibl>Johnson, S.D. and K.E. Steiner (2000) "Generalization versus specialization in plant pollination systems" Trends in Ecology and Evolutionary Biology 15:140-143.</bibl></listBibl></div></div></body></text></TEI.2>