<TEI.2><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Unsteady Flow Across Pipe</title><author>anonymized</author></titleStmt><wordcount>1841</wordcount><editionStmt><edition>Version 1.0</edition></editionStmt><extent>insert_extent</extent><publicationStmt><idno>MEC.G0.08.5</idno><publisher>The University of Michigan</publisher><pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan, USA</pubPlace><date>2007</date><availability><p>The MICUSP project is owned by the Regents of the University of Michigan, who hold the copyright. The database has been developed by the English Language Institute. The original text submissions are stored electronically in the English Language Institute and may be consulted by bona fide researchers under special arrangements. The database is available by password on the World Wide Web for study, teaching and research purposes. Copies of the text files may be distributed, as long as either this statement of availability or the citation given below appears in the text. However, if any portion of this material is to be used for commercial purposes, such as for textbooks or tests, permission must be obtained in advance and a license fee may be required. For further information about copyright permissions, please inquire at micusp@umich.edu.</p><p>The recommended citation for MICASE is: Ädel, A., J. M. Swales, and J. Sielaff. (2007) The Michigan Corpus of Upper-level Student Papers. Ann Arbor, MI: The Regents of the University of Michigan.</p></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>The Michigan Corpus of Upper-level Student Papers (MICUSP)</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><p>This document derives from an unpublished, student-authored paper contributed in electronic format.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>For information on corpus compilation and encoding practices, see the MICUSP Handbook.</p></projectDesc><classDecl><taxonomy><category><catDesc>departments</catDesc><category id="BIO"><catDesc>Biology</catDesc></category><category id="CEE"><catDesc>Civil and Environmental Engineering</catDesc></category><category id="CLS"><catDesc>Classical Studies</catDesc></category><category id="ECO"><catDesc>Economics</catDesc></category><category id="EDU"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category id="ENG"><catDesc>English</catDesc></category><category id="IOE"><catDesc>Industrial and Operational Engineering</catDesc></category><category id="LIN"><catDesc>Linguistics</catDesc></category><category id="MEC"><catDesc>Mechanical Engineering</catDesc></category><category id="NRE"><catDesc>Natural Resources</catDesc></category><category id="NUR"><catDesc>Nursing</catDesc></category><category id="PHI"><catDesc>Philosophy</catDesc></category><category id="PHY"><catDesc>Physics</catDesc></category><category id="POL"><catDesc>Political Science</catDesc></category><category id="PSY"><catDesc>Psychology</catDesc></category><category id="SOC"><catDesc>Sociology</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>student levels</catDesc><category id="G0"><catDesc>senior undergraduate</catDesc></category><category id="G1"><catDesc>first-year graduate</catDesc></category><category id="G2"><catDesc>second-year graduate</catDesc></category><category id="G3"><catDesc>third-year graduate and up</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>student-reported text types</catDesc><category id="CaseStudy"><catDesc>case study</catDesc></category><category id="Critique"><catDesc>critique</catDesc></category><category id="LiteratureReview"><catDesc>literature review</catDesc></category><category id="ResearchProposal"><catDesc>research proposal</catDesc></category><category id="ResponsePaper"><catDesc>response paper</catDesc></category><category id="TechnicalOrLabReport"><catDesc>technical report or lab report</catDesc></category><category id="TermPaper"><catDesc>term paper</catDesc></category><category id="OtherTextType"><catDesc>other</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>approximate preparation times</catDesc><category id="OneToThreeDays"><catDesc>1-3 days</catDesc></category><category id="FourToTenDays"><catDesc>4-10 days</catDesc></category><category id="TwoToThreeWeeks"><catDesc>2-3 weeks</catDesc></category><category id="ThreeToSixWeeks"><catDesc>3-6 weeks</catDesc></category><category id="OneFullSemester"><catDesc>one full semester</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>sources of feedback</catDesc><category id="NoFeedback"><catDesc>no feedback from others</catDesc></category><category id="PrimaryInstructor"><catDesc>primary course instructor</catDesc></category><category id="GSI"><catDesc>Graduate Student Instructor (teaching assistant)</catDesc></category><category id="WritingTutor"><catDesc>writing tutor</catDesc></category><category id="FriendOrClassmate"><catDesc>friend or classmate</catDesc></category><category id="OtherFeedback"><catDesc>other</catDesc></category></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><creation>Paper submitted to instructor in Mar 2008</creation><particDesc><person id="P509" sex="m" age="TwentyToTwentyThree"><affiliation>Mechanical Engineering</affiliation><firstLang>English</firstLang><dominantLang>English</dominantLang><englishInPrimarySchool value="YES"/><englishInSecondarySchool value="NO"/><englishInUndergraduate value="YES"/></person></particDesc><textClass><catRef target="MEC G0 ResearchPaper TechnicalOrLabReport TwoToThreeWeeks PrimaryInstructor"><classification><primary>Research Paper</primary><secondary/></classification><classification><primary>Research Paper</primary><secondary>Report</secondary></classification><features><feature type="Tables, graphs or figures"/><feature type="Discussion of results section"/></features></catRef></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change><date>2009-05-13</date><respStmt><name>Geoffrey Ho</name><resp>coder</resp></respStmt><item>manual adjustment of tags</item></change><change><date>2007-05-22</date><respStmt><name>Gregory Garretson</name><resp>programmer</resp></respStmt><item>initial (automated) encoding in XML</item></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="opener"><head>Project 2</head><p/></div><div type="main"><div type="head_1"><head>Introduction</head><p>Our team recreated the experimental setup shown in the project 2 description and shown in figure 1 in Braza et al. We created two different meshes, shown in figures 2 and 3 below, to check for grid independence.  The team used a uniform quad mesh. The meshes were then imported into Fluent where the calculations began. We doubled the resolution, until our results were very close to each other which indicated that the solution we obtained was grid independent. </p><p>Our first task was to show the vector plots of the velocity field in the wake region at each Reynolds number (Re) and this can be seen in figure 6 on page 5. Next, we had to show contour plots of pressure and streamlines in the wake region at each Re number. Our fourth task was to show a plot of the re-attachment length versus time for Re=40 and compare it to figure 4 in Braza et al; this is shown in figure 9 on page 8. </p><p>Next, we show a plot of the pressure distribution on the cylinder wall as a function of θ at Re=40 and compare that to figure 5 in Braza et al; this is shown in figure 10 on page 9. Our sixth task was to plot drag coefficients and separation angles as a function of Re and compare it to figures 6 and 9 in Braza et al; this is shown in figures 11 and 12 on pages 9 and 10. Next, we plotted the time history of pressure at a selected point in the near wake and used this to calculate the Strouhal number; this is shown in figure 13 on page 10. Our last and final task was to plot the Strouhal number as a function of Re and compare it to figure 9 in Braza et al; this is shown in figure 14 on page 12.</p></div><div type="head_1"><head>Fluent</head><p>In Fluent, we used air at 273K with a kinematic viscosity (νk) of 1.32E-5 m2/s and an inlet velocity determined by equation 1. The same mesh was used for all Reynolds numbers (Re). The density of the fluid (air) used was 1.292 kg/m3 and the dynamic viscosity (νd) used was 1.71e-05 kg/m*s. We first scaled our mesh in Fluent to convert from cm to m. We solved with an unsteady time and 2nd order implicit unsteady formulation. The momentum was changed to second order upwind and the absolute criteria of the residuals were changed to 1E-5 to increase the accuracy of our results. The boundary conditions of the velocity inlets were set to have an x-velocity shown in the table below and the model was initialized with zero initial conditions. From figure 9a in Braza et al, we were able to find an approximate Strouhal number and estimate the period for each Reynolds number using equation 2 below. We divided the period by 20 to find an appropriate time step size while iterating. The max iterations per a time step was set to 100 to make sure that the solution would reach the residuals and converge each cycle. For Re values of 100, 200, and 400, the model first needed to be manually triggered to achieve a periodic steady-state solution represented by vortex shedding from alternate sides of the back of the cylinder. This was done by setting the bottom velocity inlet to twice the U velocity. The trigger was allowed to run until the iteration plot showed a fine steady line under the set residual. We used a time step size 100 times less than the predicted time step size while triggering. The pressure was plotted at a point in the wake region 0.03 m above and 0.15 m to the right of the cylinder while the model was iterated. From here we could see when the solution produced a steady frequency of at least five cycles at which point we took our data measurements over five different times. </p><p><gap desc="formula"/> 	(Eqn. 1)</p><p><gap desc="formula"/>		(Eqn. 2)</p><gap desc="table"/><p><b>Table 1:</b> Summary of Data</p></div><div type="head_1"><head>Gambit</head><p>Using Gambit, we created a mesh based on the experimental setup shown in figure 1 and tried to recreate the mesh shown in the project description. Using Gambit, many different meshes were created and tested and the best single mesh is shown in figure 2. The type of mesh used was a uniform quad mesh.</p></div><div type="head_1"><head>Mesh Independence</head><p>In order to verify that we had mesh independence, we compared the values of reattachment length, drag coefficient, Strouhal Number, and separation angles for the two meshes. After creating the single mesh, we doubled it and calculated the four variables we were looking for. After realizing they were not as close as we would have like them to be, we went ahead and halved the single mesh we had and calculated the four variables again. We believe the results obtained, shown in table 2 for the three different meshes, are sufficient enough for us to use the single mesh.  We showed our mesh independence for Re=400 based on 2nd-order steady flow. </p><gap desc="table"/><p><b>Table 2:</b> Mesh independence results for half, single, and double mesh for Re=400</p><gap desc="figure"/><p><b>Figure 1:</b> Dimensions of experimental setup</p><gap desc="figure"/><gap desc="figure"/><p><b>Figures 2 and 3:</b> Single and double meshes used to check for grid independence</p><p>The boundary layers can be seen in figure 4 on page 5. We created two velocity inlets. The first one was the 2nd quadrant of the large circle attached to the top horizontal line of the rectangular box and the other was the 3rd quadrant of the large circle attached to the bottom horizontal line of the rectangular box. This was done because Fluent cannot naturally predict periodic unsteady flow. Also, an outflow was created at the end of the rectangle and both the top and bottom halves of the smaller circle were set as walls to model the cylinder.</p><gap desc="figure"/><p><b>Figure 4:</b> Boundary layer conditions</p></div><div type="head_1"><head>Vector Plots of Velocity Fields in the Wake Region at each Re</head><p>As the Re becomes greater than 40, asymmetrical eddy patterns occur seen in c. and d. below. This is shown as the alternating separation of the vortices which have been diffused from the cylinder; these are known as the Karman vortex paths. </p><gap desc="figure"/><p><b>Figure 6:</b> a, b, c, and d show the velocity field for Re=40, 100, 200, and 400 respectively in the near wake region</p></div><div type="head_1"><head>Contour Plots of Pressure and Streamlines in the Wake Region at each Re</head><gap desc="figure"/><p><b>Figure 7:</b> a, b, c, and d show the contour plots of pressure for Re=40, 100, 200, and 400 respectively in the near wake region</p><gap desc="figure"/><p><b>Figure 8:</b> a, b, c, and d show the contour plots of streamlines for Re=40, 100, 200, and 400 respectively in the near wake region</p></div><div type="head_1"><head>Plot of Re-attachment Length versus Time for Re=40 (Compare to figure 4 in Braza et al)</head><p>Using our single mesh, we obtained a plot of the reattachment length vs. time for a Re=40 as shown in figure 9 below.  Our data analysis is shown in table 3. For Re=40, figure 6a on page 5, one can see that there are two attached vortices behind the cylinder. The flow reaches steady state at approximately 16 when looking at our experimental compared to 15 when looking at figure 4 in Braza et al. Our figure for reattachment length closely matches figure 4 in Braza et al. Equation 3 was used to make time (t) dimensionless. We obtained a dimensionless reattachment length by dividing it by the radius.</p><gap desc="table"/><p><b>Table 3:</b> Summary of data for reattachment length</p><gap desc="formula"/><p>		(Eqn. 3)</p><gap desc="figure"/><gap desc="figure"/><p><b>Figure 9:</b> Time evolution of the reattachment length a) our data b) figure 4a Braza et al</p></div><div type="head_1"><head>Plot of Pressure Distribution on the Cylinder Wall as a Function of θ at Re=40 (Compare to figure 5 in Braza et al)</head><p>We were able to calculate Cp by using equation 4 below where P represents the total pressure and Po represents the initial pressure. Our values showed a similar curve to that of Braza et al, but were slightly lower than Braza’s Re=40 values and more closely match Braza’s Re=20. This can be seen in figure 10 below.  </p><p>Cp=(P-P0+.5*ρ*U2)/( .5*ρ*U2)	(Eq. 4)</p><gap desc="figure"/><gap desc="figure"/><p><b>Figure 10:</b> Plot of the Pressure coefficient versus theta for Re=40 a) our data b) figure 5a Braza et al</p></div><div type="head_1"><head>Plots of Drag Coefficient and Separation Angle as a function of Re (Compare to figures 6 and 9 in Braza et al)</head><p>To solve for the Drag Coefficient (Cd), equation 5 was used. In Fluent, we ran 5 trials for each Re and found the Drag Force. Then using density (), velocity, and the frontal area (A), we are able to produce figure 11 that shows Cd versus Re. This graph compares nicely to the one shown in figure 6 in Braza et al with our values being just slightly higher which shows that our data agrees. The area consisted of the height (diameter) of the cylinder and the width was assumed to be of unit length meter. </p><gap desc="formula"/><p>		(Eqn. 5)</p><gap desc="figure"/><gap desc="figure"/><p><b>Figure 11:</b> Plot of Cd versus Re a) our data and b) figure 9b in Braza et al</p><p>To calculate the separation angle (Ѳd), we ran 5 trials for each Re and took the average Ѳd. The results are shown in table 4 and in figure 12 below. One can see that our figure compares very nicely to figure 6 in Braza et al.</p><gap desc="table"/><p><b>Table 4:</b> Averaged values of Ѳd and Cd for each Re</p><gap desc="figure"/><gap desc="figure"/><p><b>Figure 12:</b> Separation angle plotted against Re a) our data and b) figure 6b in Braza et al</p></div><div type="head_1"><head>Plots of the Time History of Pressure at a Selected Point in the Near Wake</head><gap desc="figure"/><p><b>Figure 13:</b> Plots of Pressure versus time for Re 100, 200, and 400</p></div><div type="head_1"><head>Plot of Strouhal Number as a Function of Re (Compare to figure 9 in Braza et al)</head><p>For each Re not including 40, we ran five trials and found the period. Then we calculated the Strouhal Number (SH) using equation 2 below. D is for diameter and u, the uniform-flow velocity, was calculated from each Re.  Figure 14 a) below shows the Strouhal number for each Re which compares nicely to the reference b).</p><p><gap desc="formula"/>	(Eqn. 2)</p><gap desc="table"/><p><b>Table 5:</b> Data used to calculate the Strouhal Number for each Re</p><gap desc="figure"/><gap desc="figure"/><p><b>Figure 13:</b> Strouhal Number plotted Re a) our data and b) figure 9a in Braza et al</p></div><div type="head_1"><head>Conclusions</head><p>After running many simulations in Fluent, we noticed that at low Re values around 40, the flow was steady state with two separation bubbles as shown in figure 6a. As the Re values became higher there was vortex shedding behind the cylinder. In conclusion, we found that our calculations very closely match that in the reference Braza et al. The values for separation angle, reattachment length, Strouhal number, and drag coefficient are all within 7% for the single and double mesh. The coefficient of drag and wall pressure were the most different compared to the Braza et al., with our values leveling out around 1.5-1.6 and Braza’s near 1.2 for the coefficient of drag and our Cp closer to Braza’s Re=20 instead of 40.</p></div></div><div type="closer"><p/></div></body></text></TEI.2>