<TEI.2><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Language Lesson Plan</title><author>anonymized</author></titleStmt><wordcount>1273</wordcount><editionStmt><edition>Version 1.0</edition></editionStmt><extent>insert_extent</extent><publicationStmt><idno>LIN.G0.01.2</idno><publisher>The University of Michigan</publisher><pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan, USA</pubPlace><date>2007</date><availability><p>The MICUSP project is owned by the Regents of the University of Michigan, who hold the copyright. The database has been developed by the English Language Institute. The original text submissions are stored electronically in the English Language Institute and may be consulted by bona fide researchers under special arrangements. The database is available by password on the World Wide Web for study, teaching and research purposes. Copies of the text files may be distributed, as long as either this statement of availability or the citation given below appears in the text. However, if any portion of this material is to be used for commercial purposes, such as for textbooks or tests, permission must be obtained in advance and a license fee may be required. For further information about copyright permissions, please inquire at micusp@umich.edu.</p><p>The recommended citation for MICASE is: Ädel, A., J. M. Swales, and J. Sielaff. (2007) The Michigan Corpus of Upper-level Student Papers. Ann Arbor, MI: The Regents of the University of Michigan.</p></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>The Michigan Corpus of Upper-level Student Papers (MICUSP)</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><p>This document derives from an unpublished, student-authored paper contributed in electronic format.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>For information on corpus compilation and encoding practices, see the MICUSP Handbook.</p></projectDesc><classDecl><taxonomy><category><catDesc>departments</catDesc><category id="BIO"><catDesc>Biology</catDesc></category><category id="CEE"><catDesc>Civil and Environmental Engineering</catDesc></category><category id="CLS"><catDesc>Classical Studies</catDesc></category><category id="ECO"><catDesc>Economics</catDesc></category><category id="EDU"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category id="ENG"><catDesc>English</catDesc></category><category id="IOE"><catDesc>Industrial and Operational Engineering</catDesc></category><category id="LIN"><catDesc>Linguistics</catDesc></category><category id="MEC"><catDesc>Mechanical Engineering</catDesc></category><category id="NRE"><catDesc>Natural Resources</catDesc></category><category id="NUR"><catDesc>Nursing</catDesc></category><category id="PHI"><catDesc>Philosophy</catDesc></category><category id="PHY"><catDesc>Physics</catDesc></category><category id="POL"><catDesc>Political Science</catDesc></category><category id="PSY"><catDesc>Psychology</catDesc></category><category id="SOC"><catDesc>Sociology</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>student levels</catDesc><category id="G0"><catDesc>senior undergraduate</catDesc></category><category id="G1"><catDesc>first-year graduate</catDesc></category><category id="G2"><catDesc>second-year graduate</catDesc></category><category id="G3"><catDesc>third-year graduate and up</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>student-reported text types</catDesc><category id="CaseStudy"><catDesc>case study</catDesc></category><category id="Critique"><catDesc>critique</catDesc></category><category id="LiteratureReview"><catDesc>literature review</catDesc></category><category id="ResearchProposal"><catDesc>research proposal</catDesc></category><category id="ResponsePaper"><catDesc>response paper</catDesc></category><category id="TechnicalOrLabReport"><catDesc>technical report or lab report</catDesc></category><category id="TermPaper"><catDesc>term paper</catDesc></category><category id="OtherTextType"><catDesc>other</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>approximate preparation times</catDesc><category id="OneToThreeDays"><catDesc>1-3 days</catDesc></category><category id="FourToTenDays"><catDesc>4-10 days</catDesc></category><category id="TwoToThreeWeeks"><catDesc>2-3 weeks</catDesc></category><category id="ThreeToSixWeeks"><catDesc>3-6 weeks</catDesc></category><category id="OneFullSemester"><catDesc>one full semester</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>sources of feedback</catDesc><category id="NoFeedback"><catDesc>no feedback from others</catDesc></category><category id="PrimaryInstructor"><catDesc>primary course instructor</catDesc></category><category id="GSI"><catDesc>Graduate Student Instructor (teaching assistant)</catDesc></category><category id="WritingTutor"><catDesc>writing tutor</catDesc></category><category id="FriendOrClassmate"><catDesc>friend or classmate</catDesc></category><category id="OtherFeedback"><catDesc>other</catDesc></category></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><creation>Paper submitted to instructor in Dec 2004</creation><particDesc><person id="P13" sex="f" age="TwentyToTwentyThree"><affiliation>German, Linguistics</affiliation><firstLang>English</firstLang><dominantLang>English</dominantLang><englishInPrimarySchool value="YES"/><englishInSecondarySchool value="YES"/><englishInUndergraduate value="YES"/></person></particDesc><textClass><catRef target="LIN G0 Proposal ResponsePaper FourToTenDays NoFeedback"><classification><primary>Proposal</primary><secondary/></classification><classification><primary>Proposal</primary><secondary>Report</secondary></classification><features><feature type="Tables, graphs or figures"/></features></catRef></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change><date>2007-06-05</date><respStmt><name>Yung-Hui Chien</name><resp>coder</resp></respStmt><item>manual adjustment of tags</item></change><change><date>2007-05-22</date><respStmt><name>Gregory Garretson</name><resp>programmer</resp></respStmt><item>initial (automated) encoding in XML</item></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="opener"><head>Language Lesson Plan</head><p/></div><div type="main"><div type="head_1"><head>1. Goals</head><p>	Originally, I had intended to do a lesson plan in German for students of English, but on further reflection, I decided that for this project it would be better for understanding if I tried a slightly adapted version of the lesson for students of English as a second language in America.  My target age group would be high school-aged students at a beginner English-learning level, primarily because I will be teaching using the content-based method, and that is an age at which my chosen school subject, geography, is still taught and can therefore be more useful.</p><p>	The goal then of this lesson is to impart some knowledge of the subject of geography to students of ESL.  Students should learn and be able to use basic vocabulary involving directions and should be familiarized with the location of the different states in the US.  I am planning for a class with around twenty to thirty students with several different first languages and varying degrees of beginner English skills.  </p></div><div type="head_1"><head>2. Objectives</head><p>	The terminal objective of this lesson will be for the students to become familiar with what each of the states looks like and be able to identify them on a map.  They should also be able to make statements about the location of a state alone or in relation to another state.  This type of lesson is common in most American grade school systems today and will allow the students to learn more about the country in which they are now living.</p><p>	Enabling objectives for the lesson will include learning directions (north, south, eastern from, western from, etc.) and practicing using exercises designed to aid in memorization of terms and locations.  Students will also be expected to review the lesson as homework.</p></div><div type="head_1"><head>3. Materials and Equipment</head><p>	The materials involved will be handouts, power point, a blackboard, and a blank map to be filled out as homework (Appendix D).  The handouts will include maps of the United States (Appendix A), a list of the different directions and their attributes (Appendix B), and an exercise involving the directions (Appendix C), while the power point will be used to supplement the handouts.  I would write important phrases on the blackboard to aid the students in understanding the lesson.  The blank map will be given out at the end of class, at which time the students will be told that the test in this course will include some of the aspects of the map and that they should practice by filling it out (with the help of another map if necessary).</p></div><div type="head_1"><head>4. Procedures/Activities</head><p>	If this is the first class, I might introduce myself and have the students each say their names in the traditional <q type="example">my name is ____</q> format.  Then I would give the first handout (Appendix A) out and go over the state names, instructing the students in the pronunciation of the harder ones.  My power point would always simply be a larger replica of what I had given the students, so I would be able to demonstrate as well as answer questions using that tool.  </p><p>After pointing to state names and having the students practice saying them aloud for a while, I would give out the second handout (Appendix B) and introduce the concept of directions.  Once we had clearly defined each term and reviewed its uses and answered any questions, I would move on to some simple sentences involving the locations of the states.  Some sample sentences might be as follows:</p><p>Utah is in the West.</p><p>California is found in the West.</p><p>Florida is southeast of Montana.</p><p>	The students would again answer as a group, filling in the pauses when I spoke.  This would be followed by a little question formation using the same verbs, such as given below:</p><p>Where is Utah?  Is Utah in the East?</p><p>Is this California?</p><p>Is Michigan here?</p><p>Where can we find Arkansas?</p><p>Is Maine south of California?</p><p>	The students would answer, then be given the chance to practice together in pairs or triplets.  They would take turns asking each other questions and answering them using their new vocabulary and with the aid of the handouts.  I would go around listening to the groups and helping the students when needed.  </p><p>After a few minutes, I would combine the pairs and triplets into groups of four or five and give them the next handout (Appendix C).  The students would be given about five minutes to go complete the handout before we would go over it as a class and again review the material.  If there were enough time at the end of the class period, the students would divide into groups again for a game.  I would write the following phrases on the board for reference:</p><p>	Our state is _____.</p><p>Is your state _____?</p><p>	No, our state is not _____.</p><p>	Yes, our state is _____.</p><p>Each group of students would then take turns choosing a state and giving a clue, such as, <q type="example">Our state is north of Texas.</q>  Each of the other groups would get a chance to guess using the formula provided.  The group that had chosen the state (let's call them Group 1) would then answer with the yes or no statement given, depending on the accuracy of the guess.  If none of the other groups guessed the state on the first try, the Group 1 would give another clue.  This would go on until one of the groups guessed correctly.  Group 2 would then choose a new state, and the game would go on as long as time permitted.</p><p>At the end of class, the blank map (Appendix D) would be given out as homework.  The students would be told to fill out the map and that aspects from it would be on the test.  They would also be told to review the map because the next class period would deal more extensively with the states' names and locations.</p></div><div type="head_1"><head>5. Evaluation</head><p>	All in all, I would say that this lesson should be very effective in teaching the students directions, and also moderately effective in imparting its secondary goal of giving them a feel for the location of the states.  I know that more review of the state names and locations would be necessary to fulfill this goal, but I didn't feel that this issue could be addressed in only one class period.</p><p>	I think that the lesson did cover a good range of different activities.  There were whole-class work, small group and pair work, teacher talk, and student talk.  The students had practice listening and producing, as well as using directions for a practical purpose and as a school subject.  In conclusion, I believe that this lesson has accomplished the goals laid out for it according to the content-based method.</p></div></div><div type="closer"><div type="appendix"><head>Appendix A</head><gap desc="figure"/><p/></div><div type="appendix"><head>Appendix B</head><head>Directions: Define each term.</head><p>the North</p><p>the South</p><p>the East</p><p>the West</p><p>north of</p><p>south of</p><p>east of </p><p>west of</p><p>north </p><p>south </p><p>east </p><p>west</p></div><div type="appendix"><head>Appendix C</head><head>Directions: Insert the correct answer in the blank using the words given below.</head><p>Northeast, northeast of, northwest of, north of, South, southeast of, southwest of, south of, south of, East, east, east of, West, west of, west of</p><list><item>1. Utah is __________ Arizona.</item><item>2. Maine is in the __________.</item><item>3. Montana is __________ Washington.</item><item>4. West Virginia is __________Virginia.</item><item>5. Colorado is ____________ Arizona.</item><item>6. Missouri is __________ Iowa.	</item><item>7. South Carolina is __________ North Dakota.</item><item>8. Oregon is__________ Washington.</item><item>9. Colorado is __________ Utah.</item><item>10. Texas is in the __________.</item><item>11. Texas is __________ Louisiana.</item><item>12. Pennsylvania is __________ New York.</item><item>13. California is in the __________.</item><item>14. Maryland is in the __________.</item><item>15. If I travel from Illinois to Indiana, I must go __________.</item></list></div><div type="appendix"><head>Appendix D</head><gap desc="figure"/><p/></div></div></body></text></TEI.2>