<TEI.2><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Executive Order on Off-Road Vehicle Use</title><author>anonymized</author></titleStmt><wordcount>840</wordcount><editionStmt><edition>Version 1.0</edition></editionStmt><extent>insert_extent</extent><publicationStmt><idno>NRE.G1.14.2</idno><publisher>The University of Michigan</publisher><pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan, USA</pubPlace><date>2007</date><availability><p>The MICUSP project is owned by the Regents of the University of Michigan, who hold the copyright. The database has been developed by the English Language Institute. The original text submissions are stored electronically in the English Language Institute and may be consulted by bona fide researchers under special arrangements. The database is available by password on the World Wide Web for study, teaching and research purposes. Copies of the text files may be distributed, as long as either this statement of availability or the citation given below appears in the text. However, if any portion of this material is to be used for commercial purposes, such as for textbooks or tests, permission must be obtained in advance and a license fee may be required. For further information about copyright permissions, please inquire at micusp@umich.edu.</p><p>The recommended citation for MICASE is: Ädel, A., J. M. Swales, and J. Sielaff. (2007) The Michigan Corpus of Upper-level Student Papers. Ann Arbor, MI: The Regents of the University of Michigan.</p></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>The Michigan Corpus of Upper-level Student Papers (MICUSP)</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><p>This document derives from an unpublished, student-authored paper contributed in electronic format.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>For information on corpus compilation and encoding practices, see the MICUSP Handbook.</p></projectDesc><classDecl><taxonomy><category><catDesc>departments</catDesc><category id="BIO"><catDesc>Biology</catDesc></category><category id="CEE"><catDesc>Civil and Environmental Engineering</catDesc></category><category id="CLS"><catDesc>Classical Studies</catDesc></category><category id="ECO"><catDesc>Economics</catDesc></category><category id="EDU"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category id="ENG"><catDesc>English</catDesc></category><category id="IOE"><catDesc>Industrial and Operational Engineering</catDesc></category><category id="LIN"><catDesc>Linguistics</catDesc></category><category id="MEC"><catDesc>Mechanical Engineering</catDesc></category><category id="NRE"><catDesc>Natural Resources</catDesc></category><category id="NUR"><catDesc>Nursing</catDesc></category><category id="PHI"><catDesc>Philosophy</catDesc></category><category id="PHY"><catDesc>Physics</catDesc></category><category id="POL"><catDesc>Political Science</catDesc></category><category id="PSY"><catDesc>Psychology</catDesc></category><category id="SOC"><catDesc>Sociology</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>student levels</catDesc><category id="G0"><catDesc>senior undergraduate</catDesc></category><category id="G1"><catDesc>first-year graduate</catDesc></category><category id="G2"><catDesc>second-year graduate</catDesc></category><category id="G3"><catDesc>third-year graduate and up</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>student-reported text types</catDesc><category id="CaseStudy"><catDesc>case study</catDesc></category><category id="Critique"><catDesc>critique</catDesc></category><category id="LiteratureReview"><catDesc>literature review</catDesc></category><category id="ResearchProposal"><catDesc>research proposal</catDesc></category><category id="ResponsePaper"><catDesc>response paper</catDesc></category><category id="TechnicalOrLabReport"><catDesc>technical report or lab report</catDesc></category><category id="TermPaper"><catDesc>term paper</catDesc></category><category id="OtherTextType"><catDesc>other</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>approximate preparation times</catDesc><category id="OneToThreeDays"><catDesc>1-3 days</catDesc></category><category id="FourToTenDays"><catDesc>4-10 days</catDesc></category><category id="TwoToThreeWeeks"><catDesc>2-3 weeks</catDesc></category><category id="ThreeToSixWeeks"><catDesc>3-6 weeks</catDesc></category><category id="OneFullSemester"><catDesc>one full semester</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>sources of feedback</catDesc><category id="NoFeedback"><catDesc>no feedback from others</catDesc></category><category id="PrimaryInstructor"><catDesc>primary course instructor</catDesc></category><category id="GSI"><catDesc>Graduate Student Instructor (teaching assistant)</catDesc></category><category id="WritingTutor"><catDesc>writing tutor</catDesc></category><category id="FriendOrClassmate"><catDesc>friend or classmate</catDesc></category><category id="OtherFeedback"><catDesc>other</catDesc></category></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><creation>Paper submitted to instructor in Nov 2007</creation><particDesc><person id="P549" sex="f" age="TwentyFourToThirty"><affiliation>School of Natural Resources</affiliation><firstLang>English</firstLang><dominantLang>English</dominantLang><englishInPrimarySchool value="YES"/><englishInSecondarySchool value="YES"/><englishInUndergraduate value="YES"/></person></particDesc><textClass><catRef target="NRE G1 Critique ResponsePaper OneToThreeDays FriendOrClassmate"><classification><primary>Critique/Evaluation</primary><secondary/></classification><classification><primary>Critique/Evaluation</primary><secondary>Response Paper</secondary></classification><features> </features></catRef></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change><date>2008-12-12</date><respStmt><name>Emily Lin</name><resp>coder</resp></respStmt><item>manual adjustment of tags</item></change><change><date>2007-05-22</date><respStmt><name>Gregory Garretson</name><resp>programmer</resp></respStmt><item>initial (automated) encoding in XML</item></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="opener"><head>Implementation of Proposed Executive Order on Off-Road Vehicle Use on Federal Lands</head><p/></div><div type="main"><p>In response to your request, I have analyzed the President's proposed Executive Order on Off-Road Vehicle Use. Described below are the potential implementation problems, in order of significance. Deemed most detrimental to the program's success are problems resulting from the shared authority given to federal, state, and local agencies. Operational demands within agencies, lack of resources, and ambiguity within the executive order also create foreseeable problems.</p><div type="head_1"><head>Consequences of Sharing Program Authority</head><p>I foresee significant problems associated with giving shared authority to the Secretary of Interior, the Secretary of Agriculture, the Secretary of Defense, and the TVA Board of Directors. Each agency head must implement an ORV policy on the land they control, but due to the agencies' disparate cultures, interests, and areas of expertise, the resultant policies will not be unified. The agencies will have different zoning rationales, rules, and penalties, and this fragmentation will make enforcement less efficient and unnecessarily complicated. ORV users will both take advantage of this fragmentation (by overusing areas with fewer restrictions) and unknowingly break regulations when crossing from one jurisdiction to the next.</p><p>Relying on state and local agencies to disperse public information and enforce regulations is also problematic. Without additional funding, these agencies will have no incentive to help, especially if they value the economic gains—the business and tourism—generated by ORV use.</p></div><div type="head_1"><head>Operational Demands</head><p>The proposed ORV policy requires agencies to develop new organizational routines to complete the necessary tasks and cohesively coordinate them. Additionally, measures to protect the environment and public health will conflict with current SOPs of the agencies who normally promote multi-use. Agency culture and inertia will leave them more susceptible to pressure from ORV recreationists and local multi-use organizations than the executive order intends.</p><p>Agencies will face obstacles in carrying out required tasks due to the nature of the ORV conflict. ORVs inevitably damage environmental quality, and agencies will have trouble establishing ORV-appropriate areas not in proximity to threatened or endangered species, watersheds, or other recreational activities. Public involvement may prevent timely establishment of zoning and regulations; hearings will involve debates between scientists, environmentalists, bicyclists, and ORV recreationists, and finding a suitable compromise will be difficult. The agencies will most likely face litigation from groups suing on the basis of NEPA and ESA.</p><p>Agencies will also face problems in maintaining the efficacy of the program. Past efforts to designate ORV trails show that once they are established, more riders are drawn to the areas, leading to increased environmental damage and creation of side trails. Enforcement will be especially difficult, given that ORV users can travel vast distances and often prefer riding off trails. Agencies must establish new SOPs for patrolling and finding offenders across large areas, on both ORV lands (to enforce operating conditions) and non-ORV lands (to enforce zoning).</p></div><div type="head_1"><head>Resource Availability</head><p>The affected agencies do not currently have the resources necessary to implement the ORV policy. To establish appropriate ORV zoning, agencies will need money and scientific expertise to conduct studies that determine potential impacts on natural resources, wildlife, and public health. Agencies will need additional resources to conduct hearings, hire facilitators with expertise in handling contentious issues, undertake effective public outreach, and design informational materials. To monitor lands and enforce regulations, agencies will need to hire skilled staff and increase the size of their own ORV fleet. New and current staff will need training in catching offenders, given the different nature of ORV use. Without adequate resources, agencies will not meet goals of eliminating 90% of violations. Alternatively, they may see incentives for issuing fewer violations in order to meet this goal.</p><p>Section 7 guidelines require an ongoing investment of money and expertise to monitor efficacy and implement improvements. Ongoing resources will also be necessary to maintain the designated ORV trails and areas. Even if deemed <q type="soCalled">ORV-appropriate,</q> the land will need restoration to maintain ecological integrity and prevent ORV users from turning to more pristine areas, which is likely if they are dissatisfied with the designated areas.</p></div><div type="head_1"><head>Communication of Program Objectives</head><p>	I foresee several implementation problems arising from how the program's objectives are communicated. The program's objective—to establish a unified Federal policy—is inconsistent with delegating authority to respective agency heads. Furthermore, the executive order does not explain to what extent agency heads should coordinate (if at all) with each other to establish complementary ORV regulations. Additionally, the executive order does not prioritize the ORV program relative to other agency programs.</p><p>The executive order is ambiguous about the level of protection the agencies should put in place. Agencies will interpret the phrases <i>minimize damage</i>, <i>minimize harassment</i>, and <i>minimize conflicts</i> flexibly, based on their own capacity and external influences. The operating conditions in Section 4 are also vague and do not prioritize the objectives of protecting resource values, public welfare, and land-use conflicts. This vagueness allows agency heads to develop lax operating conditions and not instigate firmer measures, such as a permit system, that may be necessary to limit ORVs and protect natural resources and public health.</p></div></div><div type="closer"><p/></div></body></text></TEI.2>