<TEI.2><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Acid Mine Drainage</title><author>anonymized</author></titleStmt><wordcount>1436</wordcount><editionStmt><edition>Version 1.0</edition></editionStmt><extent>insert_extent</extent><publicationStmt><idno>NRE.G0.10.1</idno><publisher>The University of Michigan</publisher><pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan, USA</pubPlace><date>2007</date><availability><p>The MICUSP project is owned by the Regents of the University of Michigan, who hold the copyright. The database has been developed by the English Language Institute. The original text submissions are stored electronically in the English Language Institute and may be consulted by bona fide researchers under special arrangements. The database is available by password on the World Wide Web for study, teaching and research purposes. Copies of the text files may be distributed, as long as either this statement of availability or the citation given below appears in the text. However, if any portion of this material is to be used for commercial purposes, such as for textbooks or tests, permission must be obtained in advance and a license fee may be required. For further information about copyright permissions, please inquire at micusp@umich.edu.</p><p>The recommended citation for MICASE is: Ädel, A., J. M. Swales, and J. Sielaff. (2007) The Michigan Corpus of Upper-level Student Papers. Ann Arbor, MI: The Regents of the University of Michigan.</p></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>The Michigan Corpus of Upper-level Student Papers (MICUSP)</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><p>This document derives from an unpublished, student-authored paper contributed in electronic format.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>For information on corpus compilation and encoding practices, see the MICUSP Handbook.</p></projectDesc><classDecl><taxonomy><category><catDesc>departments</catDesc><category id="BIO"><catDesc>Biology</catDesc></category><category id="CEE"><catDesc>Civil and Environmental Engineering</catDesc></category><category id="CLS"><catDesc>Classical Studies</catDesc></category><category id="ECO"><catDesc>Economics</catDesc></category><category id="EDU"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category id="ENG"><catDesc>English</catDesc></category><category id="IOE"><catDesc>Industrial and Operational Engineering</catDesc></category><category id="LIN"><catDesc>Linguistics</catDesc></category><category id="MEC"><catDesc>Mechanical Engineering</catDesc></category><category id="NRE"><catDesc>Natural Resources</catDesc></category><category id="NUR"><catDesc>Nursing</catDesc></category><category id="PHI"><catDesc>Philosophy</catDesc></category><category id="PHY"><catDesc>Physics</catDesc></category><category id="POL"><catDesc>Political Science</catDesc></category><category id="PSY"><catDesc>Psychology</catDesc></category><category id="SOC"><catDesc>Sociology</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>student levels</catDesc><category id="G0"><catDesc>senior undergraduate</catDesc></category><category id="G1"><catDesc>first-year graduate</catDesc></category><category id="G2"><catDesc>second-year graduate</catDesc></category><category id="G3"><catDesc>third-year graduate and up</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>student-reported text types</catDesc><category id="CaseStudy"><catDesc>case study</catDesc></category><category id="Critique"><catDesc>critique</catDesc></category><category id="LiteratureReview"><catDesc>literature review</catDesc></category><category id="ResearchProposal"><catDesc>research proposal</catDesc></category><category id="ResponsePaper"><catDesc>response paper</catDesc></category><category id="TechnicalOrLabReport"><catDesc>technical report or lab report</catDesc></category><category id="TermPaper"><catDesc>term paper</catDesc></category><category id="OtherTextType"><catDesc>other</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>approximate preparation times</catDesc><category id="OneToThreeDays"><catDesc>1-3 days</catDesc></category><category id="FourToTenDays"><catDesc>4-10 days</catDesc></category><category id="TwoToThreeWeeks"><catDesc>2-3 weeks</catDesc></category><category id="ThreeToSixWeeks"><catDesc>3-6 weeks</catDesc></category><category id="OneFullSemester"><catDesc>one full semester</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>sources of feedback</catDesc><category id="NoFeedback"><catDesc>no feedback from others</catDesc></category><category id="PrimaryInstructor"><catDesc>primary course instructor</catDesc></category><category id="GSI"><catDesc>Graduate Student Instructor (teaching assistant)</catDesc></category><category id="WritingTutor"><catDesc>writing tutor</catDesc></category><category id="FriendOrClassmate"><catDesc>friend or classmate</catDesc></category><category id="OtherFeedback"><catDesc>other</catDesc></category></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><creation>Paper submitted to instructor in Oct 2008</creation><particDesc><person id="P592" sex="m" age="TwentyToTwentyThree"><affiliation>Biochemistry</affiliation><firstLang>English</firstLang><dominantLang>English</dominantLang><englishInPrimarySchool value="NO"/><englishInSecondarySchool value="NO"/><englishInUndergraduate value="NO"/><langKnown>\N</langKnown></person></particDesc><textClass><catRef target="NRE G0 Critique LiteratureReview OneToThreeDays NoFeedback"><classification><primary>Critique/Evaluation</primary><secondary/></classification><classification><primary>Critique/Evaluation</primary><secondary/></classification><features><feature type="Abstract"/><feature type="Literature review section"/><feature type="Problem-solution pattern"/><feature type="Discussion of results section"/><feature type="Reference to sources"/></features></catRef></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change><date>2009-06-04</date><respStmt><name>Geoffrey Ho</name><resp>coder</resp></respStmt><item>manual adjustment of tags</item></change><change><date>2007-05-22</date><respStmt><name>Gregory Garretson</name><resp>programmer</resp></respStmt><item>initial (automated) encoding in XML</item></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="opener"><head>Acid Mine Drainage:  Effects and Possible Solutions</head><div type="abstract"><head>Abstract</head><p>AMD is catalyzed by a series of reactions that result in the conversion of sulfide in ore to become acid.  The acid causes great environmental damage, as seen in the Berkeley Pit in Butte, Montana.  The current methods of alleviating AMD pollution are all expensive and have drawbacks, and it is currently not economical to profit from extracting metal from the waste.  Currently, the best solution to the problem is to keep mining companies economically accountable for the environmental damage they cause.	</p></div></div><div type="main"><div type="head_1"><head>Outline</head><p>Introduction</p><p>-Acid Mine Drainage has caused much damage to the environment.</p><p>-Clean up of the acidic water could be made more efficient by turning it into a profitable process.</p><p>Literature Review</p><p>-Definition of AMD</p><p>	-source:  sulfide minerals, reactions, negative effects</p><p>-Example of the effects of AMD</p><p>	-Butte</p><p>	-Pennsylvania</p><p>Dicussion/Analysis</p><p>-current cleanup methods and drawbacks of each method for old mines</p><p>-possibility of profit in AMD cleanup</p><p>-prevention of AMD in new mines</p><p>	-alkalinity of surroundings slows AMD</p><p>	-government regulations that make firms accountable for damage</p></div><div type="head_1"><head>Introduction</head><p>Mining ore has been a very profitable process for many companies.  Until recently, however, most companies did not take into account the environmental costs of mining.  Acid Mine Drainage (AMD) is one of the negative effects of mining.  It has the potential to cause large amounts of irreversible damage to the surrounding environment.  It may be possible to make the cleanup of AMD profitable, but for now mining should be done with consideration for the surrounding environment.</p></div><div type="head_1"><head>Literature Review</head><p>Acid Mine Drainage (AMD) is a common form of water contamination from mines, where the water becomes much more acidic than normal.  It occurs when sulfide containing minerals, mostly commonly FeS or pyrite, are exposed to the surface.  Exposure can occur through natural weathering, but it is very common in mines because fresh minerals are frequently exposed to the surface.  Once the sulfide minerals reach the surface they react with oxygen in the air and water in the following reaction:</p><p>1. 2FeS(s) + 7O2(g) + 2H2O(l) →  2Fe2+ + 4SO42- +4H+ </p><p>In this reaction, four acidic protons are produced for every 2 molecules of FeS, which are part of the acid pollution.  However, the Fe2+ ions and the H+ can continue to react:</p><p>2. 4Fe2+(aq) + O2(g) + 4H+(aq) → 4Fe3+(aq) + 2H2O(l)
<lb/>3. 4Fe3+(aq) + 12H2O(l) →4Fe(OH)3(s) + 12H+(aq)
<lb/>4. 2FeS(s) + 14Fe3+(aq) + 8H2O(l) → 15Fe2+ + 2SO42- +16H+</p><p>   In Reaction 3, Fe3+ reacts with water to form a yellow precipitate and acid.  This yellow precipitate is referred to as yellowboy, and it discolors water systems and collects on the bottom of streams, which prevents the plant and animal life living there from obtaining oxygen.  The death of these organisms can disrupt entire ecosystems (Wikipedia, 2008).  However, if the pH of the water is below 3.5, Fe3+ will continue to react with FeS in reaction 4.  Oxygen is not required for this reaction, and it will continue until all FeS is depleted, which can cause a great increase in the pH of the surrounding environment (Growitz, 2002).  Once the pH of the surrounding environment gets low enough, it can dissolve the trace metals in the soil, some of which are toxic.  Once dissolved, these metals can get into surrounding streams and soil.  These metals, along with acid can act as poison for wildlife.  Aquifers and roads can also become damaged by the acid and metals.</p><p>   AMD has the potential to cause great damage to the surrounding environment.  AMD is a naturally occuring process that is a byproduct of weathering of rock (Kesler, 1994).  AMD form natural weathering does cause some stress on plant and animal life.  For example in areas where natural acid mine drainage occurs, leaves may fall from trees prematurely.  However, the effects anthropogenic AMD are far worse than the natural effects.</p><p>   The Berkeley Pit in Butte, Montana is an example of the true potential for AMD damage.  The mine was shut down in 1982, and so were the pumps that prevented flooding.  The pit is now flooded with water that is laced with much higher than average concentrations of multiple poisonous metals including aresenic, cadmium, and copper.  The water in the pit is so acidic that it killed 342 geese that landed in the pit to drink.  The water from this pit has leaked into the Clark Ford River and greatly increased its metal content.  Also, the water in the pit is predicted to eventually rise to the point where it will contaminate the groundwater in Butte (Dobb, 1996).  Pennsylvania, a state where much mining takes place, illustrates another problem from AMD.  There are many streams where aquatic life has been killed by yellowboy (Alcorn, 2007), the compound from reaction 3.  It is clear that a solution to AMD pollution is necessary.</p></div><div type="head_1"><head>Discussion/Analysis</head><p>Multiple methods of alleviating AMD in old mines that are no longer in use currently exist.  A common method is to neutralize the acid with substances such as limestone or neutralizing rock (Durkinl and Hermann, 1994).  The unfortunate side effect of neutralization methods is that they generate waste that must be disposed of (Dobb, 1996).  Another method is to introduce chemicals that kill bacteria that catalyze the acid generating reactions (Durkinl and Hermann, 1994).  However, this will not stop the reactions entirely, and it introduces other chemicals that have potential to be harmful to the environment.  Collection and treatment of the waste is a possible solution, where the waste is collected and treated with base additives or passed through a wetland, but  these methods are expensive and do not treat the source of the problem, only the symptoms (Durkinl and Hermann, 1994).  Another downfall of solutions is that they are expensive.  However, there is a less expensive option that follows from the idea of collection and treatment.</p><p>	The water is AMD collects metals from the soil, which means the water contains potential resources.  An ideal solution to AMD would be to extract metals from this water at a profit.  The company Metanetix attempted to do this in Butte, but was not able to make the process economical (Dobb, 1996).  However, if this were to become economical, it would give firms incentive to clean up AMD, and the firms would be responsible for the polluted land instead of the government or the surrounding community.  Research for extraction of metals from water should receive government funding.  There has already been success in making AMD waste useful at Bucknell University, where a professor made paint from yellowboy (Alcorn, 2007).  Until it becomes economical, it appears that the best available solution to AMD is to cover acid producing rocks with clay (Durkinl and Hermann, 1994).  </p><p>	New mines that will be mined in the future have another option for dealing with AMD.  A common method of decreasing the harmful effects of AMD is to add a basic material.  However, if mines were dug in areas that were high in alkalinity, then there would already be basic material present to neutralize the acid.  While this is a good concept, most companies will dig where ore is present, whether the surroundings are alkaline or not.  </p><p>	The best way to deal with AMD when there is little alkalinity present is to make firms responsible for cleanup during mining.  This will force firms to be responsible in their practices, and they will take the environmental costs of mining into account.  Responsible practices will prevent another environmental disaster like the one at Butte.  It is much more difficult to alleviate AMD once mining has stopped because damage has already taken place, and firms will try to escape their responsibility to the environment.  For now, prevention is the ideal solution.</p></div><div type="head_1"><head>Conclusion</head><p>Mining companies have made many mistakes in the past that have greatly damaged the environment.  However, this damage does not have to be in vain.  Prevention is an ideal solution to this problem.  While the Berkeley Pit and other mines may seem to be beyond repair, they have provided valuable information on the potential effects of mining.  The best way to clean up AMD in the future is to learn from past mistakes and use prevention.</p></div></div><div type="closer"><div type="bibliography"><head>References</head><listBibl><bibl>Alcorn, Sam (2007), Professor Paints a Bright Picture with ‘yellow boy’, http://www.bucknell.edu/x38124.xml</bibl><bibl>Dobb, Edwin (1996), Pennies From Hell, Harper’s Magazine, 39-54, https://ctools.umich.edu/access/content/group/5bf437c3-5148-4ad9-8a4b-467fd1755793/Writing%20Assignments/Writing%20Assignment%202/PenniesfromHell.pdf</bibl><bibl>Durkinl, Thomas V. and Hermann, Jonathan G (1994), Focusing on the Problem of Mining Wastes:  An Introduction to Acid Mine Drainage,  http://technology.infomine.com/enviromine/publicat/amdintro.html</bibl><bibl>Growitz, Doug (2002), Factors Controlling Acid Mine Drainage Formation, http://www.osmre.gov/amdform.htm</bibl><bibl>Kesler, Stephen E. (1994), Mineral Resources, Economics and the Environment, Macmillan College Publishing Company, Inc., New York</bibl><bibl>Wikipedia (2008), “Acid Mine Drainage”, http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Acid_mine_drainage, viewed on Oct. 14, 2008</bibl></listBibl></div></div></body></text></TEI.2>