<TEI.2><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Degredation of the Mesoamerican Reef</title><author>anonymized</author></titleStmt><wordcount>2708</wordcount><editionStmt><edition>Version 1.0</edition></editionStmt><extent>insert_extent</extent><publicationStmt><idno>NRE.G2.04.1</idno><publisher>The University of Michigan</publisher><pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan, USA</pubPlace><date>2007</date><availability><p>The MICUSP project is owned by the Regents of the University of Michigan, who hold the copyright. The database has been developed by the English Language Institute. The original text submissions are stored electronically in the English Language Institute and may be consulted by bona fide researchers under special arrangements. The database is available by password on the World Wide Web for study, teaching and research purposes. Copies of the text files may be distributed, as long as either this statement of availability or the citation given below appears in the text. However, if any portion of this material is to be used for commercial purposes, such as for textbooks or tests, permission must be obtained in advance and a license fee may be required. For further information about copyright permissions, please inquire at micusp@umich.edu.</p><p>The recommended citation for MICASE is: Ädel, A., J. M. Swales, and J. Sielaff. (2007) The Michigan Corpus of Upper-level Student Papers. Ann Arbor, MI: The Regents of the University of Michigan.</p></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>The Michigan Corpus of Upper-level Student Papers (MICUSP)</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><p>This document derives from an unpublished, student-authored paper contributed in electronic format.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>For information on corpus compilation and encoding practices, see the MICUSP Handbook.</p></projectDesc><classDecl><taxonomy><category><catDesc>departments</catDesc><category id="BIO"><catDesc>Biology</catDesc></category><category id="CEE"><catDesc>Civil and Environmental Engineering</catDesc></category><category id="CLS"><catDesc>Classical Studies</catDesc></category><category id="ECO"><catDesc>Economics</catDesc></category><category id="EDU"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category id="ENG"><catDesc>English</catDesc></category><category id="IOE"><catDesc>Industrial and Operational Engineering</catDesc></category><category id="LIN"><catDesc>Linguistics</catDesc></category><category id="MEC"><catDesc>Mechanical Engineering</catDesc></category><category id="NRE"><catDesc>Natural Resources</catDesc></category><category id="NUR"><catDesc>Nursing</catDesc></category><category id="PHI"><catDesc>Philosophy</catDesc></category><category id="PHY"><catDesc>Physics</catDesc></category><category id="POL"><catDesc>Political Science</catDesc></category><category id="PSY"><catDesc>Psychology</catDesc></category><category id="SOC"><catDesc>Sociology</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>student levels</catDesc><category id="G0"><catDesc>senior undergraduate</catDesc></category><category id="G1"><catDesc>first-year graduate</catDesc></category><category id="G2"><catDesc>second-year graduate</catDesc></category><category id="G3"><catDesc>third-year graduate and up</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>student-reported text types</catDesc><category id="CaseStudy"><catDesc>case study</catDesc></category><category id="Critique"><catDesc>critique</catDesc></category><category id="LiteratureReview"><catDesc>literature review</catDesc></category><category id="ResearchProposal"><catDesc>research proposal</catDesc></category><category id="ResponsePaper"><catDesc>response paper</catDesc></category><category id="TechnicalOrLabReport"><catDesc>technical report or lab report</catDesc></category><category id="TermPaper"><catDesc>term paper</catDesc></category><category id="OtherTextType"><catDesc>other</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>approximate preparation times</catDesc><category id="OneToThreeDays"><catDesc>1-3 days</catDesc></category><category id="FourToTenDays"><catDesc>4-10 days</catDesc></category><category id="TwoToThreeWeeks"><catDesc>2-3 weeks</catDesc></category><category id="ThreeToSixWeeks"><catDesc>3-6 weeks</catDesc></category><category id="OneFullSemester"><catDesc>one full semester</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>sources of feedback</catDesc><category id="NoFeedback"><catDesc>no feedback from others</catDesc></category><category id="PrimaryInstructor"><catDesc>primary course instructor</catDesc></category><category id="GSI"><catDesc>Graduate Student Instructor (teaching assistant)</catDesc></category><category id="WritingTutor"><catDesc>writing tutor</catDesc></category><category id="FriendOrClassmate"><catDesc>friend or classmate</catDesc></category><category id="OtherFeedback"><catDesc>other</catDesc></category></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><creation>Paper submitted to instructor in Feb 2008</creation><particDesc><person id="P538" sex="f" age="TwentyFourToThirty"><affiliation>Natural Resources </affiliation><firstLang>English</firstLang><dominantLang>English</dominantLang><englishInPrimarySchool value="YES"/><englishInSecondarySchool value="YES"/><englishInUndergraduate value="YES"/></person></particDesc><textClass><catRef target="NRE G2 Report CaseStudy OneToThreeDays NoFeedback"><classification><primary>Report</primary><secondary/></classification><classification><primary>Report</primary><secondary/></classification><features><feature type="Problem-solution pattern"/><feature type="Tables, graphs or figures"/><feature type="Reference to sources"/></features></catRef></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change><date>2008-12-15</date><respStmt><name>Emily Lin</name><resp>coder</resp></respStmt><item>manual adjustment of tags</item></change><change><date>2007-05-22</date><respStmt><name>Gregory Garretson</name><resp>programmer</resp></respStmt><item>initial (automated) encoding in XML</item></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="opener"><head>﻿Degradation of the Mesoamerican Barrier Reef</head><p/></div><div type="main"><div type="head_1"><head>Overview</head><p>	The Mesoamerican Barrier Reef System (MBRS),<ptr type="footnote" target="f1"/> which stretches 700 miles from the tip of the Yucatan Peninsula to the Bay Islands of Honduras, is the second largest barrier reef in the world (Figure 1). This reef and its associated ecosystems host some of the richest biodiversity in the Caribbean as well as one of the fastest growing tourism industries in the world.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn1"/> Over the past 20 years, increasing pressure from a number of region-wide threats has degraded the appearance and structure of the reef.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn2"/></p><p>Figure 1: The Mesoamerican Reef (from the WWF Website) </p><gap desc="figure"/><p>Major threats to the MBRS include overfishing, land-based water pollution, rapidly expanding tourism, and climate change.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn3"/><ptr type="footnote" target="fn4"/> Connected as it is by currents and mobile reef species, even localized damage to segments of the reef can have regional impacts.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn5"/> The reef is also subject to natural threats such as hurricanes and coral disease, vulnerability to which can be heightened by anthropogenic stressors.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn6"/></p><p>The four countries bordering the reef – Mexico, Belize, Guatemala, and Honduras- have significantly differing capacities for monitoring and management of the reef in the face of these threats.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn7"/> Since 1997, however, they have collaborated to develop a regional approach to the conservation of the MBRS.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn8"/> The reef system is also considered a global conservation priority by numerous NGOs.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn9"/> Despite these efforts, the system remains at significant risk.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn10"/></p></div><div type="head_1"><head>History of Regional and International MRBS Protection Efforts</head><p>	The MBRS is of immense importance to the countries along whose coastlines it stretches, serving as it does as a buffer from hurricanes, a shelter for economically and culturally important fish species, and a source of significant tourism revenue. Approximately a million people in the region benefit directly from the fisheries, tourism, and coastal development associated with the MBRS.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn11"/> In Belize, economic activity around the reef makes up approximately 30 percent of the gross national product.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn12"/> It is thus not surprising, that, while monitoring and enforcement capacity remain an issue, the MBRS nations have actively sought to mitigate threats to the reef.</p><p>	Prior to establishment of regional coordination in the late 1990s, Mexico and Belize had the most fully developed management systems, with Honduras and Guatemala having few laws regulating the use of reefs.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn13"/> In Honduras, community based management efforts emerged to fill this gap in national capacity.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn14"/>  Then, as now, monitoring and enforcement varied and reliance on international funding and NGO management was significant.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn15"/></p><p>	In 1997, two years after the first recorded instance of mass coral bleaching (a sign of intense reef stress), the four bordering nations signed the Tulum Declaration outlining their intent to collaborate towards the sustainable use of the MBRS and to seek international support for regionally-focused efforts.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn16"/><ptr type="footnote" target="fn17"/>  This declaration set the stage for numerous regionally focused efforts to come, most directly the launch of the MBRS Project in 2001. This fifteen year project is funded by the Global Environment Facility (GEF) and implemented by the Central American Commission on Environment and Development (CCAD), which is made up of the environment ministers of the seven Central American countries. The MBRS project is focused on the establishment and institutional strengthening of Marine Protected Areas, the promotion of sustainable fisheries and tourism, and the establishment of a region-wide environmental monitoring system.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn18"/></p><p>In addition to the GEF, funding for transnational MBRS projects comes from a variety of regional and international sources. The U.S. Based Summit foundation  The   Four in-country foundations formed the Mesoamerican Reef Fund (MAR Fund), in 2002, to provide <q type="quote">long term financial sustainability</q> for MBRS conservation efforts which might otherwise depend on potentially inconsistent support from international groups.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn19"/> In 2003, the United Nations Foundation and U.S. Agency for International Development pledged three million dollars to contribute to <q type="quote">local, national, and regional-level resource conservation and sustainable development projects</q> in the MBRS region.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn20"/> This pledge funded the three-year International Coral Reef Action Network– Mesoamerican Reef Aliance (ICRAN-MAR) project, which concluded in the summer of 2007.</p><p>	In addition to those organizations listed above, the World Wildlife Fund for Nature (WWF), the Nature Conservancy, Wildlife Conservation Society, Conservation International, the Coral Reef Alliance, World Conservation Union, and numerous local NGOs also all run projects specifically targeted at the MBRS. Given this array of institutions and programs at work in the region it is little wonder that the coordination of these efforts, and the avoidance of duplicate work, has been called a <q type="quote">major challenge.</q><ptr type="footnote" target="fn21"/></p></div><div type="head_1"><head>Approaches to Mitigating Threats</head><div type="head_2"><head>Improving monitoring capacity </head><p>	The expansion and coordination of environmental monitoring, and resulting improvements in understanding of the MBRS, that has taken place over the last decade is considered one of the bright spots in the current prognosis for the reef, though monitoring capacity remains weak in some areas.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn22"/> The MBRS Project's Synoptic Monitoring Program coordinates environmental monitoring of the reef and associated ecosystems (such as mangroves and other wetlands) for the region, providing guidance and training to promote standardized monitoring. <ptr type="footnote" target="fn23"/> To complement this effort, an array of non-governmental organizations collaborated with the MRBS project to create the Health People Healthy Reefs initiative, a multi-institutional effort to develop and track ecological and socio-economic indicators for the MBRS. Partners in this effort include the MRBRS program, the World Bank, WWF, the Nature Conservancy, Environmental Defense, and the Smithsonian Institute.</p></div><div type="head_2"><head>Protecting Fish and Improving Regulations</head><p>	The influx of tourists and their appetite for conch, lobster, and reef fish has significantly increased fishing pressure in the MBRS region, and particularly in the rapidly developing coastal sections of Honduras.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn24"/> This overfishing problem has been approached through the use of fishing regulations and MPAs, both of which are established management tools in all MBRS countries.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn25"/>  Monitoring and enforcement of both fishing regulations and no-take zones in MPAs are, however, inconsistent due to limited monitoring and enforcement capacities.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn26"/></p><p>	All of the international environmental organizations working in the MBRS are addressing overfishing in some way, whether by seeking to enhance the strength of MPA management, training fishermen for alternative occupations, or providing education on fisheries issues to affected communities.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn27"/> WWF, working in conjunction with the ICRAN-USAID program, has been holding meetings with fishing communities in all four MAR countries to encourage acceptance of regulations and no-take zones. There are signs that outreach and education efforts are working. A 2002 survey pole in Belize showed that 45 percent of fishermen approved of marine protected areas as a management tool; by 2004 that number had increased to 75 percent.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn28"/>  In 2004, the MBRS nations also took the important step of harmonizing their regulations, which should make the standardization of both training and enforcement a possibility.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn29"/></p></div><div type="head_2"><head>Understanding and Reducing Land-based Pollution</head><p>	Currently over 300,000 hectares of land has been converted to agricultural use in the MAR watershed. Sediments, nutrients, and chemicals that drain from these areas pose a significant risk to near-shore sections of the reef. <ptr type="footnote" target="fn30"/> A 2005 report commissioned by several large environmental NGOS, described the lack of coordinated strategies to address watershed development was described as one of the major gaps in MBRS conservation.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn31"/>  In 2006, the World Resources Institute undertook a watershed analysis of the MBRS region in order to facilitate strategic efforts to reduce land-based pollution. The report found that 80 percent of the sediments, and over half of the nutrients, reaching the MBRS originate in Honduras, with Guatemala also a significant contributor of nutrients.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn32"/></p><p>	ICRAN has funded WWF to lead collaborative work with agro-business and local farmers to reduce the use of pesticides and to control erosion in the MAR watershed.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn33"/> As a result of this work several major agricultural producers, including Dole and Chiquita, are implementing a plan to reduce environmental exposure to the most toxic pesticides.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn34"/> WWF also recently signed an agreement with African oil palm producers in Honduras to jointly work towards the implementation of best management practices.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn35"/> The threat of nutrient pollution from shrimp farming to the MBRS is also receiving increasing attention and has become a priority issue for the Summit Foundation and WWF.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn36"/> Work is underway to both better understand the affects of shrimp farming on the reef and to incentivize better practices through certification programs.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn37"/></p></div><div type="head_2"><head>Reducing the Impact of Tourism</head><p>	The tourism industry which has sprung up along the MAR is one of the fastest growing in the world.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn38"/> This is both one of the great hopes for the reef – offering real economic incentives for conservation and non-consumptive employment opportunities- and a significant threat to the ecosystem.  Release of wastes by cruises hips and hotels, destruction of reef by careless snorklers and divers, and fragmentation of habitat due to coastal development are all considered key issues.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn39"/> In 2006, Conservation International and the Coral Reef Alliance formed the Mesoamerican Reef Tourism Initiative (MARTI) to address the threat of mass tourism to the reef.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn40"/>  MARTI has worked with the International Council of Cruise Lines to secure an agreement that ships will discharge waste water no fewer than four miles from the reef.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn41"/>  They are also working with hotels in Mexico and Belize to reduce solid wastes and improve the management of chemicals.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn42"/></p></div><div type="head_2"><head>Enhancing Resilience to Climate Change</head><p>	In 1995, 1998 and 2005, unusually warm temperatures caused significant coral bleaching events throughout the world. The 2005 event, which was the most sever bleaching recorded in the Caribbean, caused the bleaching of up to 95% of corals in the most significantly impacted areas. The cooling of water by storm events during 2005 spared the Mesoamerican reef from the large-scale coral mortality experienced in other parts of the Caribbean, but it might be considered a harbinger of things to come for the MBRS.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn43"/></p><p>	To address this threat, WWF and TNC have conducted an assessment of the MAR and identified, and is promoting the protection of, bleaching resilient and bleaching resistant reefs. The MBRS Synoptic Monitoring Protocol made monitoring for climate-influenced bleaching events a priority.<ptr type="footnote" target="fn44"/></p><list><head>List of particularly helpful resources (full citations are in endnotes)</head><item>• Alejandro Arrivillaga and Miguel Angel Garcia (2004), <q type="title">Status of Coral Reefs of the Mesoamerican Barrier Reef System Project Region, and Reefs of El Salvador, Nicaragua, and the Pacific Coasts of Mesoamerica</q></item><item>• Patricia ALmada-Villela et al (2002), Status of Coral Reefs of Mesoamerica- Mexico, Belize, Guatemala, Hondusas, Nicaragua, and El Salvador</item><item>• Maya Gorrez, Building Synergies in the Mesoamerican Reef (report was commissioned by WWF, MRBS project, the Nature Conservancy, and the Summit Foundation)</item><item>• ICRAN MAR Alliance Terminal Report </item><item>• MBRS project website (explains details of Tulum Declaration and hosts policy documents and agreements)</item></list></div></div></div><div type="closer"><div type="footnotes"><note type="footnote" id="f1">1 Also known simply as the Mesoamerican Barrier Reef (MAR)</note><note type="footnote" id="fn1">i Arrivillaga, Alejandro and Miguel Angel Garcia, "Status of Coral Reefs of the Mesoamerican Barrier Reef System Project Region, and Reefs of El Salvador, Nicaragua, and the Pacific Coasts of Mesoamerica," in Status of the Worlds Coral Reefs: 2004. C. Wilkinson ed. Page 475</note><note type="footnote" id="fn2">ii Arrivillaga, Alejandro and Miguel Angel Garcia, "Status of Coral Reefs of the Mesoamerican Barrier Reef System Project Region, and Reefs of El Salvador, Nicaragua, and the Pacific Coasts of Mesoamerica," in Status of the Worlds Coral Reefs: 2004. C. Wilkinson ed. Page 473</note><note type="footnote" id="fn3">iii Arrivillaga, Alejandro and Miguel Angel Garcia, (2004 "Status of Coral Reefs of the Mesoamerican Barrier Reef System Project Region, and Reefs of El Salvador, Nicaragua, and the Pacific Coasts of Mesoamerica," in Status of the Worlds Coral Reefs. C. Wilkinson ed. Page 473</note><note type="footnote" id="fn4">iv Wilkinson, C., Souter, D. (2008). Status of Caribbean coral reefs after bleaching and hurricanes in 2005. Global Coral Reef Monitoring Network, and Reef and Rainforest Research Centre, Townsville, 16</note><note type="footnote" id="fn5">v Harborne, Alastair, Daniel Afzal, Mark Andrews (2001). Honduras: Caribbean Coast, Marine Pollution Bulletin. Vol 42, No 12, page 1221</note><note type="footnote" id="fn6">vi Arrivillaga, Alejandro and Miguel Angel Garcia, (2004) "Status of Coral Reefs of the Mesoamerican Barrier Reef System Project Region, and Reefs of El Salvador, Nicaragua, and the Pacific Coasts of Mesoamerica," in Status of the Worlds Coral Reefs. C. Wilkinson ed. Page 486</note><note type="footnote" id="fn7">vii Arrivillaga, Alejandro and Miguel Angel Garcia, (2004) "Status of Coral Reefs of the Mesoamerican Barrier Reef System Project Region, and Reefs of El Salvador, Nicaragua, and the Pacific Coasts of Mesoamerica," in Status of the Worlds Coral Reefs. C. Wilkinson ed. Page 475</note><note type="footnote" id="fn8">viii Mesoamerican Reef System Project, Project Background, June 15, 2005. http://www.mbrs.org.bz/english/projdesc.htm (accessed February 18, 2008)</note><note type="footnote" id="fn9">ix Wilkinson, C., Souter, D. (2008). Status of Caribbean coral reefs after bleaching and hurricanes in 2005. Global Coral Reef Monitoring Network, and Reef and Rainforest Research Centre, Townsville, 46</note><note type="footnote" id="fn10">x Wilkinson, C., Souter, D. (2008). Status of Caribbean coral reefs after bleaching and hurricanes in 2005. Global Coral Reef Monitoring Network, and Reef and Rainforest Research Centre, Townsville, 22</note><note type="footnote" id="fn11">xi Almada-Villela, P.C, P.F. Sale, G. Gold-Bouchot, and B. Kjefve (2003). Manual of Methods for the MBRS Synoptic Monitoring Program. Mesoamerican Barrier Reef Systems Project, Belize City, Belize, v </note><note type="footnote" id="fn12">xii Cho, Leandra (2005). "Marine Protected Areas: a tool for integrated coastal management in Belize." Ocean and Coastal Management, vol. 48, Issue 11. page 1.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn13">xiii P. Almada-Villela et al., "Status of Coral Reefs of Mesoamerica," in Status of Coral Reefs of the World: 2002. C. Wilkinson, ed. (Townsville: Australian Institute of Marine Science, 2002), 317</note><note type="footnote" id="fn14">xiv Luttinger, Nina (1997). "Community-based Coral Reef Conservation in the Bay Islands of Honduras."Ocean and Coastal Management. Vol. 36, Nos 1-3. Page 13</note><note type="footnote" id="fn15">xv P. Almada-Villela et al., <quote>Status of Coral Reefs of Mesoamerica,</quote> in Status of Coral Reefs of the World: 2002. C. Wilkinson, ed. (Townsville: Australian Institute of Marine Science, 2002), 317</note><note type="footnote" id="fn16">xvi Wilkinson, C., Souter, D. (2008). Status of Caribbean coral reefs after bleaching and hurricanes in 2005. Global Coral Reef Monitoring Network, and Reef and Rainforest Research Centre, Townsville, 46</note><note type="footnote" id="fn17">xvii MBRS Project, Project Background (2005) http://www.mbrs.org.bz/english/projdesc.htm (accessed February 17, 2008)</note><note type="footnote" id="fn18">xviii MBRS Project, Project Background (2005) http://www.mbrs.org.bz/english/projdesc.htm (accessed February 17, 2008)</note><note type="footnote" id="fn19">xix MAR Fund, About MAR  Fund Founding Members http://www.marfund.org/marfundmembers.html (accessed February 19, 2008)</note><note type="footnote" id="fn20">xx ICRAN Mesoamerican Reef Alliance (2007), Terminal Report Executive Summary. page 2.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn21">xxi Arrivillaga, Alejandro and Miguel Angel Garcia, (2004), Page 489</note><note type="footnote" id="fn22">xxii Arrivillaga, Alejandro and Miguel Angel Garcia, (2004), Page 474</note><note type="footnote" id="fn23">xxiii Arrivillaga, Alejandro and Miguel Angel Garcia, (2004), Page 474</note><note type="footnote" id="fn24">xxiv</note><note type="footnote" id="fn25">xxv Central American Commission on Environment and Development (2004), the Agreement on Common Enforcements in the Mesoamerican Barrier Reef System Geographical Area </note><note type="footnote" id="fn26">xxvi Arrivillaga, Alejandro and Miguel Angel Garcia, (2004) "Status of Coral Reefs of the Mesoamerican Barrier Reef System Project Region, and Reefs of El Salvador, Nicaragua, and the Pacific Coasts of Mesoamerica," in Status of the Worlds Coral Reefs. C. Wilkinson ed. Page 484</note><note type="footnote" id="fn27">xxvii Gorrez, Maya (October, 2005), Building Synergies in the Mesoamerican Reef, page 6</note><note type="footnote" id="fn28">xxviii Arrivillaga, Alejandro and Miguel Angel Garcia, (2004) "Status of Coral Reefs of the Mesoamerican Barrier Reef System Project Region, and Reefs of El Salvador, Nicaragua, and the Pacific Coasts of Mesoamerica," in Status of the Worlds Coral Reefs. C. Wilkinson ed. Page 475</note><note type="footnote" id="fn29">xxix Central American Commission on Environment and Development (2004), the Agreement on Common Enforcements in the Mesoamerican Barrier Reef System Geographical Area </note><note type="footnote" id="fn30">xxx Burke, Lauretta and Zachary Sugg (December 1, 2005) Hydrologic Modeling of Watershed Discharge Adjacent to the Mesoamerican Reef. World Resources Institute. Page 1</note><note type="footnote" id="fn31">xxxi Gorrez, Maya (October, 2005), Building Synergies in the Mesoamerican Reef </note><note type="footnote" id="fn32">xxxii Burke, Lauretta and Zachary Sugg (December 1, 2005) Hydrologic Modeling of Watershed Discharge Adjacent to the Mesoamerican Reef. World Resources Institute. Page 3</note><note type="footnote" id="fn33">xxxiii ICRAN Mesoamerican Reef Alliance (2007). Terminal Report Executive Summary.  Page 4.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn34">xxxiv ICRAN Mesoamerican Reef Alliance (2007). Terminal Report Executive Summary.  Page 4.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn35">xxxv International Coral Reef Action Network (June 27, 2007). "Coral Reefs Protected by Sustainable Agriculture." http://www.icriforum.org/List/Thread.cfm?MessageID=2269 (Accessed February 19, 2008).</note><note type="footnote" id="fn36">xxxvi The Summit Foundation, Program Areas- Conservation of the Mesoamerican Reef http://www.summitfdn.org/foundation/programs/reef-conservation.html (accessed February 19,2008)</note><note type="footnote" id="fn37">xxxvii WWF, Aquaculture – Featured Projects: Shrimp Aquaculture in Belize http://www.worldwildlife.org/cci/aquaculture_projects2.cfm (Accessed February 19,2008).</note><note type="footnote" id="fn38">xxxviii Arrivillaga, Alejandro and Miguel Angel Garcia, (2004) "Status of Coral Reefs of the Mesoamerican Barrier Reef System Project Region, and Reefs of El Salvador, Nicaragua, and the Pacific Coasts of Mesoamerica," in Status of the Worlds Coral Reefs. C. Wilkinson ed. Page 475</note><note type="footnote" id="fn39">xxxix The Summit Foundation Mesoamerican Reef Program (2004), Report from the Field http://www.summitfdn.org/foundation/pdfs/field-report.pdf (accessed February 19, 2008)</note><note type="footnote" id="fn40">xl Conservation International (2006), The Mesoamerican Reef Tourism Initiative fact sheet http://www.celb.org/ImageCache/CELB/content/downloads/pdf/marti_5ffactsheet_2epdf/v1/marti_5ffactsheet.pdf (accessed February 19,2008.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn41">xli NYTImes</note><note type="footnote" id="fn42">xlii Tsui, Bonnie, , "Saving Coral Reefs Becomes A Tourism Priority," New York Times (June 24, 2007). file:///C:/Documents%20and%20Settings/LaurenP/My%20Documents/Winter%2008/INt%20Law%20and%20Policy/Second%20short%20paper/24headsup.html (Accessed February 17, 2008)</note><note type="footnote" id="fn43">xliii Wilkinson, C., Souter, D. (2008). Status of Caribbean coral reefs after bleaching and hurricanes in 2005. Global Coral Reef Monitoring Network, and Reef and Rainforest Research Centre, Townsville, 5.</note><note type="footnote" id="fn44">xliv Gorrez, Maya (October, 2005), Building Synergies in the Mesoamerican Reef, page 10</note></div></div></body></text></TEI.2>