<TEI.2><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Race and the Frequency of Developing Type II Diabetes</title><author>anonymized</author></titleStmt><wordcount>508</wordcount><editionStmt><edition>Version 1.0</edition></editionStmt><extent>insert_extent</extent><publicationStmt><idno>SOC.G0.06.1</idno><publisher>The University of Michigan</publisher><pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan, USA</pubPlace><date>2007</date><availability><p>The MICUSP project is owned by the Regents of the University of Michigan, who hold the copyright. The database has been developed by the English Language Institute. The original text submissions are stored electronically in the English Language Institute and may be consulted by bona fide researchers under special arrangements. The database is available by password on the World Wide Web for study, teaching and research purposes. Copies of the text files may be distributed, as long as either this statement of availability or the citation given below appears in the text. However, if any portion of this material is to be used for commercial purposes, such as for textbooks or tests, permission must be obtained in advance and a license fee may be required. For further information about copyright permissions, please inquire at micusp@umich.edu.</p><p>The recommended citation for MICASE is: Ädel, A., J. M. Swales, and J. Sielaff. (2007) The Michigan Corpus of Upper-level Student Papers. Ann Arbor, MI: The Regents of the University of Michigan.</p></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>The Michigan Corpus of Upper-level Student Papers (MICUSP)</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><p>This document derives from an unpublished, student-authored paper contributed in electronic format.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>For information on corpus compilation and encoding practices, see the MICUSP Handbook.</p></projectDesc><classDecl><taxonomy><category><catDesc>departments</catDesc><category id="BIO"><catDesc>Biology</catDesc></category><category id="CEE"><catDesc>Civil and Environmental Engineering</catDesc></category><category id="CLS"><catDesc>Classical Studies</catDesc></category><category id="ECO"><catDesc>Economics</catDesc></category><category id="EDU"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category id="ENG"><catDesc>English</catDesc></category><category id="IOE"><catDesc>Industrial and Operational Engineering</catDesc></category><category id="LIN"><catDesc>Linguistics</catDesc></category><category id="MEC"><catDesc>Mechanical Engineering</catDesc></category><category id="NRE"><catDesc>Natural Resources</catDesc></category><category id="NUR"><catDesc>Nursing</catDesc></category><category id="PHI"><catDesc>Philosophy</catDesc></category><category id="PHY"><catDesc>Physics</catDesc></category><category id="POL"><catDesc>Political Science</catDesc></category><category id="PSY"><catDesc>Psychology</catDesc></category><category id="SOC"><catDesc>Sociology</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>student levels</catDesc><category id="G0"><catDesc>senior undergraduate</catDesc></category><category id="G1"><catDesc>first-year graduate</catDesc></category><category id="G2"><catDesc>second-year graduate</catDesc></category><category id="G3"><catDesc>third-year graduate and up</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>student-reported text types</catDesc><category id="CaseStudy"><catDesc>case study</catDesc></category><category id="Critique"><catDesc>critique</catDesc></category><category id="LiteratureReview"><catDesc>literature review</catDesc></category><category id="ResearchProposal"><catDesc>research proposal</catDesc></category><category id="ResponsePaper"><catDesc>response paper</catDesc></category><category id="TechnicalOrLabReport"><catDesc>technical report or lab report</catDesc></category><category id="TermPaper"><catDesc>term paper</catDesc></category><category id="OtherTextType"><catDesc>other</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>approximate preparation times</catDesc><category id="OneToThreeDays"><catDesc>1-3 days</catDesc></category><category id="FourToTenDays"><catDesc>4-10 days</catDesc></category><category id="TwoToThreeWeeks"><catDesc>2-3 weeks</catDesc></category><category id="ThreeToSixWeeks"><catDesc>3-6 weeks</catDesc></category><category id="OneFullSemester"><catDesc>one full semester</catDesc></category></category><category><catDesc>sources of feedback</catDesc><category id="NoFeedback"><catDesc>no feedback from others</catDesc></category><category id="PrimaryInstructor"><catDesc>primary course instructor</catDesc></category><category id="GSI"><catDesc>Graduate Student Instructor (teaching assistant)</catDesc></category><category id="WritingTutor"><catDesc>writing tutor</catDesc></category><category id="FriendOrClassmate"><catDesc>friend or classmate</catDesc></category><category id="OtherFeedback"><catDesc>other</catDesc></category></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><creation>Paper submitted to instructor in Oct 2006</creation><particDesc><person id="P132" sex="m" age="TwentyToTwentyThree"><affiliation>Organizational Studies</affiliation><firstLang>English</firstLang><dominantLang>English</dominantLang><englishInPrimarySchool value="YES"/><englishInSecondarySchool value="YES"/><englishInUndergraduate value="YES"/></person></particDesc><textClass><catRef target="SOC G0 Report ResearchProposal OneToThreeDays GSI"><classification><primary>Report</primary><secondary/></classification><classification><primary>Report</primary><secondary/></classification><features><feature type="Definitions"/><feature type="Problem-solution pattern"/><feature type="Discussion of results section"/></features></catRef></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change><date>2007-12-18</date><respStmt><name>Yung-Hui Chien</name><resp>coder</resp></respStmt><item>manual adjustment of tags</item></change><change><date>2009-8-13</date><respStmt><name>Beilei Zhang</name><resp>coder</resp></respStmt><item>manual adjustment of tags</item></change><change><date>2007-05-22</date><respStmt><name>Gregory Garretson</name><resp>programmer</resp></respStmt><item>initial (automated) encoding in XML</item></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="opener"><head>Race and the Frequency of Developing Type II Diabetes</head><p/></div><div type="main"><p>Diabetes and its treatment remains a hot topic with the medical community within the U.S. and the rest of the world.  Type II Diabetes, or developed insulin resistance, is one of the fastest growing diseases within the developed world.  There are an estimated 20.1 million diabetics in the U.S. and, in addition, 41 million citizens are considered prediabetic.   Throughout the entire world, type II diabetes has been consistently growing, however at different rates among different ethnic groups.  While obesity has been linked to the occurrence of type II diabetes, U.S. statistics show that the frequency of diabetics is almost twice as likely in African Americans as in Caucasians or Hispanics, regardless of weight.</p><p>Because diabetes is a growing problem, both nationally and internationally, it is a disease that is both well researched and well funded.  Pharmaceutical companies spend billions of dollars developing new drugs and treatments to try to curb the development of type II diabetes and also create new medications to help treat the condition.  As more developing countries advance and as the <q type="soCalled">western culture</q> of obesity persists throughout the world, this issue is only going to become more salient and costly, both financially and in total lose of life.  How biological variation effects diabetes and its onset is of great importance yet comparatively little understanding compared to cultural reasons.</p><p>If genetic variation is linked to the onset and risk of developing type II diabetes this could have drastic effects on how diabetes prevention is developed and promoted as well as what kind of research goes into discovering cures and treatments.  Jorge Calles-Escandon M.D., an associate professor of endocrinology at Wake Forest University Baptist Medical Center, said <q type="quote">… black women may need to be evaluated and treated for insulin resistance and cardiovascular disease even at weight not considered obese by current standards.</q>  Further studies are being done on race and gender and its correlation to type II diabetes.</p><p>Because race is a socially created concept and one of great importance and differentiation in the U.S., how it is viewed will greatly play into future research of diabetes.  While genetic variation does cause differing levels of risk for developing type II diabetes, pigeon-holing these ideas into race can have negative consequences on effective research and treatment of the disease.  Specific treatments or life-style changes that will help prevent or curb the disease could be brought on to different people depending on color of skin instead of truly genetic differentiation.  Entire populations of people within the U.S. could be treated and diagnosed differently along with given different advice as to prevent and treat the disease as others.  While an individualize approach is warranted to each case, typifying best practices to avoid this ever increasingly common illness into racial categories can only lead to discriminator diagnosing and treatment of the disease in the future.  Until society accepts genetic variation beyond that of race as a link to type II diabetes, increasing problems and frequency of the disease are likely to occur.</p></div><div type="closer"><p/></div></body></text></TEI.2>